<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>OSDev Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>wikidb</dbname>
    <base>https://wiki.osdev.org/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.39.7</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">OSDev Wiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">OSDev Wiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>UEFI</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2924</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30311</id>
      <parentid>30019</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-17T18:56:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Makaroneder</username>
        <id>1943</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Replace source tag with syntaxhighlight tag</comment>
      <origin>30311</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="43568" sha1="o9l950k51r5nmksxsfcth17pqfo58eq" xml:space="preserve">(U)EFI or (Unified) Extensible Firmware Interface is a specification for x86, x86-64, ARM, and Itanium platforms that defines a software interface between the operating system and the platform firmware/BIOS. The original EFI was developed in the mid-1990s by Intel for use developing firmware/BIOS for Itanium platforms. In 2005 Intel transitioned the specification to a new working group called the Unified EFI Forum, consisting of companies such as AMD, Microsoft, Apple, and Intel itself. All modern PCs ship with UEFI firmware and UEFI is widely supported by both commercial and open source operating systems. Backwards compatibility is provided for legacy operating systems.

== UEFI basics ==

===Downloading UEFI images===
If you choose [[VirtualBox]] for virtualization, then UEFI is already included, no need to download the image manually. You just have to enable it in the VM's preferences by clicking "Settings" / "Systems" / "Enable EFI (special OSes only)" checkbox.

Otherwise for emulation and virtual machines, you'll need an OVMF.fd firmware image. It might be tricky to find, so here are some alternative download links too:
* [https://github.com/tianocore/tianocore.github.io/wiki/OVMF TianoCore Download] (official link)
* [https://github.com/BlankOn/ovmf-blobs OVMF-blobs] (unofficial precompiled 32 bit and 64 bit versions, easy to use)
* [https://www.kraxel.org/repos/ RPM packages] (official TianoCore packages)
* [https://packages.debian.org/sid/ovmf Debian packages]
* [https://packages.gentoo.org/useflags/ovmf Gentoo packages]
* [https://archlinux.org/packages/extra/any/edk2/ Arch packages]

Under Linux, you can also install these with your distro's package manager, for example:

'''Debian / Ubuntu'''
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
# apt-get install ovmf
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

'''RedHat / CentOS'''
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
# yum install ovmf
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

'''MacOS'''

Use the OVMF-blobs repo.

'''Windows'''

Use the OVMF-blobs repo or download the RPM version, then use ''7-Zip File Manager'' to extract the OVMF.fd file from the downloaded archive.

===UEFI vs. legacy BIOS===
A common misconception is that UEFI and BIOS are mutually exclusive. In reality, both legacy motherboards and UEFI-based motherboards both include BIOS ROMs. The differences are in where they find the bootloader/OS, how they prepare the system before executing it, and what convenience functions they provide.

====Platform initialization====
On a legacy system, the [[BIOS]] performs all the usual platform initialization (memory controller configuration, [[PCI]] bus configuration and BAR mapping, graphics card initialization, etc.), but then drops into a backwards-compatible [[Real Mode|real mode]] environment. The bootloader must enable the [[A20 Line|A20 gate]], configure a [[GDT]] and an [[IDT]], switch to [[protected mode]], and for x86-64 CPUs, configure paging and switch to [[x86-64|long mode]].

UEFI firmware performs those same steps, but it also enables the A20 gate and prepares either protected mode environment with flat [[segmentation]] (for 32-bit x86 processors) or a long mode environment with identity-mapped paging (for x86-64 processors).

Additionally, the platform initialization procedure of UEFI firmware is standardized. This allows UEFI firmware to be extended in a vendor-neutral way.

====Boot mechanism====
A legacy BIOS loads a 512 byte flat binary blob from the [[MBR]] of the boot device into memory at physical address 0x7C00 and jumps to it. The bootloader can return back to the BIOS through INT 0x18. On the other hand, UEFI firmware loads an arbitrary sized UEFI application (a relocatable [[PE]] executable file) from a [[FAT]] partition on a [[GPT]] or MBR partitioned boot device to some address selected at run-time. Then it calls that application's main entry point. The application can return control to the firmware, which will continue searching for another boot device or bring up a diagnostic menu.

====System discovery====
A legacy bootloader scans memory for structures like the [[EBDA]], [[SMBIOS]], and [[ACPI]] tables. It uses PIO to talk to the root [[PCI]] controller and scan the PCI bus. It is possible that redundant tables may be present in memory (for example, the [[MP_Specification|MP]] table in the SMBIOS contains information that's also present in the ACPI [[DSDT]] and [[MADT]]) and the bootloader can choose which to use.

When UEFI firmware calls a UEFI application's entry point function, it passes a "System Table" structure, which contains pointers to all of the system's ACPI tables, memory map, and other information relevant to an OS. Legacy tables (like MP tables) may not be present in memory.

====Convenience functions====
A legacy BIOS hooks a variety of interrupts which a bootloader can trigger to access system resources like disks and the screen. These interrupts are not standardized, except by historical convention. Each interrupt uses a different register passing convention.

UEFI firmware establishes many callable functions in memory, which are grouped into sets called "protocols" and are discoverable through the System Table. The behavior of each function in each protocol is defined by specification. UEFI applications can define their own protocols and persist them in memory for other UEFI applications to use. Functions are called with a standardized, modern calling convention supported by many C compilers.

====Development environment====
Legacy bootloaders can be developed in any environment that can generate flat binary images: NASM, GCC, etc. UEFI applications can be developed in any language that can be compiled and linked into a [[PE]] executable file and supports the calling convention used to access functions established in memory by the UEFI firmware. In practice this means one of three development environments: EDK2, GNU-EFI or POSIX-UEFI.

[[EDK2]] is a large and complex, yet feature filled environment with its own build system. It can be configured to use GCC, LLVM, MinGW, Microsoft Visual C++, etc. as a cross-compiler. Not only can it be used to compile UEFI applications, but it can also be used to compile UEFI firmware to be flashed to a BIOS ROM.

[[GNU-EFI]] is a set of libraries and headers for compiling UEFI applications with a system's native GCC (does not work with LLVM CLang). It can't be used to compile UEFI firmware. Since it's just a couple of libraries against which a UEFI application can be linked, it is much easier to use than TianoCore ( EDK2 ).

[[POSIX-UEFI]] is very similar to GNU-EFI, but it is distributed mainly as a source, not as a binary library, has ANSI C like names and works with GCC as well as LLVM CLang. It's shipped with a Makefile that sets up the compiler flags for you.

====Emulation====

[[OVMF]], a popular open source UEFI firmware, has been ported to the QEMU (but not Bochs) emulated machine. Because it implements the UEFI specification, it behaves very similarly to commercial UEFI firmware on real machines. (OVMF itself is built with TianoCore, and its source ship with it as well, but pre-built images are available.)

===Legacy bootloader or UEFI application?===
If you are targeting legacy systems for which UEFI is not available or is not reliable, you should develop a legacy bootloader. This requires intimate knowledge of 16-bit addressing and the backwards-compatibility features of an x86 or x86-64 CPU.  If you are targeting modern systems you should develop a UEFI application. Many UEFI firmwares can be configured to emulate a legacy BIOS, but there is even more variation among these emulated environments than among real legacy BIOS.

Although there is a slight learning curve to become familiar with the UEFI development environments, using the System Table, and accessing UEFI-provided protocols (functions), there are far fewer "gotchas" than trying to remain compatible with the wide variety of quickly-becoming-obsolete legacy BIOSs on real machines. UEFI is the standard for all modern PCs.

===UEFI class 0-3 and CSM===
PCs are categorized as UEFI class 0, 1, 2, or 3. A class 0 machine is a legacy system with a legacy BIOS; i.e. not a UEFI system at all.

A class 1 machine is a UEFI system that runs exclusively in Compatibility Support Module (CSM) mode. CSM is a specification for how UEFI firmware can emulate a legacy BIOS. UEFI firmware in CSM mode loads legacy bootloaders. A class 1 UEFI system may not advertise UEFI support at all, since it isn't exposed to the bootloader. It's only UEFI "within" the BIOS.

A class 2 machine is a UEFI system that can launch UEFI applications but also includes the option to run in CSM mode. The majority of modern PCs are UEFI class 2 machines. Sometimes the choice to run UEFI applications vs. CSM is a one-or-the-other setting in the BIOS configuration, and other times the BIOS will decide which to use after selecting the boot device and checking whether it has a legacy bootloader or a UEFI application.

A class 3 machine is a UEFI system that does not support CSM. UEFI class 3 machines only run UEFI applications and do not implement CSM for backwards compatibility with legacy bootloaders.

===Secure Boot===
Secure Boot is a digital signature scheme for UEFI applications that consists of four components:
* '''PK''': Platform Key
* '''KEK''': Key Exchange Keys
* '''db''': Whitelist database
* '''dbx''': Blacklist database

UEFI firmware that supports Secure Boot is always in one of three states:
* Setup mode, Secure Boot ''off''
* User mode, Secure Boot ''off''
* User mode, Secure Boot ''on''

In setup mode, any UEFI application can change or delete the PK, add/remove keys from the KEK, and add/remove whitelist or blacklist entries from the db or dbx.

In user mode, regardless of whether Secure Boot is on or off:
* The PK may only be changed or deleted by a UEFI application that already has the current PK.
* Keys can only be added/removed from the KEK by a UEFI application that has the PK.
* Whitelist and blacklist entries can only be added/removed from the db and dbx by a UEFI application that has any one of the keys in the KEK.

Finally, in user mode with Secure Boot ''on'', UEFI applications must meet one of the following four requirements to be launched:
* Signed, with signature in db and not in dbx
* Signed by a key in db and not in dbx
* Signed by a key in the KEK
* Unsigned, but a hash of the application is in db and not in dbx

Note that UEFI applications are not signed by the PK, unless the PK also happens to be in the KEK.

Not all UEFI firmwares support Secure Boot, although it is a requirement for Windows 8. Some UEFI firmwares support Secure Boot and there's no option to be disabled, which poses a problem for independent developers that do not have access to the PK or any of the keys in the KEK, and therefore can't install their own key or application signature or hash to the whitelist database. Independent developers should develop on systems that either do not support Secure Boot or has an option for Secure Boot to be turned off.

An easy way out to use a loader that is signed by Microsoft, and allows you to load another binary signed by a key and certificate owned by you (called MOK, Machine Owner's Key). Such a loader is [https://github.com/rhboot/shim shim], used by RedHat, Fedora, Suse, Ubuntu, Arch and many other distros to load GRUB. The filename of the EFI executable is hardwired in shim, but if you rename your loader to GRUBX64.EFI (or GRUBIA32.EFI), you sign it with your MOK key and certificate using [https://github.com/imedias/sbsigntool sbsigntool], then you can load any loader in Secure Boot you want.

===How to use UEFI===
Traditional operating systems like Windows and Linux have an existing software architecture and a large code base to perform system configuration and device discovery. With their sophisticated layers of abstraction they don't directly benefit from UEFI. As a result, their UEFI bootloaders do little but prepare the environment for them to run.

An independent developer may find more value in using UEFI to write feature-full UEFI applications, rather than viewing UEFI as a temporary start-up environment to be jettisoned during the boot process. Unlike legacy bootloaders, which typically interact with BIOS only enough to bring up the OS, a UEFI application can implement sophisticated behavior with the help of UEFI. In other words, an independent developer shouldn't be in a rush to leave "UEFI-land".

A good starting point is writing a UEFI application that uses the System Table to fetch a memory map, and uses the "File" protocol to read files from FAT-formatted disks. The next step might be to use the System Table to locate ACPI tables.

==Developing with POSIX-UEFI==
:''Main article: [[POSIX-UEFI]]

One option to compile UEFI applications on POSIX like systems is POSIX-UEFI. It provides a [[libc]]-like API for your EFI application, and ships with a Makefile that can detect and set up the toolchain for you. It can use GCC or LLVM, and defaults to using the host compiler, but a cross compiler is still recommended.

It uses POSIX style typedefs (like ''uintn_t'' instead of ''UINTN''), and it does not ship with the standard EFI headers. You can still get interfaces not covered by POSIX-UEFI (such as GOP) by installing the EFI headers from GNU-EFI or EDK2. Also, it compiles with the MS ABI, meaning that UEFI services can be called natively (i.e., without uefi_call_wrapper) so long as your apps are compiled with it as well.
The traditional "Hello, world" UEFI program goes like this.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
#include &lt;uefi.h&gt;
 
int main (int argc, char **argv)
{
  printf("Hello, world!\n");
  return 0;
}
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Makefile looks like this:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="make"&gt;
TARGET = main.efi
include uefi/Makefile
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Run make to build it. The result of this process is a PE executable file ''main.efi''.

==Developing with GNU-EFI==
:''Main article: [[GNU-EFI]]

GNU-EFI can be used to develop both 32-bit and 64-bit UEFI applications. This section will address 64-bit UEFI applications only, and assumes that the development environment itself is running on an x86_64 system, so that no cross-compiler is needed. For a more thorough walk-through of a proper (non-gnu-efi) development environment, see [[UEFI App Bare Bones]].
        
GNU-EFI includes four things:
* '''crt0-efi-x86_64.o''': A CRT0 (C runtime initialization code) that provides an entry point that UEFI firmware will call when launching the application, which will in turn call the "efi_main" function that the developer writes.
* '''libgnuefi.a''': A library containing a single function (''_relocate'') that is used by the CRT0.
* '''elf_x86_64_efi.lds''': A linker script used to link ELF binaries into UEFI applications.
* '''efi.h''' and other headers: Convenience headers that provide structures, typedefs, and constants improve readability when accessing the System Table and other UEFI resources.
* '''libefi.a''': A library containing convenience functions like CRC computation, string length calculation, and easy text printing.
* '''efilib.h''': Header for ''libefi.a''.

At a bare minimum, a 64-bit UEFI application will need to link against ''crt0-efi-x86_64.o'' and ''libgnuefi.a'' using the ''elf_x86_64_efi.lds'' linker script. Most likely you will want to use the provided headers and the convenience library as well, and this section will assume that going forward.

The traditional "Hello, world" UEFI program is shown below.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
#include &lt;efi.h&gt;
#include &lt;efilib.h&gt;

EFI_STATUS
EFIAPI
efi_main (EFI_HANDLE ImageHandle, EFI_SYSTEM_TABLE *SystemTable)
{
  InitializeLib(ImageHandle, SystemTable);
  Print(L"Hello, world!\n");
  return EFI_SUCCESS;
}
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

A few notes:
* efi.h is included so we can use types like EFI_STATUS, EFI_HANDLE, and EFI_SYSTEM_TABLE.
* When creating a 32-bit UEFI application, EFIAPI is empty; GCC will compile the "efi_main" function using the standard C calling convention. When creating a 64-bit UEFI application, EFIAPI expands to "__attribute__((ms_abi))" and GCC will compile the "efi_main" function using Microsoft's x64 calling convention, as specified by UEFI. Only functions that will be called directly from UEFI (including main, but also callbacks) need to use the UEFI calling convention.
* "InitializeLib" and "Print" are convenience functions provided by libefi.a with prototypes in efilib.h. "InitializeLib" lets libefi.a store a reference to the ImageHandle and SystemTable provided by BIOS. "Print" uses those stored references to print a string by reaching out to UEFI-provided functions in memory. (Later on we will see how to find and call UEFI-provided functions manually.)

This program is compiled and linked as below.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ gcc main.c                             \
      -c                                 \
      -fno-stack-protector               \
      -fpic                              \
      -fshort-wchar                      \
      -mno-red-zone                      \
      -I /path/to/gnu-efi/headers        \
      -I /path/to/gnu-efi/headers/x86_64 \
      -DEFI_FUNCTION_WRAPPER             \
      -o main.o

$ ld main.o                         \
     /path/to/crt0-efi-x86_64.o     \
     -nostdlib                      \
     -znocombreloc                  \
     -T /path/to/elf_x86_64_efi.lds \
     -shared                        \
     -Bsymbolic                     \
     -L /path/to/libs               \
     -l:libgnuefi.a                 \
     -l:libefi.a                    \
     -o main.so

$ objcopy -j .text                       \
          -j .sdata                      \
          -j .data                       \
          -j .rodata                     \
          -j .dynamic                    \
          -j .dynsym                     \
          -j .rel                        \
          -j .rela                       \
          -j .reloc                      \
          --output-target=efi-app-x86_64 \
          main.so                        \
          main.efi
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

The result of this process is a 44 kB PE executable file ''main.efi''. On a real project you'll probably want to use make or another build tool, and may need to build a cross-compiler. The way GNU-EFI works is a bit contrived: you are wrapping an ELF file built by your normal compiler into PE.

==Emulation with QEMU and OVMF==
Any recent version of QEMU with a recent version of OVMF will be sufficient to run a UEFI application. QEMU binaries are available for many platforms, and a binary OVMF image (OVMF.fd) can be found on the [http://www.tianocore.org/ovmf/ TianoCore] website. QEMU (without any boot disk) can be invoked as below. (To prevent recent versions of QEMU from attempting a PXE (network) boot when no boot disk is found, use &lt;code&gt;-net none&lt;/code&gt;.

The recommended way to use OVMF (for QEMU 1.6 or newer) is with a &lt;code&gt;pflash&lt;/code&gt; parameter. The instructions below assume you have an OVMF image split into separate CODE and VARS sections.

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ qemu-system-x86_64 -cpu qemu64 \
  -drive if=pflash,format=raw,unit=0,file=path_to_OVMF_CODE.fd,readonly=on \
  -drive if=pflash,format=raw,unit=1,file=path_to_OVMF_VARS.fd \
  -net none
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

If you prefer to work on a terminal without a display, or via SSH/telnet, you will want to run QEMU without graphics support, using the &lt;code&gt;-nographic&lt;/code&gt; flag.

If OVMF does not find a boot disk with a properly named UEFI application (more on this later) it will drop into a UEFI shell.

[[file:OVMF_shell.png]]

You can find a list of shell commands [https://web.archive.org/web/20170504062623/http://www.sysadminshare.com/2012/01/efi-shell-commands.html here] or you can type ''help'' at the shell.

===Creating disk images===
:''Main article: [[Bootable Disk]]

To launch a UEFI application you will need to create a disk image and present it to QEMU. UEFI firmware expects UEFI applications to be stored in a FAT12, FAT16, or FAT32 file system on a [[GPT]] or [[MBR]]-partitioned disk. Many firmwares only support FAT32, so that's what you'll want to use. Depending on your platform, there are several different ways to create a disk image containing your UEFI application, but they all start by creating a zeroed disk image file. The minimum FAT32 partition size is 33,548,800 bytes, plus you will need space for the primary and secondary GPT tables, plus some slack space so the partition can be aligned correctly. Throughout these examples we will be creating a 48,000,000 byte (93750 512-byte sectors, or 48 MB) disk image.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ dd if=/dev/zero of=/path/to/uefi.img bs=512 count=93750
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

====Virtual FAT disk images====

QEMU can automatically create a virtual FAT disk image from a specified directory tree. To use this feature, simply create a directory and copy any UEFI applications you want to test into it.

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ mkdir esp
$ cp /path/to/main.efi esp
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

After that, you can invoke QEMU as below.

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ qemu-system-x86_64 -cpu qemu64 \
  -drive if=pflash,format=raw,unit=0,file=path_to_OVMF_CODE.fd,readonly=on \
  -drive if=pflash,format=raw,unit=1,file=path_to_OVMF_VARS.fd \
  -drive format=raw,file=fat:rw:esp \
  -net none
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

====uefi-run helper application====
The uefi-run application is useful for quick testing. It creates a temporary FAT image containing your EFI application and starts qemu.

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ uefi-run -b /path/to/OVMF.fd -q /path/to/qemu app.efi -- &lt;extra_qemu_args&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

uefi-run is not currently packaged for any distribution. You can install it using cargo (the Rust package manager) though ("cargo install uefi-run").

====Linux, root required====
This approach requires root privileges and uses '''gdisk''', '''losetup''', and '''mkdosfs'''. First, use gdisk to create a GPT partition table with a single [[EFI System Partition]].
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ gdisk /path/to/uefi.img
GPT fdisk (gdisk) version 0.8.10

Partition table scan:
  MBR: not present
  BSD: not present
  APM: not present
  GPT: not present

Creating new GPT entries.

Command (? for help): o
This option deletes all partitions and creates a new protective MBR.
Proceed? (Y/N): y

Command (? for help): n
Partition number (1-128, default 1): 1
First sector (34-93716, default = 2048) or {+-}size{KMGTP}: 2048
Last sector (2048-93716, default = 93716) or {+-}size{KMGTP}: 93716
Current type is 'Linux filesystem'
Hex code or GUID (L to show codes, Enter = 8300): ef00
Changed type of partition to 'EFI System'

Command (? for help): w

Final checks complete. About to write GPT data. THIS WILL OVERWRITE EXISTING
PARTITIONS!!

Do you want to proceed? (Y/N): y
OK; writing new GUID partition table (GPT) to uefi.img.
Warning: The kernel is still using the old partition table.
The new table will be used at the next reboot.
The operation has completed successfully.
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Now you have disk image with [[GPT|GUID partition table]] on it and an unformatted EFI partition starting at sector 2048. Unless you deviated from the commands shown above, the disk image will use 512-byte sectors, so the EFI partition starts at byte 1,048,576 and is 46,934,528 bytes in length. Use losetup to present the partition to Linux on a loopback device.

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
losetup --offset 1048576 --sizelimit 46934528 /dev/loop0 /path/to/uefi.img
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

(If /dev/loop0 is already in use you will need to select a different loopback device.)

Format the partition for FAT32 with mkdosfs.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
mkdosfs -F 32 /dev/loop0
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

The partition can now be mounted, so that we can copy files to it. In this example we use the "/mnt" directory, but you could also create a local directory for temporary use.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
mount /dev/loop0 /mnt
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Copy any UEFI applications you want to test to the file system.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ cp /path/to/main.efi /mnt/
$ ...
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Finally, unmount the partition and free the loopback device.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ umount /mnt
$ losetup -d /dev/loop0
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

''uefi.img'' is now a disk image containing primary and secondary GPT tables, containing a single partition of type EFI, containing a FAT32 file system, containing one or more UEFI applications.

====Linux, root not required====
This approach uses '''parted''', '''mformat''', and '''mcopy''' and can be performed with user privileges. First, use parted to create primary and secondary GPT headers, and a single EFI partition spanning the same range as the approach above.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ parted /path/to/uefi.img -s -a minimal mklabel gpt
$ parted /path/to/uefi.img -s -a minimal mkpart EFI FAT16 2048s 93716s
$ parted /path/to/uefi.img -s -a minimal toggle 1 boot
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Now create a new temporary image file that will contain the EFI partition data and use mformat to format it with FAT16.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
dd if=/dev/zero of=/tmp/part.img bs=512 count=91669
mformat -i /tmp/part.img -h 32 -t 32 -n 64 -c 1
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Use mcopy to copy any UEFI applications you want to test to the file system.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ mcopy -i /tmp/part.img /path/to/main.efi ::
$ ...
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Finally, write the partition image into the main disk image.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ dd if=/tmp/part.img of=/path/to/uefi.img bs=512 count=91669 seek=2048 conv=notrunc
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

''uefi.img'' is now a disk image containing primary and secondary GPT tables, containing a single partition of type EFI, containing a FAT16 file system, containing one or more UEFI applications.

====FreeBSD, root required====
This approach requires root privileges and uses '''mdconfig''', '''gpart''', '''newfs_msdos''', and '''mount_msdosfs'''. First, create a device node that presents the zeroed disk image as a block device. This will let us work on it using standard partitioning and formatting tools.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ mdconfig -f /path/to/uefi.img
md0
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

In this example the new block device is ''md0''. Now create the empty primary and secondary GPT tables on the device.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ gpart create -s GPT md0
md0 created
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Now we can add a partition to the disk. We'll specify an "EFI" partition, which just means that GPT will set that partition's GUID to the special "EFI" type. Not all BIOSs require this, and the partition will still be able to be mounted and browsed normally on Linux, FreeBSD, and Windows.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ gpart add -t efi md0
md0p1 added
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Next, create a FAT16 file system on the new partition. You can specify various parameters for the file system if you'd like, but it isn't necessary. Ideally you would create a FAT32 partition for best firmware compatibility but FreeBSD seems to create FAT32 partitions that OVMF can't read.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ newfs_msdos -F 16 md0p1
newfs_msdos: trim 2 sectors to adjust to a multiple of 9
/dev/md2p1: 93552 sectors in 11694 FAT16 clusters (4096 bytes/cluster)
BytesPerSec=512 SecPerClust=8 ResSectors=1 FATs=2 RootDirEnts=512 Media=0xf0 FATsecs=46 SecPerTrack=9 Heads=16 HiddenSecs=0 HugeSectors=93681
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

The partition can now be mounted, so that we can copy files to it. In this example we use the ''/mnt'' directory, but you could also create a local directory for temporary use.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ mount_msdosfs /dev/md0p1 /mnt
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Copy any UEFI applications you want to test to the file system.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ cp /path/to/main.efi /mnt/
$ ...
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Finally, unmount the partition and free the block device.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ umount /mnt
$ mdconfig -d -u md0
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

''uefi.img'' is now a disk image containing primary and secondary GPT tables, containing a single partition of type EFI, containing a FAT16 file system, containing one or more UEFI applications.

====Mac OS (root not required)====
Mac OS has a single tool (hdiutil) that creates the disk image and copy files at same time.

Let's say that you're creating a UEFI boot for x86_64. By definition the file name should be BOOTX64.EFI and this file should be located in the /EFI/BOOT folder.

First, let's create a temporary folder that will contains all files and folders required for booting UEFI.
  
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ mkdir -p diskImage/EFI/BOOT
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Secondly, let's copy the boot application to the required location:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ cp bootx64.efi diskImage/EFI/BOOT/BOOTX64.EFI
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Finally, let's create a disk image partitioned with GPT, formatted with fat32 (-fs fat32), overriding destination file if needed (-ov), define disk size (-size 48m), define volume name (-volname NEWOS), the file format which the disk will be encoded (-format UDTO - the same used for DVDs/CDs) and the source folder containing the files that will be copied to the new disk:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ hdiutil create -fs fat32 -ov -size 48m -volname NEWOS -format UDTO -srcfolder diskImage uefi.cdr
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

uefi.cdr should be ready to be used by QEMU.

===Launching UEFI applications===
Once your disk image is ready, you can invoke QEMU as below.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
$ qemu-system-x86_64 -cpu qemu64 -bios /path/to/OVMF.fd -drive file=uefi.disk,if=ide
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

When OVMF drops into the UEFI shell, you will see an additional entry in the "Mapping table", labeled "FS0". This indicates that the firmware detected the disk, discovered the partition, and was able to mount the file system. You can explore the file system by switching to it using the DOS-style syntax "FS0:", as illustrated below.

[[File:OVMF_browse_fs.png]]

You can launch a UEFI application by entering its name.

[[File:OVMF_run_app.png]]

Notice that the UEFI shell resumed once the application terminated. Of course if this was a proper bootloader it would never resume, but rather launch an OS.

Some commercial UEFI firmware provides UEFI shells or the capability to launch user-selected UEFI applications, such as the firmware that ships with the HP EliteBook line of laptops. Most, however, do not expose this functionality to the end-user.

===Debugging===
OVMF can be built in debug mode, and it will output logging messages to IO port 0x402.
You can use some flags like the ones below to capture the output.

&lt;code&gt;-debugcon file:uefi_debug.log -global isa-debugcon.iobase=0x402&lt;/code&gt;

Note that release builds will not output debug messages, or will have reduced output.

See [[Debugging UEFI applications with GDB]].

==Running on real hardware==
===NVRAM variables===
{{Main|UEFI NVRAM}}
A UEFI firmware will present most of its configuration options through a text or graphical configuration menu, just like a legacy BIOS. Selections made in these menus are stored in the NVRAM chip between reboots. Unlike legacy BIOS, however, the firmware developer has the option to expose some or all of these "NVRAM variables" to the OS and end-user via convenience functions made resident in RAM by the firmware at boot.

The Linux '''efivarfs''' kernel module will use these functions to list NVRAM variables in the ''/sys/firmware/efi/efivars'' file. NVRAM variables can also be dumped from within the UEFI shell itself with the '''dmpstore''' command. Device boot order is always accessible via NVRAM variables. The Linux program '''efibootmgr''' works specifically with the boot order NVRAM variables. The UEFI shell offers the '''bcfg''' command for the same purpose.

===Bootable UEFI applications===
The boot order NVRAM variables determine where firmware will look for UEFI applications to be launched at boot. Although this can be changed (for example, an OS installer might customize the boot entry for the hard drive to which it was installed) firmware typically looks for a UEFI application named "BOOTIA32.efi" (for 32-bit applications) or "BOOTX64.efi" (for 64-bit applications) stored in the "/EFI/BOOT" path in the boot device's file system. This is the default path and name for OVMF.

Unlike a UEFI application launched from the shell, if a bootable UEFI application returns BIOS will continue searching for other boot devices.

===Exposed functionality===
Real PCs vary in the amount of UEFI capability they expose to the user. For example, even a class 3 machine may not make any mention of UEFI in its BIOS configuration and may not offer a UEFI shell. Additionally, some BIOS vendors make their UEFI firmware configuration screens look identical to their legacy BIOS configuration screens. Class 2 machines may present somewhat confusing boot menus and configuration options. For example, one laptop manufacturer includes a configuration option to enable/disable UEFI (i.e. switch between UEFI and CSM behavior), named "OS: Windows 8". Another laptop, if it fails to find a bootable UEFI application on the selected boot device (or if that application returns a status other than EFI_SUCCESS) will fall back to CSM behavior and then complain that the drive has a corrupted MBR. With time, and with the emergence of class 3 machines, clarity of UEFI boot behavior will improve.

To make testing on real hardware easier, you can install a bootable UEFI application to the internal hard drive of the system that provides a boot menu, such as [http://www.rodsbooks.com/refind/ rEFInd]. This may also be convenient for multi-boot scenarios.

===PC firmware developers===
On x86 and x86-64 platforms, the following BIOS developers offer UEFI firmware:
* AMI (Aptio).
* Phoenix (SecureCore, TrustedCore, AwardCore).
* Insyde (InsydeH20).

== UEFI applications in detail ==
=== Binary Format ===
UEFI executables are regular PE32 / PE32+ (Windows x32 / x64) images, with a specific '''subsystem'''.
Every UEFI application is basically a windows EXE (or DLL) without symbol tables.

{| class="wikitable"
|+ Types of UEFI images
|-
! Type
! Description
! Subsystem
|-
| Applications || OS loaders and other utility programs. || 10
|-
| Boot service driver || Drivers used by the firmware when booting (e.g. disk drivers, network drivers). || 11
|-
| Runtime driver || Drivers which may stay loaded even after the OS loads and exits the boot services. || 12
|}

UEFI images must also specify the type of machine code they contain. A UEFI loader will refuse to boot an incompatible image.

{| class="wikitable"
|+ Types of machines
|-
! Name / arch
! Value
|-
|x86||0x014c
|-
|x86_64||0x8664
|-
|Itanium x64||0x0200
|-
|UEFI Byte Code||0x0EBC
|-
|ARM&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;||0x01C2
|-
|AArch (ARM x64)||0xAA64
|-
|RISC-V x32||0x5032
|-
|RISC-V x64||0x5064
|-
|RISC-V x128||0x5128
|}

[1] ARM means you can use Thumb / Thumb 2 instructions, but UEFI interfaces are in ARM mode.

==== Initialization ====
Applications must either load an OS and exit boot services, or return from the main function (in which case the boot loader will look for the next app to load).

Drivers must initialize and then return 0 on success, or an error code. A computer might fail to boot if a required driver fails to load.

==== Memory ====
The memory map returned by UEFI will mark the memory areas which drivers use.

Once your OS loader finished, your kernel is allowed to reuse the memory where the boot loader was loaded.

The memory types are &lt;code&gt;Efi{Loader/BootServices/RuntimeServices}{Code/Data}&lt;/code&gt;.

After exiting the boot services, you may reuse whatever non-read-only memory the boot drivers used.

However, memory used by the runtime drivers must '''never''' be touched - the runtime drivers stay active and loaded for as long as the computer runs.

One way to see a breakdown of a PE file containing a UEFI application is by&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;$ objdump --all-headers /path/to/main.efi&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Its output is quite long. Among other things, it shows the '''subsystem''', that is the type of the UEFI image, mentioned earlier.

=== Calling Conventions ===
UEFI specifies the following calling conventions:
* '''cdecl''' for x86 UEFI functions
* '''Microsoft's 64-bit calling convention''' for x86-64 UEFI functions
* '''SMC''' for ARM UEFI functions

This has two impacts on UEFI application developers:
* A UEFI application's main entry point must expect to be called with the corresponding calling convention.
* Any UEFI-provided functions that a UEFI application calls must be called with the corresponding calling convention.
Note that functions strictly internal to the application can use whatever calling convention the developer chooses.

==== POSIX-UEFI, GNU-EFI and GCC ====
{{Main|GNU-EFI}}
cdecl is the standard calling convention used by GCC, so no special attributes or modifiers are needed for writing the main entry point or calling UEFI functions in an x86 UEFI application developed with GNU-EFI. For x86-64, however, the entry point function must be declared with the "___attribute___((ms_abi))" modifier and all calls to UEFI-provided functions must be made through the "uefi_call_wrapper" thunk. This thunk is called with cdecl, but then translates to the Microsoft x86-64 calling convention before calling the requested UEFI function. This is necessary because older releases of GCC do not support specifying calling conventions for function pointers.

For [[POSIX-UEFI]], which also uses GCC, your entry point looks like the standard main(), and no special ABI is required. Also the build environment takes care of the compiler flags for you, so you can simply call UEFI functions without "uefi_call_wrapper", no matter if you're using the host gcc or a cross-compiler.

For developer convenience, both POSIX-UEFI and GNU-EFI provides the "EFIAPI" macro, which expands to "cdecl" when targeting x86 and "__attribute__(ms_abi))" when targeting x86-64. Additionally, the "uefi_call_wrapper" thunk will simply pass the call through on x86. This allows the same source code to target x86 and x86-64. For example, the following main function will compile with the correct calling convention on both x86 and x86-64 and the call through the "uefi_call_wrapper" thunk will select the correct calling convention to use when calling the UEFI function (in this case, printing a string).
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
EFI_STATUS EFIAPI efi_main(EFI_HANDLE ImageHandle, EFI_SYSTEM_TABLE *SystemTable)
{
  EFI_STATUS status = uefi_call_wrapper(SystemTable-&gt;ConOut-&gt;OutputString,
                                        2,
                                        SystemTable-&gt;ConOut,
                                        L"Hello, World!\n");
  return status;
}
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

=== Language binding ===
UEFI applications are typically written in C, although bindings could be written for any other language that compiles to machine code. Assembly is also an option; a [[uefi.inc]] is available for [[FASM]] that allows UEFI applications to be written as below.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="asm"&gt;
format pe64 dll efi
entry main

section '.text' code executable readable

include 'uefi.inc'

main:
    ; initialize UEFI library
    InitializeLib
    jc @f

    ; call uefi function to print to screen
    uefi_call_wrapper ConOut, OutputString, ConOut, _hello

@@: mov eax, EFI_SUCCESS
    retn

section '.data' data readable writeable

_hello                                  du 'Hello World',13,10,0

section '.reloc' fixups data discardable
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

As a UEFI application contains normal x86 or x86-64 machine code, inline assembly is also an option in compilers that support it.

=== EFI Byte Code===
UEFI also includes a virtual machine specification based on a byte code format called EFI Byte Code (EBC), which can be used to write platform-independent device drivers, but not UEFI applications. As of 2015 there has been limited use of EBC.

== Common Problems ==

=== My UEFI application hangs/resets after about 5 minutes ===

When control is handed to your UEFI application by firmware, it sets a watchdog timer for 5 minutes, after which the firmware is reinvoked as it assumes your application has hung.  The firmware in this case will normally try to reset the system (although the OVMF firmware in VirtualBox simply causes the screen to go black and hang).  To counteract this, you are required to refresh the watchdog timer before it times out.  Alternatively, you can disable it completely with code like &lt;syntaxhighlight lang="C"&gt;SystemTable-&gt;BootServices-&gt;SetWatchdogTimer(0, 0, 0, NULL);&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;Obviously this is not a problem for most bootloaders, but can cause an issue if you have an interactive loader which waits for user input.  Also note that you are required to disable the watchdog timer if you exit back to the firmware.

=== My bootloader hangs if I use user defined EFI_MEMORY_TYPE values ===

For the memory management functions in EFI, an OS is meant to be able to use "memory type" values above 0x80000000 for its own purposes. In the OVMF EFI firmware release "r11337" (for Qemu, etc) there is a bug where the firmware assumes the memory type is within the range of values defined for EFI's own use, and uses the memory type as an array index. The end result is an "array index out of bounds" bug; where the higher memory type values (e.g. perfectly legal values above 0x80000000) cause the 64-bit version of the firmware to crash (page fault), and cause incorrect "attribute" values to be reported by the 32-bit version of the firmware. This same bug is also present in whatever version of the EFI firmware VirtualBox uses (which looks like an older version of OVMF); and I suspect (but don't know) that the bug may be present in a wide variety of firmware that was derived from the tianocore project (not just OVMF).

== See also ==
=== Articles ===
* [[UEFI Bare Bones]]
* [[EFI System Partition]]
* [[PE]] file format
* [[EDK2]]
* [[POSIX-UEFI]]
* [[GNU-EFI]]
* [https://github.com/nebulaeonline/nebulae/tree/UefiBarebones Uefi Barebones MSVC/Clang/Visual Studio]

=== External Links ===
* [https://uefi.org/specifications UEFI specifications et al.]
* [http://www.tianocore.org/ Intel TianoCore EDK2]
* [https://github.com/tianocore/tianocore.github.io/wiki/OVMF OVMF firmware images] for use with [[QEMU]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20181028201454/http://wiki.phoenix.com/wiki/index.php/Main_Page Phoenix UEFI Wiki]
* [http://x86asm.net/articles/others/index.html Several articles about UEFI]
* [https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=19509 PE specification covering the (U)EFI binary format]
* [https://uefi.blogspot.com/ Blog about UEFI, with bits about UEFI development]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160316192235/http://internshipatdell.wikispaces.com/file/view/How+to+build+an+UEFI+application.pptx Presentation guiding through simple UEFI application setup]
* [https://uefi.org/sites/default/files/resources/UEFI-Plugfest-WindowsBootEnvironment.pdf Presentation giving an overview of windows uefi booting]
* [https://gitlab.com/bztsrc/posix-uefi POSIX-UEFI] documentation and source
* [[Wikipedia:Extensible_Firmware_Interface|Wikipedia Article on EFI]]

[[Category:x86]]
[[Category:x86-64]]
[[Category:ARM]]
[[Category:Firmware]]
[[Category:UEFI]]
[[de:Unified_Extensible_Firmware_Interface]]</text>
      <sha1>o9l950k51r5nmksxsfcth17pqfo58eq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>EDK2</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4624</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30304</id>
      <parentid>30080</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-16T20:35:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Makaroneder</username>
        <id>1943</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Replace source tag with syntaxhighlight tag</comment>
      <origin>30304</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="9175" sha1="rces5xtiojaic5p7es1kdeviwlcro2b" xml:space="preserve">{{In_Progress}}
EDK2 is the official development environment for [[UEFI]] applications. It is developed by the open-source Tianocore project, of which Intel, HP, and Microsoft are the primary contributors. Although it may be bigger than [[GNU-EFI]], it has more features, hence, some OS developers may prefer it over GNU-EFI.

==What is EDK2?==
EDK2 is full on implementation of the [[UEFI]] spec. It contains the Open Virtual Machine Firmware (OVMF) UEFI firmware package, which is primarily targeted at [[QEMU]], and is used by many OS developers to test out their UEFI applications. It also has [[ARM]] and [[AArch64]] firmware packages for QEMU and various boards, and [[RISC-V]] firmware packages for various [[HiFive]] boards. It also has tools for UEFI driver developers, but that is outside the scope of this wiki.

Of most interest the OS developers is the UEFI library and the EDK2 build system. This article will show you the structure of EDK2, how to build firmware for QEMU and real machines, and how to build UEFI applications.

==Structure of EDK2==
EDK2 is made up of multiple repos, all of which can be found at [https://github.com/tianocore https://github.com/tianocore]. The main ones are:

- edk2, which contains the build system, library, OVMF, and ArmVirt firmware

- edk2-platforms, which contains firmware for various real hardware platforms, such as the SiFive U450, Raspberry Pi, and quite a few others

- edk2-non-osi, which contains proprietary binary blobs for various platforms.

EDK2 itself is written in C with some Python, and is licensed under the BSD 2 Clause + Patent license. The blobs are subject to their own licenses.
===Directory structure===
EDK2 is split up into multiple subdirectories, where each one normally contains a "Package". The OvmfPkg subdirectory contains OVMF, the MdePkg subdirectory contains the UEFI library, and so on. Each one of these contains a file ending in .dsc. This file describes the package inside of the folder, and contains things such as dependencies, different components, and so on. Each component is described its own file that contains sources, application type, and so on.
TODO: Describe this in more detail
==Building EDK2's base==
No matter what you are trying to build from EDK2, these steps must be completed. First, you must decide if you want to only build stuff inside of the main EDK2 repo, or if you also want stuff from edk2-platforms. Note that these guides assume you are on a Linux system (Windows Subsystem for Linux is OK)
===Building without edk2-platforms===
If you only want the UEFI library or virtual machine firmware, then this guide will suffice. Make sure you have all the dependencies installed first:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
sudo apt install build-essential git python2 uuid-dev nasm acpica-tools        # Or whatever your package manager is
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
First, we must clone EDK2
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
git clone https://github.com/tianocore/edk2.git
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Note that this is the latest non-stable source. If you want the stable source then run:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
git clone https://github.com/tianocore/edk2.git -b"stable/202011"
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
or whatever is appropriate at the time you are reading this. After that, we now must clone the submodules
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
cd edk2
git submodule update --init
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Then, we need to setup the environment for EDK2
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
export EDK_TOOLS_PATH=$PWD/BaseTools
# If you are compiling for ARM, then this is needed
sudo apt install gcc-aarch64-linux-gnu        # Or whatever your package manager is
export GCC5_AARCH64_PREFIX=aarch64-linux-gnu-
# This is needed on RISC-V
sudo apt install gcc-riscv64-linux-gnu        # Or whatever your package manager is
export GCC5_RISCV64_PREFIX=riscv64-linux-gnu-
# Run this no matter what you are compiling for
source edksetup.sh
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
The last step generates various configuration files and sets up some variables. Note that edksetup.sh must be sourced, as its variables must persist.
Now we need to build the base tools
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
make -C BaseTools
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
And lastly, we must actually build EDK2 using its Python build script. 
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
build -a YOUR_ARCH -t GCC5 -p YOUR_PACKAGE
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
YOUR_ARCH can be IA32, X64, AARCH64, ARM, or RISCV64. Note that not all packages compile for all architectures. YOUR_PACKAGE must point to a package in the source tree. Further guides in this article will tell you what -p option to pass to EDK2's build script.

==== EDK2 since stable release 202602 ====
If you decide to compile from the latest Git source tree (as of 2026-02-27), the build command changes slightly, as the &lt;code&gt;GCC5&lt;/code&gt; compiler option has been deprecated. Instead, simply remove the '5', so that the compiler option simply becomes &lt;code&gt;GCC&lt;/code&gt;. This also applies when building OVMF and ArmVirt.

===Building with edk2-platforms===
If you actually want firmware that runs on real hardware, then you must perform the following steps instead of the one above

First, we need to create our workspace folder
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
mkdir edk2 &amp;&amp; cd edk2
export WORKSPACE=$PWD
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Now we need to clone the source to all repos. edk2-non-osi is optional depending on the platform you are building for, but I would recommend downloading it anyway
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
git clone https://github.com/tianocore/edk2.git -b"stable/202011"
git clone https://github.com/tianocore/edk2-platforms.git
git clone https://github.com/tianocore/edk2-non-osi.git
cd edk2 &amp;&amp; git submodule update --init
cd ../edk2-platforms &amp;&amp; git submodule update --init &amp;&amp; cd ..
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
We need to let EDK2's build system know where these folders are. We'll also setup a couple other variables as well
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
export EDK_TOOLS_PATH="$PWD/BaseTools"
export PACKAGES_PATH="$PWD/edk2:$PWD/edk2-platforms:$PWD/edk2-non-osi"
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
We now must setup the environment now
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
. edk2/edksetup.sh
make -C edk2/BaseTools
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
After that, building is exactly like before. To build for a certain platform in edk2-platforms, simply find the relevant .dsc file.
==Building an EDK2 UEFI application==
Once you have EDK2's base built, building UEFI applications is super easy. As OS developers, the main package will be working with is MdeModulePkg, a complete UEFI wrapper library.

First, we must create a directory that contains our application. We'll create it inside of the main EDK2 directory, like this
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
cd edk2
mkdir MyEfiApp
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Now, create a file named MyEfiApp.inf in the MyEfiApp directory. Give it the following contents
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="ini"&gt;
[Defines]
  INF_VERSION = 1.25
  BASE_NAME = MyEfiApp
  FILE_GUID = # Get a GUID from guidgen.com
  MODULE_TYPE = UEFI_APPLICATION
  VERSION_STRING = 1.0
  ENTRY_POINT = UefiEntry

[Sources]
  UefiMain.c

[Packages]
  MdePkg/MdePkg.dec

[LibraryClasses]
  UefiApplicationEntryPoint
  UefiLib

[Guids]

[Ppis]

[Protocols]

[FeaturePcd]

[Pcd]

&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Create a file called UefiMain.c in the same directory MyEfiApp.inf, and give it the following contents
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
#include &lt;Uefi.h&gt;
#include &lt;Library/UefiLib.h&gt;
#include &lt;Library/UefiBootServicesTableLib.h&gt;

EFI_STATUS EFIAPI UefiEntry(IN EFI_HANDLE imgHandle, IN EFI_SYSTEM_TABLE* sysTable)
{
    gST = sysTable;
    gBS = sysTable-&gt;BootServices;
    gImageHandle = imgHandle;
    // UEFI apps automatically exit after 5 minutes. Stop that here
    gBS-&gt;SetWatchdogTimer(0, 0, 0, NULL);
    Print(L"Hello, world!\r\n");
    // Allocate a string
    CHAR16* str = NULL;
    gBS-&gt;AllocatePool(EfiLoaderData, 36, (VOID**)&amp;str);
    // Copy over a string
    CHAR16* str2 = L"Allocated string\r\n";
    gBS-&gt;CopyMem((VOID*)str, (VOID*)str2, 36);
    Print(str);
    gBS-&gt;FreePool(str);
    return EFI_SUCCESS;
}
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Now run edksetup.sh if need be. After that, find a "Components" section MdeModulePkg/MdeModulePkg.dsc, and add this to it
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="ini"&gt;
[Components]
  ...
  MyEfiApp/MyEfiApp.inf
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
After that, call EDK2's build system like this to build MyEfiApp
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
build -a YOUR_ARCH -t GCC5 -p MdeModulePkg/MdeModulePkg.dsc
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Finally, in the folder Build/MdeModule/DEBUG_GCC5/YOUR_ARCH, there should be a file named MyEfiApp.efi.

==Building OVMF and ArmVirt==
Building OVMF and ArmVirtPkg is easy, after setting up EDK2, run the following for OVMF:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
build -a YOUR_ARCH -t GCC5 -p OvmfPkg/OvmfPkgYOUR_ARCH.dsc
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
YOUR_ARCH can only be IA32 or X64 for OVMF. For ArmVirtPkg, run this instead:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
build -a YOUR_ARCH -t GCC5 -p ArmVirtPkg/ArmVirtQemu.dsc
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
YOUR_ARCH can only be ARM or AARCH64. After this,, the firmware will be output in for OVMF Build/OvmfYOUR_ARCH/DEBUG_GCC5/FV, or for ArmVirtPkg Build/ArmVirtQemu-YOUR_ARCH/DEBUG_GCC5/FV

[[Category:UEFI]]
[[Category:Firmware]]</text>
      <sha1>rces5xtiojaic5p7es1kdeviwlcro2b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>EFI System Partition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4394</id>
    <revision>
      <id>27953</id>
      <parentid>27443</parentid>
      <timestamp>2023-07-09T16:07:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Khaledhammouda</username>
        <id>1596</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>27953</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2242" sha1="lde44zel514p2i8pz2cldekxay5mgke" xml:space="preserve">The EFI System Partition (ESP) is a dedicated partition on [[GPT]]. Usually a small one (32-256MiB), located at the beginning of the disk and its partition record at the beginning of the GPT.

== Identify ==
Unlike normal bootable partitions, which have the attribute flag bit 2 set, ESP is identified by its GUID, which is

 C12A7328-F81F-11D2-BA4B-00A0C93EC93B

== Format ==
In theory ESP can be formatted to any [[FAT]] file system, [[FAT12]]/[[FAT16|16]]/[[FAT32|32]]. In reality most firmware only support FAT32, and some platforms with limited resources may support [[FAT16]] too. [[FAT12]] is very rarely implemented, and it's safe to assume it won't work on a real hardware.

There's one notable exception, Apple machines (like iMac and MacBooks) use a special firmware which only accepts [[HFS+]] file system on the EFI System Partition.

== Access ==
In the EFI Shell, the ESP is the very first file system, denoting as ''FS0:''. [[GRUB]] and [http://elilo.sourceforge.net ELILO] recognize ESP, and they install their files there by default. Other boot loaders, like [http://www.rodsbooks.com/refind/ rEFInd] can only work if ESP exists.
From your application, you can use the [[Loading files under UEFI|EFI_SIMPLE_FILESYSTEM_PROTOCOL]] to access files on the ESP programmatically.

== Important Files on ESP ==
* FS0:\STARTUP.NSH - an EFI Shell script, similar to MS-DOS autoexec.bat
* FS0:\BOOTMGR.EFI - the EFI boot manager
* FS0:\BOOT\BOOTX86.EFI - the default x86_32 boot loader
* FS0:\BOOT\BOOTX64.EFI - the default x86_64 boot loader

To avoid filename clashes, you should not create files in the root directory of ESP. The specification mandates that root directory is for vendor directories, like FS0:\APPLE, FS0:\MICROSOFT etc. Some applications (like GRUB) just creates a one level directory without vendor parent directory. Feel free to create a directory for your own OS, and put your files there.

== See Also ==
=== Articles ===
* [[UEFI]]
* [[Bootable Disk]] - tutorial on how to create GPT

=== External Links ===
* [http://www.intel.com/technology/efi/ Intel EFI specifications et al.]
* [[wikipedia:EFI_System_Partition|Wikipedia: EFI System Partition]]

[[Category:Firmware]]
[[Category:UEFI]]
[[Category:Disks]]</text>
      <sha1>lde44zel514p2i8pz2cldekxay5mgke</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>AMD-Vi IOMMU</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4987</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30805</id>
      <parentid>30804</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-06-20T22:26:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Demindiro</username>
        <id>1745</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Cursory research in special MSI / MSI-X address ranges for this IOMMU</comment>
      <origin>30805</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="13887" sha1="8tz62yq22w7qrofz6ursqhftdyuw9kq" xml:space="preserve">{{stub}}

AMD-Vi provides a [[IOMMU]] to translate "Device Virtual Addresses" (DVAs) to "System Physical Addresses" (SPAs). Without nested paging, it is equivalent to translating linear/virtual addresses to physical addresses. It is also able to remap interrupt lines.

The IOMMU can be located in the PCI configuration space and is identified by checking class=0x8, subclass=0x6 and progif=0x0. None of the BAR registers are used, instead registers in capability space (id=0xf) must be used.

== Overview ==

The IOMMU requires several in-memory structures to operate.
Communication with the IOMMU is primarily done through ring buffers to improve throughput.

=== Device table ===

The device table describes how to handle transactions for devices behind the IOMMU.
There is one entry for each device, up to 65536 (the maximum for a single PCI segment).

By default, the array must be contiguous in memory. As each entry is 32 bytes it means a maximum of 2MiB is required, though it can be shorter if the start/end range contains no devices. The IOMMU may support a segmented device table to save further memory.

=== I/O page tables ===

The I/O page tables are compatible with [[Paging#64-Bit_Paging|long-mode]] page tables. It uses a number of the AVL bits to set device permissions and other attributes.

=== Interrupt remapping ===

=== Nested translation ===

=== Command buffer ===

=== Event log ===

== Device table ==

{| class="wikitable"
|+ Device Table Entry (DTE)
!
! 31
! 30
! 29
! 28
! 27
! 26
! 25
! 24
! 23
! 22
! 21
! 20
! 19
! 18
! 17
! 16
! 15
! 14
! 13
! 12
! 11
! 10
!  9
!  8
!  7
!  6
!  5
!  4
!  3
!  2
!  1
!  0
|-
! +0
|colspan="20"| Host Page Table Root Pointer[31:12]
|colspan="3" | Mode
|colspan="2" | HAD
|colspan="5" | ''res''
|colspan="1" | TV
|colspan="1" | V
|-
! +4
|colspan="1" | ''res''
|colspan="1" | IW
|colspan="1" | IR
|colspan="3" | GCR3 TRP[14:12]
|colspan="2" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| GLX
|colspan="1" | GV
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| GIoV
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| GPRP
|colspan="1" | PPR
|colspan="20"| Host Page Table Root Pointer[51:32]
|-
! +8
|colspan="16"| GCR3 Table Root Pointer[30:15]
|colspan="16"| Domain ID[15:0]
|-
! +12
|colspan="21"| GCR3 Table Root Pointer[51:31]
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| SATS
|colspan="2" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| SysMgt
|colspan="1" | EX
|colspan="1" | SD
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| Cache
|colspan="2" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| IoCtl
|colspan="1" | SA
|colspan="1" | SE
|colspan="1" | I
|-
! +16
|colspan="26"| Interrupt Table Root Pointer[31:6]
|colspan="1" | IG
|colspan="4" | IntTabLen
|colspan="1" | IV
|-
! +20
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| Lint1Pass
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| Lint0Pass
|colspan="2" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| IntCtl
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| HPTMode
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| NMIPass
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| EIntPass
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| InitPass
|colspan="2" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| GuestPagingMode
|colspan="2" | ''res''
|colspan="20"| Interrupt Table Root Pointer[51:32]
|-
! +24
|colspan="16"| GDeviceID[15:0]
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| vImuEn
|colspan="15"| ''reserved''
|-
! +28
|colspan="8" | SnoopAttribute
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| Mode0FC
|colspan="1" style="writing-mode:vertical-rl"| AttrV
|colspan="6" | ''reserved''
|colspan="16"| GuestID[15:0]
|}

== I/O page tables ==

{| class="wikitable"
|+ Page Table Entry (PTE)
! 63
! 62
! 61
! 60
! 59
! 58:52
! 51:12
! 11:9
! 8:7
! 6
! 5
! 4:1
! 0
|-
| ''ign''
| IW
| IR
| FC
| U
| ''resv''
| physical address
| next level
| ''ign''
| D
| A
| ''ign''
| P
|}

{| class="wikitable"
|+ Page Directory Entry (PDE)
! 63
! 62
! 61
! 60:52
! 51:12
! 11:9
! 8:6
! 5
! 4:1
! 0
|-
| ''ign''
| IW
| IR
| ''resv''
| physical address
| next level
| ''ign''
| A
| ''ign''
| P
|}

== Commands ==

Each command entry is 128 bits in size.

{| class="wikitable"
|+ Command entry
|-
!colspan="1"  style="width:4em" | Offset
!colspan="1"  style="width:4em" | 63:60
!colspan="15" style="width:60em"| 59:0
|-
| +0
| Opcode
| First opcode dependent operand
|-
| +8
|colspan="2"| Second opcode dependent operand
|}

To send commands, the '''Command Buffer Base Register''' must be programmed. It must point to a ring buffer aligned to a 4KiB boundary.
The '''Command Buffer Head Pointer Register''' and '''Command Buffer Tail Pointer Register''' are automatically reset to 0 when the base register is written to.

{| class="wikitable"
|+ Command Buffer Base Register
!colspan="1"  style="width:4em" | 63:60
!colspan="1"  style="width:4em" | 59:56
!colspan="1"  style="width:4em" | 55:52
!colspan="10" style="width:40em"| 51:12
!colspan="3"  style="width:12em"| 11:00
|-
| /
| Length
| /
|colspan="10"| Base
| /
|-
|}

{| class="wikitable
|+ Length encoding
! Encoding
! Number of entries
! Byte size
|-
| 0-7
|colspan="2"| (reserved)
|-
| 8
| 256 entries
| 4 KiB
|-
| 9
| 512 entries
| 8 KiB
|-
|colspan="3" style="text-align:center"| ...
|-
| 15
| 32768 entries
| 512 KiB
|}

{| class="wikitable"
|+ Command Buffer Head Pointer Register
!colspan="11" style="width:44em"| 63:19
!colspan="4"  style="width:16em"| 18:4
!colspan="1"  style="width:4em" | 3:0
|-
|colspan="11"| /
|colspan="4" | Head pointer
|colspan="1" | /
|}

{| class="wikitable"
|+ Command Buffer Tail Pointer Register
!colspan="11" style="width:44em"| 63:19
!colspan="4"  style="width:16em"| 18:4
!colspan="1"  style="width:4em" | 3:0
|-
|colspan="11"| /
|colspan="4" | Tail pointer
|colspan="1" | /
|}

To notify the IOMMU, the Tail Pointer Register must be incremented, wrapping if necessary (modulo ring buffer size).

The IOMMU will increment the Head Pointer Register when a command has been fetched.
This does not mean the command has been processed! To ensure a command has been processed, use COMPLETION_WAIT.

Commands are only processed when '''CmdBufRun=1'''. Modifying the Base Register or the Head Pointer Register is only allowed when CmdBufRun=0.

=== 1. COMPLETION_WAIT ===

=== 2. INVALIDATE_DEVTAB_ENTRY ===

=== 3. INVALIDATE_IOMMU_PAGES ===

=== 4. INVALIDATE_IOTLB_PAGES ===

=== 5. INVALIDATE_INTERRUPT_TABLE ===

=== 6. PREFETCH_IOMMU_PAGES ===

=== 7. COMPLETE_PPR_REQUEST ===

=== 8. INVALIDATE_IOMMU_ALL ===

=== 9. INSERT_GUEST_EVENT ===

=== 10. RESET_VMMIO ===

== Events ==

=== 1. ILLEGAL_DEV_TABLE_ENTRY ===

=== 2. IO_PAGE_FAULT ===

=== 3. DEV_TAB_HARDWARE_ERROR ===

=== 4. PAGE_TAB_HARDWARE_ERROR ===

=== 5. ILLEGAL_COMMAND_ERROR ===

=== 6. COMMAND_HARDWARE_ERROR ===

=== 7. IOTLB_INV_TIMEOUT ===

=== 8. INVALID_DEVICE_REQUEST ===

=== 9. INVALID_PPR_REQUEST ===

=== 10. EVENT_COUNTER_ZERO ===

=== 11. GUEST_EVENT_FAULT ===

=== 12. VIOMMU_HARDWARE_ERROR ===

=== 13. RMP_PAGE_FAULT ===

=== 14. RMP_HARDWARE_ERROR ===

== Interrupt Remapping ==

=== MSI / MSI-X ===

To remap MSI the address need to be configured to point to &lt;code&gt;FD_F8xx_xxxx&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;See Table 3 in specification.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Registers ==

=== PCI configuration space ===

All accesses ''must'' be 32-bits and aligned to a 32-bit boundary.
Software should write zeros to reserved bits.

==== Base Capability (id=0xf) ====

{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Offset
! Name
|-
| 0x00
| Capability Header
|-
| 0x04
| Base Address Low Register
|-
| 0x08
| Base Address High Register
|-
| 0x0C
| Range Register
|-
| 0x10
| Miscellaneous Information Register 0
|-
| 0x14
| Miscellaneous Information Register 1
|-
|}

=== MMIO ===

All accesses ''should'' be 64-bits and properly aligned,
but smaller power-of-two accesses (32/16/8-bits) are also permitted.
Larger accesses (128/...-bits) are ''not'' permitted.

{| class="wikitable" style="table-layout:fixed"
! Offset
!style="width:50%"| Name (+4)
!style="width:50%"| Name (+0)
|-
!colspan="3"| 0x0000 to 0x1000
|-
| 0x0000
|colspan="2"| Device Table Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0008
|colspan="2"| Command Buffer Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0010
|colspan="2"| Event Log Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0018
|colspan="2"| IOMMU Control Register
|-
| 0x0020
|colspan="2"| IOMMU Exclusion Base Register / Completion Store Base Register
|-
| 0x0028
|colspan="2"| IOMMU Exclusion Range Limit Register / Completion Store Limit Register
|-
| 0x0030
|colspan="2"| IOMMU Extended Feature Register
|-
| 0x0038
|colspan="2"| PPR Log Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0040
|colspan="2"| IOMMU Hardware Event Upper Register
|-
| 0x0048
|colspan="2"| IOMMU Hardware Event Lower Register
|-
| 0x0050
|colspan="2"| Hardware Event Status Register
|-
| 0x0058
|colspan="2"| (unmapped)
|-
| 0x0060
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 0
|-
| 0x0068
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 1
|-
| 0x0070
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 2
|-
| 0x0078
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 3
|-
| 0x0080
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 4
|-
| 0x0088
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 5
|-
| 0x0090
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 6
|-
| 0x0098
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 7
|-
| 0x00A0
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 8
|-
| 0x00A8
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 9
|-
| 0x00B0
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 10
|-
| 0x00B8
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 11
|-
| 0x00C0
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 12
|-
| 0x00C8
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 13
|-
| 0x00D0
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 14
|-
| 0x00D8
|colspan="2"| SMI Filter Register 15
|-
| 0x00E0
|colspan="2"| Guest Virtual APIC Log Base Address Register
|-
| 0x00E8
|colspan="2"| Guest Virtual APIC Log Tail Address Register
|-
| 0x00F0
|colspan="2"| PPR Log B Base Address Register
|-
| 0x00F8
|colspan="2"| Event Log B Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0100
|colspan="2"| Device Table Segment 1 Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0108
|colspan="2"| Device Table Segment 2 Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0110
|colspan="2"| Device Table Segment 3 Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0118
|colspan="2"| Device Table Segment 4 Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0120
|colspan="2"| Device Table Segment 5 Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0128
|colspan="2"| Device Table Segment 6 Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0130
|colspan="2"| Device Table Segment 7 Base Address Register
|-
| 0x0138
|colspan="2"| Device-Specific Feature Extension (DSFX) Register
|-
| 0x0140
|colspan="2"| Device-Specific Control Extension (DSCX) Register
|-
| 0x0148
|colspan="2"| Device-Specific Status Extension (DSSX) Register
|-
| 0x0150
| MSI Vector Register 1
| MSI Vector Register 0
|-
| 0x0158
| MSI Address Low Register
| MSI Capability Header Register
|-
| 0x0160
| MSI Data Register
| MSI Address High Register
|-
| 0x0168
| IOMMU Performance Optimization Control Register
| MSI Mapping Capability Header Register
|-
| 0x0170
|colspan="2"| XT IOMMU General Interrupt Control Register
|-
| 0x0178
|colspan="2"| XT IOMMU PPR Interrupt Control Register
|-
| 0x0180
|colspan="2"| XT IOMMU GA Log Interrupt Control Register
|-
| 0x0188
|colspan="2"| (reserved)
|-
| 0x0190
|colspan="2"| vIOMMU Status Register
|-
| 0x0198
|colspan="2"| (reserved)
|-
| 0x01A0
|colspan="2"| IOMMU Extended Feature 2 Register
|-
|colspan="3"| ...
|-
| 0x0200
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 0 Base Register
|-
| 0x0208
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 0 Relocation Register
|-
| 0x0210
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 0 Length Register
|-
| 0x0218
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 1 Base Register
|-
| 0x0220
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 1 Relocation Register
|-
| 0x0228
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 1 Length Register
|-
| 0x0230
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 2 Base Register
|-
| 0x0238
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 2 Relocation Register
|-
| 0x0240
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 2 Length Register
|-
| 0x0248
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 3 Base Register
|-
| 0x0250
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 3 Relocation Register
|-
| 0x0258
|colspan="2"| MARC Aperture 3 Length Register
|-
| 0x0260
|colspan="2"| (reserved)
|-
|colspan="3"| ...
|-
!colspan="3"| 0x1000 to 0x2000
|-
| 0x1000
|colspan="2"| (reserved)
|-
|colspan="3"| ...
|-
| 0x1FF8
|colspan="2"| IOMMU Reserved Register
|-
!colspan="3"| 0x2000 to 0x3000
|-
| 0x2000
|colspan="2"| Command Buffer Head Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2008
|colspan="2"| Command Buffer Tail Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2010
|colspan="2"| Event Log Head Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2018
|colspan="2"| Event Log Tail Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2020
|colspan="2"| IOMMU Status Register
|-
| 0x2028
|colspan="2"| (reserved)
|-
| 0x2030
|colspan="2"| IOMMU PPR Log Head Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2038
|colspan="2"| IOMMU PPR Log Tail Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2040
|colspan="2"| Guest Virtual APIC Log Head Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2048
|colspan="2"| Guest Virtual APIC Log Tail Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2050
|colspan="2"| PPR Log B Head Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2058
|colspan="2"| PPR Log B Tail Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2060
|colspan="2"| Event Log B Head Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2068
|colspan="2"| Event Log B Tail Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2070
|colspan="2"| Event Log B Head Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2078
|colspan="2"| Event Log B Tail Pointer Register
|-
| 0x2080
|colspan="2"| PPR Log Auto Response Register
|-
| 0x2088
|colspan="2"| PPR Log Overflow Early Indicator Register
|-
| 0x2090
|colspan="2"| PPR Log B Overflow Early Indicator Register
|-
| 0x2098
|colspan="2"| (reserved)
|}

== Troubleshooting ==

=== QEMU: no DMA translation ===

DMA translation needs to explicitly enabled:

&lt;pre&gt;
-device amd-iommu,dma-remap=on
&lt;/pre&gt;

Interrupt remapping, IOTLB and other features also need to be enabled explicitly. Run with &lt;code&gt;help&lt;/code&gt; to see all options:

&lt;pre&gt;
-device amd-iommu,help
&lt;/pre&gt;

== See also ==

&lt;references /&gt;

=== External Links ===

* [https://docs.amd.com/api/khub/documents/2oKZlc87KNCKiT3B~xJjHg/content AMD I/O Virtualization Technology (IOMMU) Specification (48882-PUB—Rev 3.11—Apr 2026)]

[[Category:X86 Virtualization]]
[[Category:X86-64]]</text>
      <sha1>8tz62yq22w7qrofz6ursqhftdyuw9kq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>CPU Registers x86-64</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3774</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30266</id>
      <parentid>29722</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-16T17:44:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Makaroneder</username>
        <id>1943</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Replace source tag with syntaxhighlight tag</comment>
      <origin>30266</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="10973" sha1="9nybui8insku9k13jiu91kqsble2s4d" xml:space="preserve">==General Purpose Registers==

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
! colspan=5 | Monikers
! rowspan=2 | Description
|-
! 64-bit
! 32-bit
! 16-bit
! 8 high bits of lower 16 bits
! 8-bit
|-
| RAX
| EAX
| AX
| AH
| AL
| Accumulator
|-
| RBX
| EBX
| BX
| BH
| BL
| Base
|-
| RCX
| ECX
| CX
| CH
| CL
| Counter
|-
| RDX
| EDX
| DX
| DH
| DL
| Data (commonly extends the A register)
|-
| RSI
| ESI
| SI
| N/A
| SIL
| Source index for string operations
|-
| RDI
| EDI
| DI
| N/A
| DIL
| Destination index for string operations
|-
| RSP
| ESP
| SP
| N/A
| SPL
| Stack Pointer
|-
| RBP
| EBP
| BP
| N/A
| BPL
| Base Pointer (meant for stack frames)
|-
| R8
| R8D
| R8W
| N/A
| R8B
| General purpose
|-
| R9
| R9D
| R9W
| N/A
| R9B
| General purpose
|-
| R10
| R10D
| R10W
| N/A
| R10B
| General purpose
|-
| R11
| R11D
| R11W
| N/A
| R11B
| General purpose
|-
| R12
| R12D
| R12W
| N/A
| R12B
| General purpose
|-
| R13
| R13D
| R13W
| N/A
| R13B
| General purpose
|-
| R14
| R14D
| R14W
| N/A
| R14B
| General purpose
|-
| R15
| R15D
| R15W
| N/A
| R15B
| General purpose
|}

Note: you cannot access ''AH'', ''BH'', ''CH'' and ''DH'' when using the REX.W instruction prefix.
This prefix is added (automatically by assemblers) when an operand contains a 64-bit register.

==Pointer Registers==

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
! colspan=3 | Monikers
! rowspan=2 | Description
|-
! 64-bit
! 32-bit
! 16-bit
|-
| RIP
| EIP
| IP
| Instruction Pointer
|-
|}

Note: The instruction pointer can only be used in RIP-relative addressing, which was introduced with long mode.

==Segment Registers==

All these are 16 bits long.

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
! Moniker
! Description
|-
| CS
| Code Segment
|-
| DS
| Data Segment
|-
| SS
| Stack Segment
|-
| ES
| Extra Segment (used for string operations)
|-
| FS
| General-purpose Segment
|-
| GS
| General-purpose Segment
|-
|}

Segments of ''CS'', ''DS'', ''ES'', and ''SS'' are treated as if their base was 0 no matter what the segment descriptors in the GDT say.
Exceptions are ''FS'' and ''GS'' which have MSRs to change their base.

Limit checks are disabled for all segments.

==RFLAGS Register==

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
! Bit(s)
! Label
! Description
|-
| 0
| CF
| Carry Flag
|-
| 1
| 1
| Reserved
|-
| 2
| PF
| Parity Flag
|-
| 3
| 0
| Reserved
|-
| 4
| AF
| Auxiliary Carry Flag
|-
| 5
| 0
| Reserved
|-
| 6
| ZF
| Zero Flag
|-
| 7
| SF
| Sign Flag
|-
| 8
| TF
| Trap Flag
|-
| 9
| IF
| Interrupt Enable Flag
|-
| 10
| DF
| Direction Flag
|-
| 11
| OF
| Overflow Flag
|-
| 12-13
| IOPL
| I/O Privilege Level
|-
| 14
| NT
| Nested Task
|-
| 15
| 0
| Reserved
|-
| 16
| RF
| Resume Flag
|-
| 17
| VM
| Virtual-8086 Mode
|-
| 18
| AC
| Alignment Check / Access Control
|-
| 19
| VIF
| Virtual Interrupt Flag
|-
| 20
| VIP
| Virtual Interrupt Pending
|-
| 21
| ID
| ID Flag
|-
| 22-63
| 0
| Reserved
|-
|}

==Control Registers==

====CR0====

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
! Bit(s)
! Label
! Description
|-
| 0
| PE
| Protected Mode Enable
|-
| 1
| MP
| Monitor Co-Processor
|-
| 2
| EM
| Emulation
|-
| 3
| TS
| Task Switched
|-
| 4
| ET
| Extension Type
|-
| 5
| NE
| Numeric Error
|-
| 6-15
| 0
| Reserved
|-
| 16
| WP
| Write Protect
|-
| 17
| 0
| Reserved
|-
| 18
| AM
| Alignment Mask
|-
| 19-28
| 0
| Reserved
|-
| 29
| NW
| Not-Write Through
|-
| 30
| CD
| Cache Disable
|-
| 31
| PG
| Paging
|-
| 32-63
| 0
| Reserved
|-
|}
NOTE that this register is the only control register that can be written and read via 2 ways unlike the other that can be accessed only via the MOV instruction
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="asm"&gt;
;way 1:
;write:
mov cr0,reg32(64)
;read:
mov reg32(64),cr0 
;----------------------
;way 2:
;write:
lmsw reg16(32/64) ; the 'w' in lms(w) stands for word size (16 bit) but the instruction itself can modify the upper 48 bit of cr0 using instruction overrides.

;read:
smsw reg16(32/64) ; SAME as above
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

====CR2====

This control register contains the linear (virtual) address which triggered a page fault, available in the page fault's interrupt handler.

====CR3====

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
! colspan=2 | Bit(s)
! Label
! Description
! Condition
|-
| rowspan=4 | 0-11
| 0-2
| 0
| Reserved
| rowspan=4 | CR4.PCIDE = 0
|-
| 3
| PWT
| Page-Level Write Through
|-
| 5
| PCD
| Page-Level Cache Disable
|-
| 5-11
| 0
| Reserved
|-
| colspan=2 | 0-11
| colspan=2 | PCID
| CR4.PCIDE = 1
|-
| colspan=2 | 12-63
| colspan=2 | Physical Base Address of the PML4
|-
|}
Note that this must be page aligned

====CR4====

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
! Bit(s)
! Label
! Description
|-
| 0
| VME
| Virtual-8086 Mode Extensions
|-
| 1
| PVI
| Protected Mode Virtual Interrupts
|-
| 2
| TSD
| Time Stamp enabled only in ring 0
|-
| 3
| DE
| Debugging Extensions
|-
| 4
| PSE
| Page Size Extension
|-
| 5
| PAE
| Physical Address Extension
|-
| 6
| MCE
| Machine Check Exception
|-
| 7
| PGE
| Page Global Enable
|-
| 8
| PCE
| Performance Monitoring Counter Enable 
|-
| 9
| OSFXSR
| OS support for fxsave and fxrstor instructions
|-
| 10
| OSXMMEXCPT
| OS Support for unmasked simd floating point exceptions
|-
| 11
| UMIP
| User-Mode Instruction Prevention (SGDT, SIDT, SLDT, SMSW, and STR are disabled in user mode)
|-
| 12
| LA57
| 5 level paging
|-
| 13
| VMXE
| Virtual Machine Extensions Enable
|-
| 14
| SMXE
| Safer Mode Extensions Enable
|-
| 15
| 0
| Reserved
|-
| 16
| FSGSBASE
| Enables the instructions RDFSBASE, RDGSBASE, WRFSBASE, and WRGSBASE 
|-
| 17
| PCIDE
| PCID Enable
|-
| 18
| OSXSAVE
| XSAVE And Processor Extended States Enable
|-
| 19
| 0
| Reserved
|-
| 20
| SMEP
| Supervisor Mode Executions Protection Enable
|-
| 21
| SMAP
| Supervisor Mode Access Protection Enable
|-
| 22
| PKE
| Enable protection keys for user-mode pages
|-
| 23
| CET
| Enable Control-flow Enforcement Technology
|-
| 24
| PKS
| Enable protection keys for supervisor-mode pages
|-
| 25-63
| 0
| Reserved
|-
|}

====CR8====

CR8 is a new register accessible in 64-bit mode using the REX prefix. CR8 is used to prioritize external [[interrupts]] and is referred to as the task-priority register (TPR).

The AMD64 architecture allows software to define up to 15 external interrupt-priority classes. Priority classes are numbered from 1 to 15, with priority-class 1 being the lowest and priority-class 15 the highest. CR8 uses the four low-order bits for specifying a task priority and the remaining 60 bits are reserved and must be written with zeros.

System software can use the TPR register to temporarily block low-priority interrupts from interrupting a high-priority task. This is accomplished by loading TPR with a value corresponding to the highest-priority interrupt that is to be blocked. For example, loading TPR with a value of 9 (1001b) blocks all interrupts with a priority class of 9 or less, while allowing all interrupts with a priority class of 10 or more to be recognized. Loading TPR with 0 enables all external interrupts. Loading TPR with 15 (1111b) disables all external interrupts.

The TPR is cleared to 0 on reset.

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
!Bit
!Purpose
|-
|0-3
|Priority
|-
|4-63
|Reserved
|}

====CR1, CR5-7, CR9-15====

Reserved, the cpu will throw a #ud exeption when trying to access them.

==MSRs==

====IA32_EFER====

Extended Feature Enable Register (EFER) is a [[MSR|model-specific register]] added in the AMD K6 processor, to allow enabling the SYSCALL/SYSRET instruction, and later for entering and exiting [[x86-64|long mode]]. This register becomes architectural in [[AMD64]] and has been adopted by Intel. Its MSR number is 0xC0000080.
 
{| class="wikitable"
!Bit
!Name
!Label
!Ops
!Description
|- |-
|0
|SYSCALL Enable
|IA32_EFER.SCE
|R/W
|Enables SYSCALL/SYSRET instructions in 64-bit mode.
|-
|1
| colspan="4" rowspan="7" |Reserved
|-
|2
|-
|3
|-
|4
|-
|5
|-
|6
|-
|7
|-
|8
|IA-32e Mode Enable
|IA32_EFER.LME
|R/W
|Enables IA-32e mode operation.
|-
|9
| colspan="4" | Reserved
|-
|10
|IA-32e Mode Active
|IA32_EFER.LMA
|R
|Indicates IA-32e mode is active when set.
|-
|11
|Execute Disable Bit Enable
| IA32_EFER.NXE
| R/W
|
|-
|⋮
| colspan="4" |Reserved
|}
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Table from https://wiki.jwo.cz/index.php?title=IA32_EFER.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====FS.base, GS.base====
MSRs with the addresses 0xC0000100 (for FS) and 0xC0000101 (for GS) contain the base addresses of the FS and GS segment registers. These are commonly used for thread-pointers in user code and CPU-local pointers in kernel code. Safe to contain anything, since use of a segment does not confer additional privileges to user code.

In newer CPUs, these can also be written with WRFSBASE and WRGSBASE instructions at any privilege level.

====KernelGSBase====
MSR with the address 0xC0000102. Is basically a buffer that gets exchanged with GS.base after a swapgs instruction. Usually used to seperate kernel and user use of the GS register.

==Debug Registers==

====DR0 - DR3 ====

Contain linear addresses of up to 4 breakpoints. If paging is enabled, they are translated to physical addresses.

====DR6====

It permits the debugger to determine which debug conditions have occurred. When an enabled debug exception is triggered, low order bits 0-3 are set before entering debug exception handler.

==== DR7====

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
!Bit
!Description
|-
|0
|Local DR0 Breakpoint
|-
|1
|Global DR0 Breakpoint
|-
|2
|Local DR1 Breakpoint
|-
|3
|Global DR1 Breakpoint
|-
|4
|Local DR2 Breakpoint
|-
|5
|Global DR2 Breakpoint
|-
| 6
| Local DR3 Breakpoint
|-
|7
|Global DR3 Breakpoint
|-
|16-17
|Conditions for DR0
|-
|18-19
|Size of DR0 Breakpoint
|-
|20-21
|Conditions for DR1
|-
|22-23
|Size of DR1 Breakpoint
|-
|24-25
|Conditions for DR2
|-
|26-27
|Size of DR2 Breakpoint
|-
|28-29
|Conditions for DR3
|-
|30-31
|Size of DR3 Breakpoint
|-
|}
A local breakpoint bit deactivates on hardware task switches, while a global does not.&lt;br&gt;
00b condition means execution break, 01b means a write watchpoint, and 11b means an R/W watchpoint. 10b is reserved for I/O R/W (unsupported).

==Test Registers==

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
!Name
!Description
|-
|TR3 - TR5
|Undocumented
|-
|TR6
|Test Command Register
|-
|TR7
|Test Data Register
|-
|}

==Protected Mode Registers==

====GDTR====

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
|-
! colspan="2" |Operand Size
! rowspan="2" |Label
! rowspan="2" |Description
|-
!64-bit
! 32-bit
|-
| colspan="2" style="text-align:center" |Bits 0-15
|Limit
|Size of [[GDT]]
|-
| Bits 16-79
|Bits 16-47
|Base
| Starting Address of GDT
|-
|}

====LDTR====

Stores the segment selector of the [[LDT]].

====TR ====

Stores the segment selector of the [[TSS]].

====IDTR====

{| class="wikitable" border="1"
! colspan="2" |Operand Size
! rowspan="2" |Label
! rowspan="2" |Description
|-
!64-bit
! 32-bit
|-
| colspan="2" style="text-align:center" |Bits 0-15
|Limit
|Size of [[IDT]]
|-
|Bits 16-79
|Bits 16-47
|Base
|Starting Address of IDT
|-
|}

[[Category:CPU Registers]]
[[Category:X86 CPU]]
[[Category:X86-64]]</text>
      <sha1>9nybui8insku9k13jiu91kqsble2s4d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Creating a 64-bit kernel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2257</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30270</id>
      <parentid>27945</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-16T17:47:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Makaroneder</username>
        <id>1943</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Replace source tag with syntaxhighlight tag</comment>
      <origin>30270</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="11721" sha1="pn3hxlesp6kncygz4uc2ynm5m1q66gy" xml:space="preserve">{{Rating|2}}{{Template:Kernel designs}}
{{In_Progress}}
{{Disputed|Talk:Creating_a_64-bit_kernel#Disputed}}

== Prerequisites ==

Make sure that you have the following done before proceeding:

* Have [[GCC_Cross-Compiler|built a cross-compiler]] for the x86_64-elf target.
* Read up on long mode and how to [[X86-64|initialize/use it]] (if you intend on not using a 64-bit aware bootloader or rolling your own).
* Decide now on how to load your kernel - your own bootloader, [[GRUB]] (with separate loader executable), GRUB2 (elf64 + 32-bit bootstrap code), or a 64-bit capable bootloader such as [[Limine]] or [[BOOTBOOT]].

== The Main Kernel ==
The kernel should run in a uniform environment. Let's make this simple for now...

=== kernel.c ===
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
void kernel_main(void)
{
    /* What goes here is up to you */
}
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

== Compiling ==
Compile each source file like any piece of C code, just remember to use the cross-compiler and the proper options.
Linking will be done later...

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;
x86_64-elf-gcc -ffreestanding -mcmodel=large -mno-red-zone -mno-mmx -mno-sse -mno-sse2 -c foo.c -o foo.o
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

The -mcmodel=large argument enables us to run the kernel at any 64-bit virtual memory address we want. In fact, using the 'large' code model is discouraged due to its inefficiency, but it can be fine as a start. Check the [[System V ABI|SysV AMD64 ABI]] document for extra details.

You will need to instruct GCC not to use the the AMD64 ABI 128-byte 'red zone', which resides below the stack pointer, or your kernel will be ''interrupt unsafe''. Check this [http://forum.osdev.org/viewtopic.php?t=21720 thread] on the forums for extra context.

We disable [[SSE]] floating point ops. They need special %cr0 and %cr4 setup that we're not ready for. Otherwise, several #UD and #NM exceptions will be triggered.

== Linking ==
The kernel will be linked as an x86_64 executable, to run at a virtual higher-half address. We use a linker script:

=== link.ld ===
 ENTRY(_start)
 SECTIONS
 {
     . = KERNEL_VMA;
 
     .text : AT(ADDR(.text) - KERNEL_VMA)
     {
         _code = .;
         *(.text)
         *(.rodata*)
         . = ALIGN(4096);
     }
 
    .data : AT(ADDR(.data) - KERNEL_VMA)
    {
         _data = .;
         *(.data)
         . = ALIGN(4096);
    }
 
    .eh_frame : AT(ADDR(.eh_frame) - KERNEL_VMA)
    {
        _ehframe = .;
        *(.eh_frame)
         . = ALIGN(4096);
    }
 
    .bss : AT(ADDR(.bss) - KERNEL_VMA)
    {
        _bss = .;
        *(.bss)
 
        /*
         * You usually need to include generated COMMON symbols
         * under kernel BSS section or use gcc's -fno-common
         */
 
         *(COMMON)
        . = ALIGN(4096);
    }
 
    _end = .;
 
    /DISCARD/ :
    {
         *(.comment)
    }
 }

Feel free to edit this linker script to suit your needs. Set ENTRY(...) to your entry function, and KERNEL_VMA to your base virtual address.

You can link the kernel like this:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="bash"&gt;x86_64-elf-gcc -ffreestanding &lt;other options&gt; -T &lt;linker script&gt; &lt;all object files&gt; -o &lt;kernel executable&gt; -nostdlib -lgcc&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

'''Note''': Obviously there is no bootstrap assembly yet, which is the hard part of starting out, and you can't link without it.

== Loading ==
Before you can actually use your kernel, you need to deal with the hard job of loading it. Here are your four options:

=== With your own boot loader ===
This method is the simplest (since you write all the code), though it requires the most work.

I won't give any code, but the basic outline is:
* Set up a stable environment
* Do Protected Mode readying stuff (GDT, IDT, A20 gate, etc.)
* Enter Protected Mode (or skip this step and [[Entering Long Mode Directly|enter long mode directly]])
* Parse kernel [[ELF]] headers (if kernel is separate from executable)
* Set up Long Mode readying stuff (PAE, PML4, etc.) - Remember to set up the higher-half addressing!
* Enter Long Mode by far jump to the kernel entry point in (virtual) memory

=== With a 64 bit aware loader ===
Open Source boot loaders written for long mode kernels already exist, you don't have to reinvent the wheel. Unlike GRUB (which does not support switching to long mode), bootloaders such as [[Limine]] or [[BOOTBOOT]] can load your 64-bit kernel directly by doing all the things listed in the previous section (and more). It saves you the struggle to write and properly link bootstrap code or to implement your own boot loader entirely from scratch. Therefore using a 64-bit aware bootloader is a nice and easy, reasonably bullet-proof, choice for beginners.

=== With legacy GRUB ===
'''Note''': The advise in this section is bit questionable in its current form.
See [[Creating_a_64-bit_kernel_using_a_separate_loader|Creating a 64-bit kernel using a separate loader]]

This requires the use of [[GRUB]] or another multiboot1-compliant loader. This may be the most error free of the four, but creating a multiboot-compatible kernel properly has its own set of pitfalls.

A quick rundown:
* Set up a stable environment
* Read the multiboot information struct to see where GRUB loaded your kernel (look at the module section)
* Parse kernel [[ELF]] headers
* Set up Long Mode readying stuff (PAE, PML4, etc.) - Remember to set up the higher-half addressing!
* Enter Long Mode by far jump to the kernel entry point

Note that this code has to be stored in a elf32 format and must contain the multiboot1-header.

Also remember to set the text section to start at 0x100000 (-Ttext 0x100000) when linking your loader.

Set up GRUB to boot your loader as a kernel in its own right, and your actual kernel as a module. Something like this in menu.lst:
 title My Kernel
 kernel --type=multiboot &lt;loader executable&gt;
 module &lt;kernel executable&gt;

=== With a 32-bit bootstrap in your kernel ===

This requires the use of any ELF64-compatible loader that loads into protected-mode (GRUB2, or patched GRUB Legacy). This may be the simplest in the long run, but is more difficult to set up.
Note that GRUB2, which implements [http://download.savannah.gnu.org/releases-noredirect/grub/phcoder/multiboot.pdf Multiboot 2], does not support switching into long mode.

First, create an assembly file like the following, which will set up virtual addressing and long mode:
==== bootstrap.S ====
 .section .text
 .code32
 
 multiboot_header:
     (only needed if you're using multiboot)
 
 bootstrap:
     (32-bit to 64-bit code goes here)
     (jump to 64-bit code)

Then, add the following to your original linker file:
==== link.ld ====
 ...
 ENTRY(bootstrap)
 ...
 SECTIONS
 {
     . = KERNEL_LMA;
 
     .bootstrap :
     {
         &lt;path of bootstrap object&gt; (.text)
     }
 
     . += KERNEL_VMA;
 
     .text : AT(ADDR(.text) - KERNEL_VMA)
     {
         _code = .;
         *(EXCLUDE_FILE(*&lt;path of bootstrap object&gt;) .text)
         *(.rodata*)
         . = ALIGN(4096);
     }
 ...
The above edits allow the linker to link the bootstrap code with physical addressing, as virtual addressing is set up by the bootstrap.
Note that in this case, KERNEL_VMA will be equivalent to 0x0, meaning that text would have a virtual address at KERNEL_LMA + KERNEL_VMA instead of just at KERNEL_VMA.
Change '+=' to '=' and your bootstrap code if you do not want this behaviour.

Compile and link as usual, just remember to compile the bootstrap code as well!

Set up GRUB2 to boot your kernel (depends on your bootloader) with grub.cfg:
 menuentry "My Kernel" {
     multiboot &lt;kernel executable&gt;
 }

==== With Visual C++ ====
The technique for creating a 64 bit kernel with a 32 bit bootstrap is similar to GCC. You need to create an assembly bootstrap with nasm (masm may work, but the author uses nasm).
Note that this stub '''must''' be assembled to a ''64'' bit object file (-f win64). Your stub then has a BITS 32 directive.
Note that, although nasm will not complain about this, Microsoft link will. It complains about address relocations, due to the memory model settings (/LARGEADDRESSAWARE, which is required for /DRIVER).
As such, you need a method of generating the correct 32 bit code, while fooling link into generating a 64 bit relocation. Here is a macro for you:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang='asm'&gt;
;Encode 32 bit moves without the ADDR32 issue
%macro mov_abs32 2
%if %1==eax
db 0xB8
%elif %1==ebx
db 0xBB
%elif %1==ecx
db 0xB9
%elif %1==edx
db 0xBA
%elif %1==edi
db 0xBF
%elif %1==esi
db 0xBE
%elif %1==ebp
db 0xBD
%elif %1==esp
db 0xBC
%else
%error "Unknown register"
%endif
dq %2+(0x90909090 &lt;&lt; 32)
%endmacro
;This translates as mov %1, %2 NOP NOP NOP NOP
;Example usage:
;mov_abs32 eax, (gdtr-KADDR_OFFSET)
;lgdt [eax]
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

== Possible Problems ==
You may experience some problems. Fix them '''immediately''' or risk spending a lot of time debugging later...

=== My kernel is way too big! ===
Try each of the following, in order:
* Try linking your kernel with the option "-z max-page-size=0x1000" to force the linker to use 4kb pages.
* Make sure you're compiling with the -nostdlib option (equivalent to passing the both -nodefaultlibs and -nostartfiles options).
* You can try changing the OUTPUT_FORMAT to elf64-little.
* Try cross-compiling the '''latest''' version of binutils and gcc.

== Kernel Virtual Memory ==
(This section is based on notes by Travis Geiselbrecht (geist) at the osdev IRC channel)

Long mode provides essentially an infinite amount of address space. An interesting design decision is how to map and use the kernel address space. Linux approaches the problem by permanently mapping the -2GB virtual region 0xffffffff80000000 -&gt; 0xffffffffffffffff to physical address 0x0 upwards. Kernel data structures, which are usually allocated by kmalloc() and the slab allocator, reside above the 0xffffffff80000000 virtual base and are allocate from the physical 0 -&gt; 2GB zone. This necessitates the ability of 'zoning' the page allocator, asking the page allocator to returning a page frame from a specific region, and only from that region. If a physical address above 2GB needs to accessed, the kernel temporarily map it to its space in a temporary mapping space below the virtual addresses base. The Linux approach provides the advantage of not having to modify the page tables much which means less TLB shootdowns on an SMP system.

Another approach is to treat the kernel address space as any other address space and dynamically map its regions. This provides the advantage of simplifying the page allocator by avoiding the need of physical memory 'zones': all physical RAM is available for any part of the kernel. An example of this approach is mapping the kernel to 0xfffffff800000000 as usual. Below that virtual address you put a large mapping for the entire physical address space, and use the virtual 0xfffffff800000000 -&gt; 0xffffffffffffffff region above kernel memory area as a temporary mappings space.

==See Also==
===Articles===
* [[X86-64]]
===Forum Threads===
* [http://forum.osdev.org/viewtopic.php?f=8&amp;t=16779 Creating a 64-bit Kernel Tutorial] about this article
* [http://forum.osdev.org/viewtopic.php?p=170634 Linker-script writers beware: COMMON Symbols] on the obscure 'COMMON' symbols and their effect on BSS
* [http://forum.osdev.org/viewtopic.php?t=21720 Long-mode Kernels and the AMD64 ABI 'Red Zone'] on the 'red zone' and its major effect on interrupt handling
* [http://forum.osdev.org/viewtopic.php?f=1&amp;p=136701 Leaving long mode] to protected mode
* [http://forum.osdev.org/viewtopic.php?f=1&amp;t=17213 Switching from long mode to compatibility mode]

[[Category:Tutorials|Creating a 64-bit kernel]]
[[Category:X86-64|Creating a 64-bit kernel]]
[[Category:Kernel]]</text>
      <sha1>pn3hxlesp6kncygz4uc2ynm5m1q66gy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>X86-64</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1447</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30486</id>
      <parentid>30261</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-15T15:10:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tocariimaa</username>
        <id>2217</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* 64 bit Environment Models */ use wikitable class</comment>
      <origin>30486</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="10229" sha1="qxt3ariwrx2s15wss43ss7tour5sb6l" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:x86-64}}
This article discusses '''x86-64''' CPUs (AMD64 and Intel's equivalent [[EM64T]] implementation). [[IA-64]] (Itanium) is '''really''' a different beast and not addressed here.

== Features ==

===Long Mode===

Long mode extends general registers to 64 bits (RAX, RBX, RIP, RSP, RFLAGS, etc), and adds eight additional integer registers (R8, R9, ..., R15) plus eight more SSE registers (XMM8 to XMM15) to the CPU. Linear addresses are extended to 64 bit (however, a given CPU may implement less than this) and the physical address space is extended to 52 bits (a given CPU may implement less than this). In essence long mode adds another mode to the CPU.

Long mode does not support hardware task switching or virtual 8086 tasks. In long mode the current CS determines if the code currently running is 64 bit code (true long mode) or 32 bit code (compatibility mode), or even 16-bit protected mode code (still in compatibility mode). Using paging has become mandatory, and segmentation has been stripped down for performance reasons.

The first 64 bit CPUs from both Intel and AMD support 40 bit physical addresses and 48 bit linear addresses.

=== Segmentation in Long Mode ===

Segmentation in long mode functions with a flat model with the exception of two registers: FS and GS.  Setting the base address for these two segment registers is possible via two specific [[MSR|Model Specific Register (MSR)]]s, FS.base (C000_0100h) and GS.base (C000_0101h).  

Additionally there is a long mode specific instruction called [[SWAPGS]], which swaps the contents of GS.base and another MSR called KernelGSBase (C000_0102h).  This instruction is particularly useful for preserving kernel information for a specific logical processor core across context switches.  '''Note: This is an exchange operation'''.

=== Further information ===

''This feature overview is incomplete. Please see the [[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X86-64 Wikipedia article on x86-64]] for more information.

==Setting up==

===How do I detect if the CPU is 64 bits ?===

After calling CPUID with EAX=0x80000001, all AMD64 compliant processors have the longmode-capable-bit turned on in the extended feature flags (bit 29) in EDX. There are also other bits required by long mode; you can check them out in the CPUID docs in the [http://support.amd.com/us/Processor_TechDocs/24594.pdf AMD general purpose instruction reference] (Link dead, the original author probably meant "AMD64 Architecture Programmer’s Manual Volume 3: General Purpose and System Instructions", found here: http://developer.amd.com/resources/developer-guides-manuals/)

===How do I enable Long Mode ?===

The steps for enabling long mode are:
* Disable paging
* Set the PAE enable bit in CR4
* Load CR3 with the physical address of the PML4 (Level 4 Page Map)
* Enable long mode by setting the LME flag (bit 8) in MSR 0xC0000080 (aka [[CPU_Registers_x86-64#IA32_EFER|EFER]])
* Enable paging

''Reference: [https://www.intel.com/content/dam/www/public/us/en/documents/manuals/64-ia-32-architectures-software-developer-vol-3a-part-1-manual.pdf Intel 64 and IA-32 Architectures Software Developer's Manual], Section 9.8.5''

Now the CPU will be in compatibility mode, and instructions are still 32-bit.  To enter long mode, the D/B bit (bit 22, 2nd 32-bit value) of the GDT code segment must be clear (as it would be for a 16-bit code segment), and the L bit (bit 21, 2nd 32-bit value) of the GDT code segment must be set.  Once that is done, the CPU is in 64-bit long mode.

=== Are there restrictions on 32-bit code running in Legacy Mode ?===

x86-64 processors can operate in a legacy mode, they still start in real mode and 16 and 32 bit protected mode is still available (along with the associated Virtual 8086 mode). This means an x86 operating system, even DOS, will still run just fine. The only difference is that physical addresses can be up to 52 bits (or as many bits as implemented by the CPU) when PAE is used.

However, [[Virtual 8086 Mode]] does not exist in long/compatibility mode.

If you are running on a multi-processor system, you could send one processor a STARTUP IPI to a real mode memory address (see Intel MultiProcessor specification for more details) that loads a real mode program. The main problem with this approach is that it relies on multiple processors being present in the system.

===Entering Long Mode directly===

Protected mode must be entered before activating long mode. A minimal protected-mode environment must be established to allow long-mode initialization to take place. This environment must include the following:
* A protected-mode IDT for vectoring interrupts and exceptions to the appropriate handlers while in protected mode.
* The protected-mode interrupt and exception handlers referenced by the IDT.
* Gate descriptors for each handler must be loaded in the IDT.
:--''AMD64 docs, volume 2, section 14.4 (Enabling Protected Mode), 24593 Rev. 3.10 February 2005''

That being said, [[Topic:11093|we have a thread]] where Brendan shows how to enable 64-bit long mode with no 32-bit IDT and no 32-bit segments - be assured, however, that any paging-related exception that occurs in long mode before you enable 64-bit IDT will cause the processor to reset due to a triple fault.

There is also [[Entering Long Mode Directly|an example]] of this implemented in a [[bootloader]].

=== Notifying the BIOS ===

In order for the firmware built into the system to optimize itself for running in Long Mode, AMD recommends that the OS notify the BIOS about the intended target environment that the OS will be running in: 32-bit mode, 64-bit mode, or a mixture of both modes.  This can be done by calling the BIOS interrupt 15h from Real Mode with AX set to 0xEC00, and BL set to 1 for 32-bit Protected Mode, 2 for 64-bit Long Mode, or 3 if both modes will be used.

== 64 bit Environment Models ==

There are three 64 bit programming models you need to consider: LP64, ILP64, LLP64. Each model has its own pitfalls. The I/L/P stand for Int, Long, Pointer, respectively; the 64 is the number of bits in each.

LP64 means Longs (and Long Longs) and Pointers are 64 bits wide, Ints are 32 bits wide.
LLP64 means Long Longs and Pointers are 64 bits wide, Longs and Ints are 32 bit wide.
ILP64 means Ints, Longs (and Long Longs) and Pointers are 64 bit wide.

Most *nixes use the LP64 model, Windows uses the LLP64 convention. ILP64 is used very rarely.

=== Data Types ===
This table lists the breakdown of sizes in the various programming models.

{| class="wikitable"
|-
!Datatype
!LP64
!ILP64
!LLP64
!ILP32
!LP32
|-
!char 
|      8 
|       8 
|       8 
|       8 
|      8
|-
!short 
|     16 
|      16 
|      16 
|      16 
|     16
|-
!_int   
|     32 
|      -- 
|      32 
|      -- 
|     --
|-
!int     
|     32 
|      64 
|      32 
|      32 
|     16
|-
!long 
|     64 
|      64 
|      32 
|      32 
|     32
|-
!long long
|     -- 
|      -- 
|      64 
|      -- 
|     --
|-
!pointer
|     64 
|      64 
|      64 
|      32 
|     32
|}

=== Models used by 64bit OSs ===
The following table lists what some current 64bit OS have as a programming model.

{| class="wikitable"
! OS               
! Mode
|-
| Windows XP X64       
| LLP64
|-
| Linux                
|  LP64
|-
| FreeBSD/OpenBSD      
|  LP64
|-
| Solaris              
|  LP64
|-
| DEC OSF/1 Alpha      
|  LP64
|-
| SGI Irix             
|  LP64
|-
| HP UX 11             
|  LP64
|}

=== Text Segment Types ===

Another thing that you must keep in mind, that although the address space (and with it all the pointers) are 64 bit wide, the generated code in the text segment is most likely not. That's because by default gcc compiles to the "mov" instruction which has only 32 bit immediate. This means 64 bit programs are limited to 2G, just as 32 bit mode programs.

If you have ever seen an error message like this:
&lt;pre&gt;
relocation truncated to fit: R_X86_64_32 against symbol
&lt;/pre&gt;
then your code hit this barrier. For Assembly, you must use the "movabs" instruction instead of "mov", and for gcc you need to select a different text segment model with the "-mcmodel" argument.

{| class="wikitable"
! Flag               
! Text Segment Addressing
|-
| -mcmodel=small
| The program and its symbols must be linked in the lower 2 GB of the address space (this is the default model)
|-
| -mcmodel=large
| This model makes no assumptions about addresses and sizes of sections.
|-
| -mcmodel=medium
| The program is linked in the lower 2 GB of the address space. Small symbols are also placed there. Symbols with sizes larger than -mlarge-data-threshold are put into large data or bss sections and can be located above 2GB.
|-
| -mcmodel=kernel
| The kernel runs in the negative 2 GB of the address space. This model has to be used for Linux kernel code.
|}
It worth noting that code models are different for architectures, as they are tied with the instruction encoding. For example, AArch64 has a "-mcmodel=tiny" too, which allows 1M addressing, unknown to x86_64. And for AArch64 "-mcmodel=small" has a 4G limitation, not 2G as for the x86_64.

== See Also ==
=== Articles ===
* [[EM64T|Intel EM64T]]
* [[Creating a 64-bit kernel]]
* [[BOOTBOOT|BOOTBOOT bootloader]]
* [[Limine|Limine bootloader]]
* [[X86-64 Instruction Encoding]]
* [[Setting_Up_Long_Mode|Setting up long mode]]

=== Wikipedia ===
* [[Wikipedia:AMD64|AMD64]]
* [[Wikipedia:64-bit|64-bit]]
=== External Links ===
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090419192844/http://www.amd.com/us-en/assets/content_type/DownloadableAssets/dwamd_AMD64_Porting_FAQ.pdf Porting to AMD64: FAQ]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20190515211610/http://www.amdboard.com/hammerspecial.html AMD64 Information]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160707054920/http://www.x86-64.org/documentation.html x86-64 ABI and assembly guide]
* [https://downloads.openwatcom.org/ftp/devel/docs/elf-64-gen.pdf ELF-64 Object File Format]
* [https://stackoverflow.com/questions/1753602/what-are-the-names-of-the-new-x86-64-processors-registers What are the names of the new X86_64 processors registers? on Stack Overflow]

[[Category:X86 CPU]]
[[Category:X86-64]]
[[Category:Operating Modes]]

[[de:Long Mode]]</text>
      <sha1>qxt3ariwrx2s15wss43ss7tour5sb6l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>X86-64 Instruction Encoding</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2350</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30896</id>
      <parentid>29524</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-07-17T12:50:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Blazingblast</username>
        <id>2325</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Add note about REX.B also extending +rw (and similar) register operands.</comment>
      <origin>30896</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="33398" sha1="teqwokcmv9x8tkbhmjtie0jeyf1bqqh" xml:space="preserve">This article describes how x86 and x86-64 instructions are encoded.

== General Overview ==
An x86-64 instruction may be at most 15 bytes in length. It consists of the following components in the given order, where the prefixes are at the least-significant (lowest) address in memory:
* [[#Legacy Prefixes|Legacy prefixes]] (1-4 bytes, optional)
* [[#Opcode|Opcode with prefixes]] (1-4 bytes, required)
* [[#ModR.2FM|ModR/M]] (1 byte, if required)
* [[#SIB|SIB]] (1 byte, if required)
* [[#Displacement|Displacement]] (1, 2, 4 or 8 bytes, if required)
* [[#Immediate|Immediate]] (1, 2, 4 or 8 bytes, if required)

== Registers ==
The registers are encoded using the 4-bit values in the X.Reg column of the following table. ''X.Reg'' is in binary.
&lt;div style="font-size: smaller"&gt;
{| {{wikitable|background: white;}}
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| X.Reg
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 8-bit GP
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 16-bit GP
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 32-bit GP
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 64-bit GP
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 80-bit x87
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 64-bit MMX
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 128-bit XMM
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 256-bit YMM
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 16-bit Segment
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 32-bit Control
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 32-bit Debug
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 0.000 (0)
|AL||AX||EAX||RAX||ST0||MMX0||XMM0||YMM0||ES||CR0||DR0
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 0.001 (1)
|CL||CX||ECX||RCX||ST1||MMX1||XMM1||YMM1||CS||CR1||DR1
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 0.010 (2)
|DL||DX||EDX||RDX||ST2||MMX2||XMM2||YMM2||SS||CR2||DR2
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 0.011 (3)
|BL||BX||EBX||RBX||ST3||MMX3||XMM3||YMM3||DS||CR3||DR3
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 0.100 (4)
|AH, SPL&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table1Note1|1]]&lt;/span&gt;||SP||ESP||RSP||ST4||MMX4||XMM4||YMM4||FS||CR4||DR4
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 0.101 (5)
|CH, BPL&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table1Note1|1]]&lt;/span&gt;||BP||EBP||RBP||ST5||MMX5||XMM5||YMM5||GS||CR5||DR5
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 0.110 (6)
|DH, SIL&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table1Note1|1]]&lt;/span&gt;||SI||ESI||RSI||ST6||MMX6||XMM6||YMM6||-||CR6||DR6
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 0.111 (7)
|BH, DIL&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table1Note1|1]]&lt;/span&gt;||DI||EDI||RDI||ST7||MMX7||XMM7||YMM7||-||CR7||DR7
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 1.000 (8)
|R8L||R8W||R8D||R8||-||MMX0||XMM8||YMM8||ES||CR8||DR8
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 1.001 (9)
|R9L||R9W||R9D||R9||-||MMX1||XMM9||YMM9||CS||CR9||DR9
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 1.010 (10)
|R10L||R10W||R10D||R10||-||MMX2||XMM10||YMM10||SS||CR10||DR10
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 1.011 (11)
|R11L||R11W||R11D||R11||-||MMX3||XMM11||YMM11||DS||CR11||DR11
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 1.100 (12)
|R12L||R12W||R12D||R12||-||MMX4||XMM12||YMM12||FS||CR12||DR12
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 1.101 (13)
|R13L||R13W||R13D||R13||-||MMX5||XMM13||YMM13||GS||CR13||DR13
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 1.110 (14)
|R14L||R14W||R14D||R14||-||MMX6||XMM14||YMM14||-||CR14||DR14
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| 1.111 (15)
|R15L||R15W||R15D||R15||-||MMX7||XMM15||YMM15||-||CR15||DR15
|}
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;small id="Table1Note1"&gt;1: When any REX prefix is used, SPL, BPL, SIL and DIL are used. Otherwise, without any REX prefix AH, CH, DH and BH are used.&lt;/small&gt;

== Legacy Prefixes ==
Each instruction can have up to four prefixes. Sometimes a prefix is required for the instruction while it loses its original meaning (i.e. a 'mandatory prefix'). The following prefixes can be used, the order does not matter:
* Prefix group 1
** 0xF0: LOCK prefix
** 0xF2: REPNE/REPNZ prefix
** 0xF3: REP or REPE/REPZ prefix
* Prefix group 2
** 0x2E: CS segment override
** 0x36: SS segment override
** 0x3E: DS segment override
** 0x26: ES segment override
** 0x64: FS segment override
** 0x65: GS segment override
** 0x2E: Branch not taken
** 0x3E: Branch taken
* Prefix group 3
** 0x66: Operand-size override prefix
* Prefix group 4
** 0x67: Address-size override prefix

When there are two or more prefixes from a single group, the behavior is undefined. Some processors ignore the subsequent prefixes from the same group, or use only the last prefix specified for any group.

=== LOCK prefix ===
With the LOCK prefix, certain read-modify-write instructions are executed atomically. The LOCK prefix can only be used with the following instructions or an [[Exceptions#Invalid Opcode|Invalid Opcode Exception]] occurs: ADC, ADD, AND, BTC, BTR, BTS, CMPXCHG, CMPXCHG8B, CMPXCHG16B, DEC, INC, NEG, NOT, OR, SBB, SUB, XADD, XCHG and XOR.

=== REPNE/REPNZ, REP and REPE/REPZ prefixes ===
The repeat prefixes cause string handling instructions to be repeated.

The '''REP''' prefix will repeat the associated instruction up to CX times, decreasing CX with every repetition. It can be used with the INS, LODS, MOVS, OUTS and STOS instructions.

'''REPE''' and '''REPZ''' are synonyms and repeat the instruction until CX reaches 0 or when ZF is set to 0. It can be used with the CMPS, CMPSB, CMPSD, CMPSW, SCAS, SCASB, SCASD and SCASW instructions.

'''REPNE''' and '''REPNZ''' also are synonyms and repeat the instruction until CX reaches 0 or when ZF is set to 1. It can be used with the CMPS, CMPSB, CMPSD, CMPSW, SCAS, SCASB, SCASD and SCASW instructions

=== CS, SS, DS, ES, FS and GS segment override prefixes ===
Segment overrides are used with instructions that reference non-stack memory. The default segment is implied by the instruction, and using a specific override forces the use of the specified segment for memory operands.

In 64-bit the CS, SS, DS and ES segment overrides are ignored.

=== Branch taken/not taken prefixes ===
Branch hints may be used to lessen the impact of branch misprediction somewhat. The 'branch taken' hint is a strong hint, while the 'branch not taken' hint is a weak hint. The branch hints are only supported by Intel since the Pentium 4. Whether using them on AMD architectures has any (positive or negative) effect at all is not known.

=== Operand-size and address-size override prefix ===
The default operand-size and address-size can be overridden using these prefix. See the following table:

{| {{wikitable|background-color: white}}
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| &amp;nbsp;
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| CS.d
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| REX.W
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| Prefix (0x66 if operand, 0x67 if address)
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| Operand size
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9"| Address size
|-
!style="background-color: #f9f9f9" rowspan="2"| Real mode /&lt;br /&gt;Virtual 8086 mode
| N/A||N/A||{{No}}||16-bit||16-bit
|-
| N/A||N/A||{{Yes}}||32-bit||32-bit
|-
! style="background-color: #f9f9f9" rowspan="4" | Protected mode /&lt;br /&gt;Long compatibility mode
| {{No|0}}||N/A||{{No}}||16-bit||16-bit
|-
| {{No|0}}||N/A||{{Yes}}||32-bit||32-bit
|-
| {{Yes|1}}||N/A||{{No}}||32-bit||32-bit
|-
| {{Yes|1}}||N/A||{{Yes}}||16-bit||16-bit
|-
! style="background-color: #f9f9f9" rowspan="4" | Long 64-bit mode
| Ignored||{{No|0}}||{{No}}||32-bit||64-bit
|-
| Ignored||{{No|0}}||{{Yes}}||16-bit||32-bit
|-
| Ignored||{{Yes|1}}||{{No}}||64-bit&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table2Note1|1]]&lt;/span&gt;||64-bit
|-
| Ignored||{{Yes|1}}||{{Yes}}||64-bit||32-bit
|}
&lt;small id="Table2Note1"&gt;1: Certain instructions default to (or are fixed at) 64-bit operands and do not need the REX prefix for this, see [[#Usage|this table]].&lt;/small&gt;

==== NASM ====
NASM determines the operand size by looking at the ''MODRM.reg'' or (for a register) ''MODRM.rm'' fields. When they are both 32-bit, the operand size becomes 32-bit. Same for 16-bit and 64-bit. When they differ, an error occurs at compile time.
The address size is determined by looking at (for a memory operand) the ''MODRM.rm'' field, or the ''SIB.base'', ''SIB.index'' and displacement, in that order. So when ''SIB.base'' uses a 16-bit register (such as AX), the address size becomes 16-bit. Using a 32-bit displacement will result in the displacement being truncated.

== Opcode ==
The x86-64 instruction set defines many opcodes and many ways to encode them, depending on several factors.

=== Legacy opcodes ===
Legacy (and x87) opcodes consist of, in this order:
* mandatory prefix;
* REX prefix;
* opcode.

==== Mandatory prefix ====
Certain instructions (most notably the SIMD instructions) require a mandatory prefix (0x66, 0xF2 or 0xF3), which looks like a normal modifier prefix. When a mandatory prefix is required, it is put with the modifier prefixes before the REX prefix (if any).

==== REX prefix ====
The REX prefix is only available in [[Long Mode|long mode]].

===== Usage =====
A REX prefix must be encoded when:
* using 64-bit operand size and the instruction does not default to 64-bit operand size; or
* using one of the extended registers (R8 to R15, XMM8 to XMM15, YMM8 to YMM15, CR8 to CR15 and DR8 to DR15); or
* using one of the uniform byte registers SPL, BPL, SIL or DIL.

A REX prefix must not be encoded when:
* using one of the high byte registers AH, CH, BH or DH.

In all other cases, the REX prefix is ignored. The use of multiple REX prefixes is undefined, although processors seem to use only the last REX prefix.

Instructions that default to 64-bit operand size in long mode are:
{| {{wikitable}}
|-
| CALL (near)||ENTER||Jcc
|-
| JrCXZ||JMP (near)||LEAVE
|-
| LGDT||LIDT||LLDT
|-
| LOOP||LOOPcc||LTR
|-
| MOV CR(n)||MOV DR(n)||POP reg/mem
|-
| POP reg||POP FS||POP GS
|-
| POPFQ||PUSH imm8||PUSH imm32
|-
| PUSH reg/mem||PUSH reg||PUSH FS
|-
| PUSH GS||PUSHFQ||RET (near)
|}

===== Encoding =====
The layout is as follows:
&lt;pre&gt;
  7                           0
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0   1   0   0 | W | R | X | B |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
&lt;/pre&gt;
{| {{wikitable|background-color:white;}}
! style="background-color:#f9f9f9;" | Field
! style="background-color:#f9f9f9;" | Length
! style="background-color:#f9f9f9;" | Description
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| 0100
|4 bits||Fixed bit pattern
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| W
|1 bit||When 1, a 64-bit operand size is used. Otherwise, when 0, the default operand size is used (which is 32-bit for most but not all instructions, see [[#Operand-size and address-size override prefix|this table]]).
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| R
|1 bit||This 1-bit value is an extension to the ''MODRM.reg'' field. See [[#Registers|Registers]].
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| X
|1 bit||This 1-bit value is an extension to the ''SIB.index'' field. See [[#64-bit addressing|64-bit addressing]].
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| B
|1 bit||This 1-bit value is an extension to the ''MODRM.rm'' field or the ''SIB.base'' field. See [[#64-bit addressing|64-bit addressing]]. It also extends the register operand for instructions with an opcode ending in ''+rb'', ''+rw'', ''+rd'', ''+ro''.&lt;ref&gt;Intel-64 and IA-32 architectures software manual, volume 2, chapter 3, section 1.1.1. At https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/content-details/825760/intel-64-and-ia-32-architectures-software-developer-s-manual-combined-volumes-2a-2b-2c-and-2d-instruction-set-reference-a-z.html#page=104&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

Because the first four bits always equal 4, the existence of the REX prefix wipes out opcodes 0x40-0x4F, which were previously individual increment and decrement instructions for all eight registers. The Intel 64 and IA-32 Architectures
Software Developer’s Manual volume 2 states "The single-byte-opcode forms of the INC/DEC instructions are not available in 64-bit mode. INC/DEC functionality is still available using ModR/M forms of the same instructions (opcodes FF/0 and FF/1)."

==== Opcode ====
The opcode can be 1, 2 or 3 bytes in length. Depending on the opcode escape sequence, a different opcode map is selected. Possible opcode sequences are:
* &lt;op&gt;
* 0x0F &lt;op&gt;
* 0x0F 0x38 &lt;op&gt;
* 0x0F 0x3A &lt;op&gt;

Note that opcodes can specify that the REG field in the ModR/M byte is fixed at a particular value.

=== VEX/XOP opcodes ===
A VEX/XOP prefix must be encoded when:
* the instruction has only its VEX/XOP opcode and no legacy opcode; or
* 256-bit YMM registers are used; or
* more than three operands are used (e.g. ''nondestructive-source operations''); or
* when using 128-bit XMM destination registers, bits 128-255 of the corresponding YMM register must be cleared.

A VEX/XOP prefix must not be encoded when:
* when using 128-bit XMM destination registers, bits 128-255 of the corresponding YMM register must not be changed.


There are many VEX and XOP instructions, all of which can be encoded using the three byte VEX/XOP escape prefix. The VEX and XOP escape prefixes use fields with the following semantics:

{| {{wikitable|background-color:white;}}
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| Field
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| Length
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| Description
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| VEX/XOP prefix
|style="vertical-align: top;"|8 bits||Prefix.
{| {{wikitable}}
! Prefix
! Opcode map and encoding
|-
| 0xC4||Three-byte VEX
|-
| 0xC5||Two-byte VEX
|-
| 0x8F||Three-byte XOP
|}
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| ~R
|style="vertical-align: top;"|1 bit||This 1-bit value is an 'inverted' extension to the ''MODRM.reg'' field. The inverse of REX.R. See [[#Registers|Registers]].
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| ~X
|style="vertical-align: top;"|1 bit||This 1-bit value is an 'inverted' extension to the ''SIB.index'' field. The inverse of REX.X. See [[#64-bit addressing|64-bit addressing]].
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| ~B
|style="vertical-align: top;"|1 bit||This 1-bit value is an 'inverted' extension to the ''MODRM.rm'' field or the ''SIB.base'' field. The inverse of REX.B. See [[#64-bit addressing|64-bit addressing]].
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| map_select
|style="vertical-align: top;"|5 bits||Specifies the opcode map to use.
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| W/E
|style="vertical-align: top;"|1 bit||For integer instructions: when 1, a 64-bit operand size is used; otherwise, when 0, the default operand size is used (equivalent with REX.W). For non-integer instructions, this bit is a general opcode extension bit.
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| ~vvvv
|style="vertical-align: top;"|4 bits||An additional operand for the instruction. The value of the XMM or YMM register (see [[#Registers|Registers]]) is 'inverted'.
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| L
|style="vertical-align: top;"|1 bit||When 0, a 128-bit vector lengh is used. Otherwise, when 1, a 256-bit vector length is used.
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| pp
|style="vertical-align: top;"|2 bits||Specifies an implied mandatory prefix for the opcode.
{| {{wikitable}}
! Value (binary)
! Implied mandatory prefix
|-
| 00||none
|-
| 01||0x66
|-
| 10||0xF3
|-
| 11||0xF2
|}
|}

==== Three byte VEX escape prefix ====
The layout is as follows, starting with a byte with value 0xC4:
&lt;pre&gt;
  7                           0       7                           0     7                           0
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 1   1   0   0   0   1   0   0 |   |~R |~X |~B |     map_select    |   |W/E|     ~vvvv     | L |   pp  |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
&lt;/pre&gt;
A VEX instruction whose values for certain fields are VEX.~X == 1, VEX.~B == 1, VEX.W/E == 0 and map_select == b00001 may be encoded using the [[#Two_byte_VEX_escape_prefix|two byte VEX escape prefix]].

==== Three byte XOP escape prefix ====
The layout is the same as the [[#Three_byte_VEX_escape_prefix|three-byte VEX escape prefix]], but with initial byte value 0x8F:
&lt;pre&gt;
  7                           0       7                           0     7                           0
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 1   0   0   0   1   1   1   1 |   |~R |~X |~B |     map_select    |   |W/E|     ~vvvv     | L |   pp  |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
&lt;/pre&gt;

The AMD64 Architecture Programmer’s Manual Volume 6 states that the map_select field must be equal to or greater than 8, to differentiate the XOP prefix from the POP instruction that formerly used opcode 0x8F.

==== Two byte VEX escape prefix ====
A VEX instruction whose values for certain fields are VEX.~X == 1, VEX.~B == 1, VEX.W/E == 0 and map_select == b00001 may be encoded using the two byte VEX escape prefix. The layout is as follows:
&lt;pre&gt;
  7                           0       7                           0
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 1   1   0   0   0   1   0   1 |   |~R |     ~vvvv     | L |   pp  |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
&lt;/pre&gt;

=== 3DNow! opcodes ===
3DNow! opcodes consist of, in this order:
* fixed opcode;
* (ModR/M, SIB, displacement);
* immediate opcode byte.

==== Fixed opcode ====
All 3DNow! opcodes have a fixed two-byte sequence equal to 0x0F 0x0F in the opcode position of the instruction.

==== Immediate opcode byte ====
3DNow! instructions encode the actual opcode as an 8-bit immediate value trailing the instruction (thus after the ModR/M, SIB and displacement).

== ModR/M and SIB bytes ==
The ModR/M and SIB bytes are used to encode up to two operands of an instruction, each of which is a direct register or effective memory address.

=== ModR/M ===
The ModR/M byte encodes a register or an opcode extension, and a register or a memory address. It has the following fields:
&lt;pre&gt;
  7                           0
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|  mod  |    reg    |     rm    |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
&lt;/pre&gt;
{| {{wikitable|background-color: white}}
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| Field
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| Length
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| Description
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| MODRM.mod
|style="vertical-align: top;"|2 bits||In general, when this field is b11, then register-direct addressing mode is used; otherwise register-indirect addressing mode is used.
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| MODRM.reg
|style="vertical-align: top;"|3 bits||This field can have one of two values:
* A 3-bit opcode extension, which is used by some instructions but has no further meaning other than distinguishing the instruction from other instructions.
* A 3-bit register reference, which can be used as the source or the destination of an instruction (depending on the instruction). The referenced register depends on the [[#Operand-size and address-size override prefix|operand-size]] of the instruction and the instruction itself. See [[#Registers|Registers]] for the values to use for each of the registers. The REX.R, VEX.~R or XOP.~R field can extend this field with 1 most-significant bit to 4 bits total.
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"| MODRM.rm
|style="vertical-align: top;"|3 bits||Specifies a direct or indirect register operand, optionally with a displacement. The REX.B, VEX.~B or XOP.~B field can extend this field with 1 most-significant bit to 4 bits total.
|}

==== 16-bit addressing ====
These are the meanings of the ''Mod'' (vertically) and ''REX/VEX/XOP.B'' and ''R/M'' bits (horizontally) for [[#Operand-size and address-size override prefix|16-bit addressing]]. ''B.R/M'' and ''Mod'' are in binary. The SIB-byte is not used in 16-bit addressing. In ''Long processing mode'' there is no way to specify 16-bit addresses.
&lt;div style="font-size: 70%; text-align: center"&gt;
{| {{wikitable}}
! 16-bit!! colspan="16" style="text-align: left;" | B.R/M
|-
! Mod
! x.000&lt;br /&gt;AX, R8W
! x.001&lt;br /&gt;CX, R9W
! x.010&lt;br /&gt;DX, R10W
! x.011&lt;br /&gt;BX, R11W
! x.100&lt;br /&gt;SP, R12W
! x.101&lt;br /&gt;BP, R13W
! x.110&lt;br /&gt;SI, R14W
! x.111&lt;br /&gt;DI, R15W
|-
! 00
| style="background-color: white" |[BX + SI]
| style="background-color: white" |[BX + DI]
| style="background-color: white" |[BP + SI]
| style="background-color: white" |[BP + DI]
| style="background-color: white" |[SI]
| style="background-color: white" |[DI]
| style="background-color: white" |[disp16]
| style="background-color: white" |[BX]
|-
! 01
| style="background-color: white" |[BX + SI + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" |[BX + DI + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" |[BP + SI + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" |[BP + DI + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" |[SI + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" |[DI + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" |[BP + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" |[BX + disp8]
|-
! 10
| style="background-color: white" |[BX + SI + disp16]
| style="background-color: white" |[BX + DI + disp16]
| style="background-color: white" |[BP + SI + disp16]
| style="background-color: white" |[BP + DI + disp16]
| style="background-color: white" |[SI + disp16]
| style="background-color: white" |[DI + disp16]
| style="background-color: white" |[BP + disp16]
| style="background-color: white" |[BX + disp16]
|-
! 11
| style="background-color: white" colspan="8"|r/m
|}
&lt;/div&gt;

==== 32/64-bit addressing ====
These are the meanings of the ''Mod'' (vertically) and ''REX/VEX/XOP.B'' and ''R/M'' bits (horizontally) for [[#Operand-size and address-size override prefix|32 and 64-bit addressing]]. ''B.R/M'' and ''Mod'' are in binary.
&lt;div style="font-size: 70%; text-align: center"&gt;
{| {{wikitable}}
! 32/64-bit!! colspan="16" style="text-align: left;" | B.R/M
|-
! Mod
! 0.000&lt;br /&gt;AX
! 0.001&lt;br /&gt;CX
! 0.010&lt;br /&gt;DX
! 0.011&lt;br /&gt;BX
! 0.100&lt;br /&gt;SP
! 0.101&lt;br /&gt;BP
! 0.110&lt;br /&gt;SI
! 0.111&lt;br /&gt;DI
! 1.000&lt;br /&gt;R8
! 1.001&lt;br /&gt;R9
! 1.010&lt;br /&gt;R10
! 1.011&lt;br /&gt;R11
! 1.100&lt;br /&gt;R12
! 1.101&lt;br /&gt;R13
! 1.110&lt;br /&gt;R14
! 1.111&lt;br /&gt;R15
|-
! 00
| style="background-color: white" colspan="4"|[r/m]
| style="background-color: white" |&amp;#91;[[#SIB|SIB]]]
| style="background-color: white" |&amp;#91;[[#RIP.2FEIP-relative_addressing|RIP/EIP]]&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table8Note1|1]],[[#Table8Note2|2]]&lt;/span&gt; + disp32]
| style="background-color: white" colspan="6"|[r/m]
| style="background-color: white" |&amp;#91;[[#SIB|SIB]]]
| style="background-color: white" |&amp;#91;[[#RIP.2FEIP-relative_addressing|RIP/EIP]]&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table8Note1|1]],[[#Table8Note2|2]]&lt;/span&gt; + disp32]
| style="background-color: white" colspan="2"|[r/m]
|-
! 01
| style="background-color: white" colspan="4"|[r/m + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" |&amp;#91;[[#SIB|SIB]] + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" colspan="7"|[r/m + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" |&amp;#91;[[#SIB|SIB]] + disp8]
| style="background-color: white" colspan="3"|[r/m + disp8]
|-
! 10
| style="background-color: white" colspan="4"|[r/m + disp32]
| style="background-color: white" |&amp;#91;[[#SIB|SIB]] + disp32]
| style="background-color: white" colspan="7"|[r/m + disp32]
| style="background-color: white" |&amp;#91;[[#SIB|SIB]] + disp32]
| style="background-color: white" colspan="3"|[r/m + disp32]
|-
! 11
| style="background-color: white" colspan="16"|r/m
|}
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;small id="Table8Note1"&gt;1: In protected/compatibility mode, this is just ''disp32'', but in long mode this is ''[RIP]+disp32'' (for 64-bit addresses) or ''[EIP]+disp32'' (for 32-bit addresses, i.e. with address-size override prefix, [https://web.archive.org/web/20150810173516/http://objectmix.com/asm-x86-asm-370/69055-effect-address-size-prefix-rip-relative-addressing.html see here]).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;small id="Table8Note2"&gt;2: In long mode, to encode ''disp32'' as in protected/compatibility mode, use the SIB byte.&lt;/small&gt;

===== RIP/EIP-relative addressing =====
Addressing in x86-64 can be relative to the current instruction pointer value. This is indicated with the ''RIP'' (64-bit) and ''EIP'' (32-bit) instruction pointer registers, which are not otherwise exposed to the program and may not exist physically. RIP-relative addressing allows object files to be location independent.

=== SIB ===
The SIB byte has the following fields:
&lt;pre&gt;
  7                           0
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| scale |   index   |    base   |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
&lt;/pre&gt;
{| {{wikitable|background-color: white}}
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| Field
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| Length
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9;"| Description
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"|SIB.scale
|style="vertical-align: top;"|2 bits||This field indicates the scaling factor of SIB.index, where ''s'' (as used in the tables) equals 2&lt;span style="vertical-align: super;"&gt;SIB.scale&lt;/span&gt;.
{| {{wikitable}}
! SIB.scale
! factor ''s''
|-
| b00||1
|-
| b01||2
|-
| b10||4
|-
| b11||8
|}
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"|SIB.index
|style="vertical-align: top;"|3 bits||The index register to use. See [[#Registers|Registers]] for the values to use for each of the registers. The REX.X, VEX.~X or XOP.~X field can extend this field with 1 most-significant bit to 4 bits total.
|-
!style="background-color:#f9f9f9; text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"|SIB.base
|style="vertical-align: top;"|3 bits||The base register to use. See [[#Registers|Registers]] for the values to use for each of the registers. The REX.B, VEX.~B or XOP.~B field can extend this field with 1 most-significant bit to 4 bits total.
|}

==== 32/64-bit addressing ====
The meaning of the SIB byte while using 32 or 64-bit addressing is as follows. The ModR/M byte's ''Mod'' field and the SIB byte's ''index'' field are used vertically, the SIB byte's ''base'' field and REX/VEX/XOP.B bit horizontally. The ''s'' is the [[#SIB|scaling factor]]. ''B.Base'', ''X.Index'' and ''Mod'' are in binary.
&lt;div style="font-size: 70%; text-align: center"&gt;
{| {{wikitable}}
! colspan="2" | !! colspan="16" style="text-align: left;" | B.Base
|-
! Mod
! style="text-align: left;" | X.Index
! 0.000&lt;br /&gt;AX
! 0.001&lt;br /&gt;CX
! 0.010&lt;br /&gt;DX
! 0.011&lt;br /&gt;BX
! 0.100&lt;br /&gt;SP
! 0.101&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table10Note1|1]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;BP
! 0.110&lt;br /&gt;SI
! 0.111&lt;br /&gt;DI
! 1.000&lt;br /&gt;R8
! 1.001&lt;br /&gt;R9
! 1.010&lt;br /&gt;R10
! 1.011&lt;br /&gt;R11
! 1.100&lt;br /&gt;R12
! 1.101&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table10Note1|1]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;R13
! 1.110&lt;br /&gt;R14
! 1.111&lt;br /&gt;R15
|-
! rowspan="16" | 00 !! style="text-align: left;" | 0.000 AX
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="4" colspan="5"|[base + (index * s)]
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="4"|[(index * s) + disp32]
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="4" colspan="7" |[base + (index * s)]
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="4"|[(index * s) + disp32]
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="4" colspan="2"|[base + (index * s)]
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.001 CX
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.010 DX
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.011 BX
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.100&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table10Note2|2]]&lt;/span&gt; SP
| style="background-color: white" colspan="5"|[base]
| style="background-color: white"| [disp32]
| style="background-color: white" colspan="7"|[base]
| style="background-color: white"| [disp32]
| style="background-color: white" colspan="2"|[base]
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.101 BP
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="11" colspan="5"|[base + (index * s)]
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="11"|[(index * s) + disp32]
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="11" colspan="7"|[base + (index * s)]
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="11"|[(index * s) + disp32]
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="11" colspan="2"|[base + (index * s)]
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.110 SI
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.111 DI
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.000 R8
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.001 R9
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.010 R10
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.011 R11
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.100 R12
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.101 R13
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.110 R14
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.111 R15
|-
| colspan="18" style="background-color: white; border-top: solid 2px black; border-bottom: solid 2px black; border-left: none; border-right: none;" |
|-
! colspan="2" | !! colspan="16" style="text-align: left;" | B.Base
|-
! Mod
! style="text-align: left;" | X.Index
! 0.000&lt;br /&gt;AX
! 0.001&lt;br /&gt;CX
! 0.010&lt;br /&gt;DX
! 0.011&lt;br /&gt;BX
! 0.100&lt;br /&gt;SP
! 0.101&lt;br /&gt;BP
! 0.110&lt;br /&gt;SI
! 0.111&lt;br /&gt;DI
! 1.000&lt;br /&gt;R8
! 1.001&lt;br /&gt;R9
! 1.010&lt;br /&gt;R10
! 1.011&lt;br /&gt;R11
! 1.100&lt;br /&gt;R12
! 1.101&lt;br /&gt;R13
! 1.110&lt;br /&gt;R14
! 1.111&lt;br /&gt;R15
|-
! rowspan="16" | 01 !! style="text-align: left;" | 0.000 AX
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="4" colspan="16"|[base + (index * s) + disp8]
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.001 CX
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.010 DX
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.011 BX
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.100&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table10Note2|2]]&lt;/span&gt; SP
| style="background-color: white" colspan="16"|[base + disp8]
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.101 BP
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="11" colspan="16"|[base + (index * s) + disp8]
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.110 SI
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.111 DI
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.000 R8
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.001 R9
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.010 R10
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.011 R11
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.100 R12
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.101 R13
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.110 R14
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.111 R15
|-
| colspan="18" style="background-color: white; border-top: solid 2px black; border-bottom: solid 2px black; border-left: none; border-right: none;" |
|-
! colspan="2" | !! colspan="16" style="text-align: left;" | B.Base
|-
! Mod
! style="text-align: left;" | X.Index
! 0.000&lt;br /&gt;AX
! 0.001&lt;br /&gt;CX
! 0.010&lt;br /&gt;DX
! 0.011&lt;br /&gt;BX
! 0.100&lt;br /&gt;SP
! 0.101&lt;br /&gt;BP
! 0.110&lt;br /&gt;SI
! 0.111&lt;br /&gt;DI
! 1.000&lt;br /&gt;R8
! 1.001&lt;br /&gt;R9
! 1.010&lt;br /&gt;R10
! 1.011&lt;br /&gt;R11
! 1.100&lt;br /&gt;R12
! 1.101&lt;br /&gt;R13
! 1.110&lt;br /&gt;R14
! 1.111&lt;br /&gt;R15
|-
! rowspan="16" | 10 !! style="text-align: left;" | 0.000 AX
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="4" colspan="16"|[base + (index * s) + disp32]
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.001 CX
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.010 DX
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.011 BX
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.100&lt;span style="vertical-align: super"&gt;[[#Table10Note2|2]]&lt;/span&gt; SP
| style="background-color: white" colspan="16"|[base + disp32]
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.101 BP
| style="background-color: white" rowspan="11" colspan="16"|[base + (index * s) + disp32]
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.110 SI
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 0.111 DI
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.000 R8
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.001 R9
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.010 R10
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.011 R11
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.100 R12
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.101 R13
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.110 R14
|-
! style="text-align: left;" | 1.111 R15
|}
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;small id="Table10Note1"&gt;1: No base register is encoded.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;small id="Table10Note2"&gt;2: No index register is encoded.&lt;/small&gt;

== Displacement ==
A displacement value is a 1, 2, 4, or 8 byte offset added to the calculated address. When an 8 byte displacement is used, no immediate operand is encoded.

The displacement value, if any, follows the ModR/M and SIB bytes discussed above. When the ModR/M or SIB tables state that a ''disp'' value is required, or without a ModR/M byte the use of ''moffset'' (AMD) or ''moffs'' (Intel) in the mnemonic syntax of the instruction, then the displacement bytes are required.

== Immediate ==
Some instructions require an immediate value. The instruction (and the operand-size column in the above table) determine the length of the immediate value. The ''imm8'' mnemonic (or 8-bit [[#Operand-size and address-size override prefix|operand-size]]) means a one byte immediate value, ''imm16'' (or 16-bit operand-size) means a two byte immediate value, ''imm32'' (or 32-bit operand-size) a four byte value and ''imm64'' (or 64-bit operand-size) an eight byte value. When an 8 byte immediate value is encoded, no displacement can be encoded.

== See Also ==
=== External References ===
* AMD64 Architecture Programmer's Manual [https://www.amd.com/system/files/TechDocs/24594.pdf Volume 3: General-Purpose and System Instructions]
* [http://www.intel.com/products/processor/manuals/ Intel 64 and IA-32 Architectures Software Developer's Manuals]

[[Category:X86 CPU]]
[[Category:X86-64]]</text>
      <sha1>teqwokcmv9x8tkbhmjtie0jeyf1bqqh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>ACPI</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1438</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30223</id>
      <parentid>29957</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-16T14:50:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Makaroneder</username>
        <id>1943</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Replace source tag with syntaxhighlight tag</comment>
      <origin>30223</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3282" sha1="47aynaqd5ps2kj3rszpydic916kdnq9" xml:space="preserve">{{ACPI}}

ACPI (Advanced Configuration and Power Interface) is a [[:Category:Power management|power management]] and configuration standard for the PC, developed by Intel, Microsoft and Toshiba. ACPI allows the operating system to discover the hardware configuration of the computer and control the amount of power each device is given (allowing it to put certain devices on standby or power-off for example). It is also used to control and/or check thermal zones (temperature sensors, fan speeds, etc), battery levels, PCI IRQ routing, CPUs, NUMA domains and many other things.

== Implementing ACPI ==

Information about ACPI is stored in the [[BIOS]] memory (for those systems that support ACPI of course).

There are 2 main parts to ACPI. The first part is the tables used by the OS for configuration during boot (these include things like how many CPUs, APIC details, NUMA memory ranges, etc). The second part is the run time ACPI environment, which consists of [[AML]] code (a platform independent OOP language that comes from the BIOS and devices) and the ACPI SMM (System Management Mode) code.

To begin using ACPI, the operating system must look for the RSDP (Root System Description Pointer). This is covered in [[RSDP]] because it is too verbose to put here.

If the RSDP is found and the verification is valid, it contains a pointer to the [[RSDT]] (Root System Description Table) and for newer versions of ACPI (ACPI 2.0 and later) there is an additional XSDT (eXtended System Description Table). Both the RSDT and the XSDT contain pointers to other tables. The only real difference between the RSDT and the XSDT is that the XSDT contains 64 bit pointer instead of 32 bit pointers.

For the run time part of ACPI the main table to detect is the FADT (Fixed ACPI Description Table) as this contains information needed to enable ACPI.

You have two possibilities of using the ACPI. You can write your own ACPI table reader and AML interpreter. Or you can integrate [[ACPICA]] in your OS.

== Switching to ACPI Mode ==

On some PCs, this is already done for you if...

* the SMI command field in the FADT is 0
* the ACPI enable and ACPI disable fields in the FADT are both 0
* bit 0 (value 1) of the PM1a control block I/O port is set

Otherwise, write the value of the ACPI Enable field into the register number pointed to by the smi command field, like so:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
outb(fadt-&gt;smi_command,fadt-&gt;acpi_enable);
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Linux waits 3 seconds for the hardware to change modes.
Then poll the PM1a control block until bit 0 (value 1) sets. When this bit is set, it means power management events are generating SCIs and not SMIs, which means your OS has to handle the events and the System Management BIOS isn't doing anything for you. The SCI is an IRQ that the FADT tells you about.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
while (inw(fadt-&gt;pm1a_control_block) &amp; 1 == 0);
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

== See Also ==
=== Articles ===
* [[Shutdown]]
* [[ACPICA]]
* [[UACPI]]
* [[RSDP]]
* [[RSDT]]

=== Forum Links ===
* [[Topic:16990|ACPI Shutdown code with good explanation in C]]

=== External Links ===
* [https://uefi.org/sites/default/files/resources/ACPI_6_3_final_Jan30.pdf ACPI Specification]

[[Category:ACPI]]
[[de:Advanced Configuration and Power Interface]]</text>
      <sha1>47aynaqd5ps2kj3rszpydic916kdnq9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>HPET</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3378</id>
    <revision>
      <id>28151</id>
      <parentid>26671</parentid>
      <timestamp>2023-07-10T14:17:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Khaledhammouda</username>
        <id>1596</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>28151</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="14114" sha1="3gk1dqmgubs8dtadyaj752k4hpxj84p" xml:space="preserve">:''This page is not meant as a full description of HPET, only as a lightweight introduction. If you need any information not covered by this article, consult the [http://www.intel.com/content/dam/www/public/us/en/documents/technical-specifications/software-developers-hpet-spec-1-0a.pdf HPET specification].''

'''HPET''', or High Precision Event Timer, is a piece of hardware designed by Intel and Microsoft to replace older [[PIT]] and [[RTC]]. It consists of (usually 64-bit) main counter (which counts up), as well as from 3 to 32 32-bit or 64-bit wide comparators. HPET is programmed using memory mapped IO, and the base address of HPET can be found using [[ACPI]].

==Detecting HPET using ACPI==

The [http://www.intel.com/content/dam/www/public/us/en/documents/technical-specifications/software-developers-hpet-spec-1-0a.pdf HPET specification] defines an ACPI 2.0 table that is to be used to detect presence, address and capabilities of HPET present in the system. If this table doesn't exist, you should assume there is no HPET and you should fall back to [[PIT]] or the [[APIC timer]].

&lt;source lang="cpp"&gt;
struct address_structure
{
    uint8_t address_space_id;    // 0 - system memory, 1 - system I/O
    uint8_t register_bit_width;
    uint8_t register_bit_offset;
    uint8_t reserved;
    uint64_t address;
} __attribute__((packed));

struct description_table_header
{
    char signature[4];    // 'HPET' in case of HPET table
    uint32_t length;
    uint8_t revision;
    uint8_t checksum;
    char oemid[6];
    uint64_t oem_tableid;
    uint32_t oem_revision;
    uint32_t creator_id;
    uint32_t creator_revision;
} __attribute__((packed));

struct hpet : public description_table_header
{
    uint8_t hardware_rev_id;
    uint8_t comparator_count:5;
    uint8_t counter_size:1;
    uint8_t reserved:1;
    uint8_t legacy_replacement:1;
    uint16_t pci_vendor_id;
    address_structure address;
    uint8_t hpet_number;
    uint16_t minimum_tick;
    uint8_t page_protection;
} __attribute__((packed));
&lt;/source&gt;

==HPET - timer vs comparators==

There is just one up counting main counter in the timer, but interrupt generation is handled by *comparators*. There're from 3 to 32 comparators, and the exact amount is indicated by &lt;code&gt;comparator_count&lt;/code&gt; field in the above &lt;code&gt;hpet&lt;/code&gt; structure. Keep in mind you have to initialize both the main counter and all of the comparators. Also, the routing as well as '''allowed''' routing of comparator interrupts is independent, so you have to detect and set it up for each of them individually. More information on this procedure is provided further in the text.

==HPET operating modes==

HPET offers two operating modes: one-shot (also called "non-periodic" by the specification) and periodic mode.

===One-shot mode===

In non-periodic mode, the OS programs one of timer's comparator registers with value of main counter that is to trigger an interrupt. If the timer is set to 32 bit mode, it will also generate an interrupt when the counter wraps around. The comparator register's value is never written by the hardware, you are free to write to it and read from it at any time, therefore you can change at what value in the main counter the interrupt will be generated.

Every comparator in HPET '''must support''' non-periodic mode.

===Periodic mode===

Periodic mode is more tricky than non-periodic mode. For periodic mode, similarly to one-shot mode, you write a value at which an interrupt shall be generated to the comparator register. When the interrupt is generated, however, the hardware will '''increase the value in comparator register by the last value written to it'''! This is a consequence of HPET's main counter being up-counting.

So, if the main counter's value is 12345 when we set the timer up, and we write 12456 to comparator (i.e. the interrupt should trigger 111 time units from now), when the interrupt triggers, 12456 will be ''added'' to the comparator register, so it will become 24912, which is 12456 time units from the first interrupt. There are two techniques to deal with this problem; they will both be described in later part of the article.

Comparators are '''NOT required''' to support this mode; you must detect this capability when initializing a comparator. More information on this is provided further in the article.

==Interrupt routing==

HPET supports three interrupt mapping options: "legacy replacement" option, standard option, and FSB option. 

==="Legacy replacement" mapping===

In this mapping, HPET's timer (comparator) #0 replaces PIT interrupts, whereas timer #1 replaces RTC's interrupts (in other words, PIC and RTC will no longer cause interrupts). While the HPET specification provides the following table describing the routing of timers #0 and #1 in this mapping, it is recommended to at least check the routing of IRQ0 and IRQ8 to I/O APIC in ACPI tables.

{| {{wikitable}}
!Timer
!PIC mapping
!IOAPIC mapping
|-
|0
|IRQ0
|IRQ2
|-
|1
|IRQ8
|IRQ8
|-
|N
|As per IRQ Routing Field
|As per IRQ Routing Field
|}

===Standard mapping===

In standard mapping, each timer has its own interrupt routing control. Allowed I/O APIC inputs are found by reading timer's capabilities register.

===FSB mapping===

This mapping is almost identical to PCI's Message Signaled Interrupts. The "Timer N FSB Interrupt Route Register" which defines how FSB interrupts are configured can be found in the specification. FSB interrupts are enabled using "Tn_FSB_EN_CNF" field in timer's configuration register. This mapping mode will not be further discussed in this article.

==HPET registers==

The following table and field descriptions can also be found in the specification. "Offset" means offset from the address defined in &lt;code&gt;address&lt;/code&gt; field of &lt;code&gt;hpet&lt;/code&gt; struct. The following table skips reserved registers defined in the specification.

{| {{wikitable}}
!Offset
!Register
!Type
|-
|0x000 - 0x007
|General Capabilities and ID Register
|Read only
|-
|0x010 - 0x017
|General Configuration Register
|Read/write
|-
|0x020 - 0x027
|General Interrupt Status Register
|Read/write clear
|-
|0x0F0 - 0x0F7
|Main Counter Value Register
|Read/write
|-
|(0x100 + 0x20 * N) - (0x107 + 0x20 * N)
|Timer N Configuration and Capability Register
|Read/write
|-
|(0x108 + 0x20 * N) - (0x10F + 0x20 * N)
|Timer N Comparator Value Register
|Read/write
|-
|(0x110 + 0x20 * N) - (0x117 + 0x20 * N)
|Timer N FSB Interrupt Route Register
|Read/write
|}

===General Capabilities and ID Register===

{| {{wikitable}}
!Bits
!Name
!Description
|-
|63:32
|COUNTER_CLK_PERIOD
|Main counter tick period in femtoseconds (10^-15 seconds). Must not be zero, must be less or equal to 0x05F5E100, or 100 nanoseconds.
|-
|31-16
|VENDOR_ID
|This field should be interpreted similarly to PCI's vendor ID.
|-
|15
|LEG_RT_CAP
|If this bit is 1, HPET is capable of using "legacy replacement" mapping.
|-
|14
|Reserved
| -
|-
|13
|COUNT_SIZE_CAP
|If this bit is 1, HPET main counter is capable of operating in 64 bit mode.
|-
|12:8
|NUM_TIM_CAP
|The amount of timers - 1.
|-
|7:0
|REV_ID
|Indicates which revision of the function is implemented; must not be 0.
|}

===General Configuration Register===

{| {{wikitable}}
!Bits
!Name
!Description
|-
|63:2
|Reserved
| -
|-
|1
|LEG_RT_CNF
|0 - "legacy replacement" mapping is disabled
1 - "legacy replacement" mapping is enabled
|-
|0
|ENABLE_CNF
|Overall enable.
0 - main counter is halted, timer interrupts are disabled

1 - main counter is running, timer interrupts are allowed if enabled
|}

===General Interrupt Status Register===

{| {{wikitable}}
!Bits
!Name
!Description
|-
|63:32
|Reserved
| -
|-
|n
|Tn_INT_STS
|The functionality is dependent of whether edge or level-triggered mode is used for timer #n.

'''For level-triggered:''' the default value is 0. When a corresponding timer interrupt is active, this bit is set. If it is set, software can clear it by writing 1 to this bit. Writes of 0 have no effect.

'''For edge-triggered:''' this bit should be ignored. It is always set to 0.
|}

===Main Counter Value Register===

Bits 63:0 of this register are called MAIN_COUNTER_VAL. Writes to this register should only be done when the counter is halted (ENABLE_CNF = 0). Reads will return current value of the main counter. 32-bit counters will always return 0 for the upper 32 bits. If 32 bit reads are performed on 64 bit counter, consult 2.4.7 in the specification for instructions how to do it safely. It is recommended to use 32 bit counter when on 32-bit only software.

===Timer N Configuration and Capability Register===

{| {{wikitable}}
!Bits
!Name
!Description
|-
|63:32
|Tn_INT_ROUTE_CAP
|Timer n Interrupt Routing Capability. If bit X is set in this field, it means that this timer can be mapped to IRQX line of I/O APIC.
|-
|31:16
|Reserved
| -
|-
|15
|Tn_FSB_INT_DEL_CAP
|If this read-only bit is 1, this timer supports FSB interrupt mapping.
|-
|14
|Tn_FSB_EN_CNF
|If this bit is set to 1, this timer will use FSB interrupt mapping.
|-
|13:9
|Tn_INT_ROUTE_CNF
|This field indicates I/O APIC routing. Allowed values can be determined using Tn_INT_ROUTE_CAP. If an illegal value is written, then value read back from this field will not match the written value.
|-
|8
|Tn_32MODE_CNF
|For 64-bit timer, if this field is set, the timer will be forced to work in 32-bit mode. Otherwise it has no effect.
|-
|7
|Reserved
| -
|-
|6
|Tn_VAL_SET_CNF
|This field is used to allow software to directly set periodic timer's accumulator. Detailed explanation is provided further in the article.
|-
|5
|Tn_SIZE_CAP
|If this read-only bit is set to 1, the size of the timer is 64-bit. Otherwise, it's 32-bit.
|-
|4
|Tn_PER_INT_CAP
|If this read-only bit is set to 1, this timer supports periodic mode.
|-
|3
|Tn_TYPE_CNF
|If Tn_PER_INT_CAP is 1, then writing 1 to this field enables periodic timer and writing 0 enables non-periodic mode. Otherwise, this bit will be ignored and reading it will always return 0.
|-
|2
|Tn_INT_ENB_CNF
|Setting this bit to 1 enables triggering of interrupts. Even if this bit is 0, this timer will still set Tn_INT_STS.
|-
|1
|Tn_INT_TYPE_CNF
|0 - this timer generates edge-triggered interrupts.
1 - this timer generates level-triggered interrupts. When the interrupt is generated, Tn_INT_STS is set. If another interrupt occurs before that bit is cleared, the interrupt will remain active.
|-
|0
|Reserved
| -
|}

===Timer N Comparator Value Register===

Bits 63:0 (or 31:0, if the timer operates in 32 bit mode) are used to compare with main counter to check if an interrupt should be generated.

==Initialization==

The following is the procedure you need to perform to initialize main counter and comparators in order to receive interrupts.

General initialization:

1. Find HPET base address in 'HPET' ACPI table.

2. Calculate HPET frequency (f = 10^15 / period).

3. Save minimal tick (either from ACPI table or configuration register).

4. Initialize comparators.

5. Set ENABLE_CNF bit.

Timer N initialization:

1. Determine if timer N is periodic capable, save that information to avoid re-reading it every time.

2. Determine allowed interrupt routing for current timer and allocate an interrupt for it.

I am enabling the timers only when I actually use them, so there's no "real" initialization of comparators here.

Keep in mind that allowed interrupt routing '''may be insane'''. Namely, you probably want to use some of ISA interrupts - or, at very least, be able to use them at one point unambiguously. Last time I checked VirtualBox allowed mappings for HPET, it allowed every timer to be routed to ''any'' of 32 I/O APIC inputs present on the system. Knowing how buggy hardware can be, I wouldn't be too surprised if there exists a PC with HPET claiming that input #31 is allowed, when there are only 24 I/O APIC inputs. Be aware of this when choosing interrupt routing for timers.

==Using timers==

===One-shot mode===

To enable one-shot mode:

&lt;source lang="cpp"&gt;
// "time" is time in femtoseconds from now to interrupt
if (time &lt; COUNTER_CLK_PERIOD)
{
    time = adjust_time(time);
}

write_register_64(timer_configuration(n), (ioapic_input &lt;&lt; 9) | (1 &lt;&lt; 2));
write_register_64(timer_comparator(n), read_register(main_counter) + time);
&lt;/source&gt;

I hope the above code is obvious. If it's not, please analyze the meaning of specific fields in registers used above.

===Periodic mode===

To enable periodic mode:

&lt;source lang="cpp"&gt;
// "time" is time in femtoseconds from now to interrupt
if (time &lt; COUNTER_CLK_PERIOD)
{
    time = adjust_time(time);
}

write_register_64(timer_configuration(n), (ioapic_input &lt;&lt; 9) | (1 &lt;&lt; 2) | (1 &lt;&lt; 3) | (1 &lt;&lt; 6));
write_register_64(timer_comparator(n), read_register(main_counter) + time);
write_register_64(timer_comparator(n), time);
&lt;/source&gt;

This snippet requires some more comments.

Bit 2 is the same as above, Interrupt Enable. Bit 3 is also quite straightforward - 1 means periodic timer. But we've also set bit 6. Why?

Let's take a look at quote from the HPET specification:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Timer n Value Set: [...] Software uses this read/write bit only for timers that have been set to periodic mode. By writing this bit to a 1, the software is then allowed to directly set a periodic timer’s accumulator.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Software does NOT have to write this bit back to 0 (it automatically clears). Software should not write a 1 to this bit position if the timer is set to non-periodic mode.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This means that next write to timer N comparator register will have the usual meaning, while ''second'' next write will write directly to the accumulator. I believe that the wording could've been much better.

==See also==
* [[IOAPIC]]
* [[APIC]]
* [[APIC timer]]
* [[PIT]]
* [[RTC]]

==External links==
* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Precision_Event_Timer HPET article on Wikipedia]
* [http://www.intel.com/content/dam/www/public/us/en/documents/technical-specifications/software-developers-hpet-spec-1-0a.pdf Intel's HPET Specification v1.0a]


[[Category:Common Devices]]
[[Category:Interrupts]]
[[Category:Timers]]</text>
      <sha1>3gk1dqmgubs8dtadyaj752k4hpxj84p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>APIC Timer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3127</id>
    <revision>
      <id>28146</id>
      <parentid>28145</parentid>
      <timestamp>2023-07-10T14:11:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Khaledhammouda</username>
        <id>1596</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>moved [[APIC timer]] to [[APIC Timer]]</comment>
      <origin>28146</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="13400" sha1="cfp5ib03hxtaysokxmo62u7c9dmthjx" xml:space="preserve">The great benefit of the Local [[APIC]] timer is that it is hardwired to each CPU core, unlike the [[PIT|Programmable Interval Timer]] which is a separate circuit. Because of this, there is no need for any resource management, which makes things easier. The downside is that it's oscillating at (one of) the CPU's frequencies, which varies from machine to machine, while the PIT uses a standard frequency (1,193,182 Hz). To make use of it, you have to know how many interrupts/sec it's capable of.

== APIC Timer Modes ==

The timer has 2 or 3 modes. The first 2 modes (periodic and one-shot) are supported by all local APICs. The third mode (TSC-Deadline mode) is an extension that is only supported on recent CPUs.

=== Periodic Mode ===

For periodic mode, software sets a "initial count" and the local APIC uses it for a "current count". The local APIC decrements the current count until it reaches zero, then generates a timer IRQ and resets the current count to the initial count and begins decrementing the current count again. In this way the local APIC generates IRQs at a fixed rate depending on the initial count. The current count is decremented at a rate that depends on the CPU's external frequency ("bus frequency") divided by the value in the local APIC's "Divide Configuration Register".

For example, for a 2.4 GHz CPU with an external/bus frequency of 800 MHz, if the Divide Configuration Register is set to "divide by 4" and the initial count is set to 123456; then the local APIC timer would decrement the count at a rate of 200 MHz and generate a timer IRQ every 617.28 us, giving a rate of IRQs of 1620.01 Hz.

=== One-Shot Mode ===

For one-shot mode, the local APIC decrements the current count (and generates a timer IRQ when the count reaches zero) in the same way as in periodic mode; however it doesn't reset the current count to the initial count when the current count reaches zero. Instead, software has to set a new count each time if it wants more timer IRQs.

The advantage of this mode is that software can have precise control over when timer IRQs occur. For example, during task switches an OS could set the count to a value that depends on the new task's priority (so that some tasks run for a small amount of time and other tasks run for a larger amount of time), and there wouldn't be any unwanted IRQs. Some OSs use this approach to implement a generic high precision timer service, where the local APIC count is set to a value that depends on which event will happen soonest. For example, if the currently running task switch should be pre-empted in 1234 nanoseconds, a sleeping task needs to wake up in 333 nanoseconds and alarm signal has to be sent in 44444 nanoseconds, then the timer's count would be set to 333 nanoseconds (the earliest delay needed) and when the the timer IRQ occurs the OS knows that there's 901 nanoseconds remaining before the current task should be pre-empted and 441111 nanoseconds until the alarm signal needs to be sent (and would set the count to 901 nanoseconds for the next timer IRQ).

The disadvantages are that it's harder to track real-time with one-shot mode and special care needs to be taken to avoid race conditions; especially if a new count is set before the old count expires.

=== TSC-Deadline mode ===

TSC-Deadline mode is very different to the other 2 modes. Instead of using the CPU's external/bus frequency to decrement a count, software sets a "deadline" and the local APIC generates a timer IRQ when the value of the CPU's time stamp counter is greater than or equal to the deadline.

Despite these differences, software would/could use it in the same way that one-shot mode would be used. The advantages (compared to one-shot mode) are that you get higher precision (because the CPU's time stamp counter runs at the CPU's (nominal) internal frequency rather than the CPU's external/bus frequency), and it's easier to avoid/handle race conditions.

== Enabling APIC Timer ==

Before enabling the local APIC timer, you should setup the rest of the local APIC. This includes:

* Determine the local APIC's physical address (via. ACPI tables or MultiProcessor Specification tables)
* Specify a spurious interrupt and software enable the APIC
* Make sure the TPR (Task Priority Register) is set (so it won't block/postpone lower priority IRQs)

Once that's done:

* Set the local APIC timer's divide configuration register
* Configure the local APIC timer's interrupt vector and unmask the timer's IRQ
* Set the local APIC timer's initial count

Note: It's recommended to follow the order given above (especially setting the local APIC timer's initial count last). Doing things in a different order (e.g. setting the initial count, then enabling the timer) can lead to problems on some (real or virtual) machines (e.g. everything seems right and counter is decreasing, but IRQ is never sent).

== Initializing ==
''Please note that this is the recommended way of determining the frequency of the APIC timer.''

'''NOTE:''' According to Intel's documentation for IA-32 (x86) and Intel 64 (x86_64), APIC timer's frequency is equal to the bus' frequency '''OR''' the core crystal's frequency divided by the chosen frequency divider. The bus' and the core crystal's frequency can be found in the [[CPUID|CPUID]] functions [https://sandpile.org/x86/cpuid.htm#level_0000_0015h 0x15] and [https://sandpile.org/x86/cpuid.htm#level_0000_0016h 0x16], respectively. Through CPUID.0x15 can also be determined the TSC frequency. The frequency of the APIC timer depends on whether the system is using local APIC or ''discrete'' APIC ([https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Programmable_Interrupt_Controller 82489DX]). When the local APIC is built in core's crystal, the APIC timer is using core's frequency. Otherwise, it is using the bus frequency.


There are several ways to do this, but all of them use a different, CPU bus frequency independent clock source to do that. Examples: [[RTC|Real Time Clock]], [[TSC|TimeStamp Counter]], PIT or even polling [[CMOS#Getting_Current_Date_and_Time_from_RTC|CMOS registers]]. In this tutorial we will use the good old PIT, as it's the easiest. Steps that need to be done:
* Reset APIC to a well known state
* Enable APIC timer
* Reset APIC timer counter
* Wait a specific amount of time measured by a different clock
* Get number of ticks from APIC timer counter
* Adjust it to a second
* Divide it by the quantum of your choice (results X)
* Make the APIC timer fire an interrupt at every X ticks

The APIC timer can be set to make a tick (decrease counter) at a given frequency, which is called "divide value". This means you have to multiply APIC timer counter ticks by this divide value to get the true CPU bus frequency. You could use a value of 1 (ticks on every bus cycle) up to 128 (ticks on every 128th cycle). See Intel manual vol3A Chapter 9.5.4 for details. Note that according to my tests, Bochs seems not to handle divide value of 1 properly, so I will use 16.

=== Prerequisites ===
Before we start, let's define some constant and functions.
&lt;source lang="asm"&gt;
apic		= the linear address where you have mapped the APIC registers

APIC_APICID	= 20h
APIC_APICVER	= 30h
APIC_TASKPRIOR	= 80h
APIC_EOI	= 0B0h
APIC_LDR	= 0D0h
APIC_DFR	= 0E0h
APIC_SPURIOUS	= 0F0h
APIC_ESR	= 280h
APIC_ICRL	= 300h
APIC_ICRH	= 310h
APIC_LVT_TMR	= 320h
APIC_LVT_PERF	= 340h
APIC_LVT_LINT0	= 350h
APIC_LVT_LINT1	= 360h
APIC_LVT_ERR	= 370h
APIC_TMRINITCNT	= 380h
APIC_TMRCURRCNT	= 390h
APIC_TMRDIV	= 3E0h
APIC_LAST	= 38Fh
APIC_DISABLE	= 10000h
APIC_SW_ENABLE	= 100h
APIC_CPUFOCUS	= 200h
APIC_NMI	= (4&lt;&lt;8)
TMR_PERIODIC	= 20000h
TMR_BASEDIV	= (1&lt;&lt;20)

		;Interrupt Service Routines
isr_dummytmr:	mov			dword [apic+APIC_EOI], 0
		iret
isr_spurious:	iret
		;function to set a specific interrupt gate in IDT
		;al=interrupt
		;ebx=isr entry point
writegate:	...
		ret
&lt;/source&gt;
I will also assume that you have a working [[IDT]], and you have a function to write a gate for a specific interrupt: writegate(intnumber,israddress).
Furthermore, to make things simple, I'll assume that you did not change the default interrupt mapping found in almost every tutorial:
* interrupt 0-31: exceptions
* interrupt 32: timer, IRQ0
* interrupt 39: spurious irq, IRQ7
If you've already changed this, modify accordingly.


=== Example code in ASM ===
Here's a possible way to initialize APIC timer in fasm syntax assembly:
&lt;source lang="asm"&gt;
		;you should read MSR, get APIC base and map to "apic"
		;you should have used lidt properly

		;set up isrs
		mov			al, 32
		mov			ebx, isr_dummytmr
		call			writegate
		mov			al, 39
		mov			ebx, isr_spurious
		call			writegate

		;initialize LAPIC to a well known state
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_DFR], 0FFFFFFFFh
		mov			eax, dword [apic+APIC_LDR]
		and			eax, 00FFFFFFh
		or			al, 1
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_LDR], eax
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_LVT_TMR], APIC_DISABLE
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_LVT_PERF], APIC_NMI
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_LVT_LINT0], APIC_DISABLE
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_LVT_LINT1], APIC_DISABLE
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_TASKPRIOR], 0
		;okay, now we can enable APIC
		;global enable
		mov			ecx, 1bh
		rdmsr
		bts			eax, 11
		wrmsr
		;software enable, map spurious interrupt to dummy isr
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_SPURIOUS], 39+APIC_SW_ENABLE
		;map APIC timer to an interrupt, and by that enable it in one-shot mode
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_LVT_TMR], 32
		;set up divide value to 16
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_TMRDIV], 03h

		;ebx=0xFFFFFFFF;
		xor			ebx, ebx
		dec			ebx

		;initialize PIT Ch 2 in one-shot mode
		;waiting 1 sec could slow down boot time considerably,
		;so we'll wait 1/100 sec, and multiply the counted ticks
		mov			dx, 61h
		in			al, dx
		and			al, 0fdh
		or			al, 1
		out			dx, al
		mov			al, 10110010b
		out			43h, al
		;1193180/100 Hz = 11931 = 2e9bh
		mov			al, 9bh		;LSB
		out			42h, al
		in			al, 60h		;short delay
		mov			al, 2eh		;MSB
		out			42h, al
		;reset PIT one-shot counter (start counting)
		in			al, dx
		and			al, 0feh
		out			dx, al		;gate low
		or			al, 1
		out			dx, al		;gate high
		;reset APIC timer (set counter to -1)
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_TMRINITCNT], ebx
		;now wait until PIT counter reaches zero
@@:		in			al, dx
		and			al, 20h
		jz			@b
		;stop APIC timer
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_LVT_TMR], APIC_DISABLE
		;now do the math...
		xor			eax, eax
		xor			ebx, ebx
		dec			eax
		;get current counter value
		mov			ebx, dword [apic+APIC_TMRCURRCNT]
		;it is counted down from -1, make it positive
		sub			eax, ebx
		inc			eax
		;we used divide value different than 1, so now we have to multiply the result by 16
		shl			eax, 4		;*16
		xor			edx, edx
		;moreover, PIT did not wait a whole sec, only a fraction, so multiply by that too
		mov			ebx, 100	;*PITHz
		mul			ebx
	;-----edx:eax now holds the CPU bus frequency-----
		;now calculate timer counter value of your choice
		;this means that tasks will be preempted 1000 times in a second. 100 is popular too.
		mov			ebx, 1000
		xor			edx, edx
		div			ebx
		;again, we did not use divide value of 1
		shr			eax, 4		;/16
		;sanity check, min 16
		cmp			eax, 010h
		jae			@f
		mov			eax, 010h
		;now eax holds appropriate number of ticks, use it as APIC timer counter initializer
@@:		mov			dword [apic+APIC_TMRINITCNT], eax
		;finally re-enable timer in periodic mode
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_LVT_TMR], 32 or TMR_PERIODIC
		;setting divide value register again not needed by the manuals
		;although I have found buggy hardware that required it
		mov			dword [apic+APIC_TMRDIV], 03h
&lt;/source&gt;

=== Example code in C ===
This code is an example of how to initialize the APIC timer so that it ticks every 10 milliseconds. This is done by letting the APIC timer run, waiting for 10ms using the PIT and then getting the number of ticks that were done from the APIC timer. It assumes that you have functions to "write"/"read" the APIC's registers and "pit_prepare_sleep"/"pit_perform_sleep" to perform an as accurate as possible measurement of the timer's frequency.
&lt;source lang="c"&gt;
void apic_start_timer() {
        // Tell APIC timer to use divider 16
        write(APIC_REGISTER_TIMER_DIV, 0x3);
 
        // Prepare the PIT to sleep for 10ms (10000µs)
        pit_prepare_sleep(10000);
 
        // Set APIC init counter to -1
        write(APIC_REGISTER_TIMER_INITCNT, 0xFFFFFFFF);
 
        // Perform PIT-supported sleep
        pit_perform_sleep();
 
        // Stop the APIC timer
        write(APIC_REGISTER_LVT_TIMER, APIC_LVT_INT_MASKED);
 
        // Now we know how often the APIC timer has ticked in 10ms
        uint32_t ticksIn10ms = 0xFFFFFFFF - read(APIC_REGISTER_TIMER_CURRCNT);
 
        // Start timer as periodic on IRQ 0, divider 16, with the number of ticks we counted
        write(APIC_REGISTER_LVT_TIMER, 32 | APIC_LVT_TIMER_MODE_PERIODIC);
        write(APIC_REGISTER_TIMER_DIV, 0x3);
        write(APIC_REGISTER_TIMER_INITCNT, ticksIn10ms);
}
&lt;/source&gt;

== See also ==
=== Articles ===
* [[APIC]]
=== Threads ===
* [http://www.osdev.org/phpBB2/viewtopic.php?t=10686 APIC timer]

=== External Links ===
* [http://www.intel.com/products/processor/manuals/ Volume 3A:System Programming Guide, Part 1,manuals has a chapter on the APIC]
* [http://www.osdever.net/tutorials/view/advanced-programming-interrupt-controller Advanced Programmable Interrupt Controller by Mike Rieker]

[[Category:Interrupts]]
[[Category:Timers]]</text>
      <sha1>cfp5ib03hxtaysokxmo62u7c9dmthjx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Programmable Interval Timer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1560</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30843</id>
      <parentid>30555</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-07-03T00:12:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tocariimaa</username>
        <id>2217</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>use nasm highlight for the assembly code</comment>
      <origin>30843</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="39581" sha1="in1g7hi054dm4c9lwm7wa4pkz0auwaz" xml:space="preserve">{{Historical}}

The '''Programmable Interval Timer''' ('''PIT''') chip (Intel 8253/8254) basically consists of an oscillator, a prescaler and 3 independent frequency dividers. Each frequency divider has an output, which is used to allow the timer to control external circuitry (for example, IRQ 0).

On modern systems, the '''PIT''' has been obsoleted by both the [[HPET]] timer which offers higher precision and performance, the [[ACPI Timer]] which is easier to detect, and by the [[APIC Timer]] which is multiprocessor aware. In addition, PIT has been found to be broken (at least on Arrow Lake) or absent (at least on Surface Pro 4 &lt;ref&gt;[https://www.kernel.org/pub/linux/kernel/v4.x/ChangeLog-4.9.104]&lt;/ref&gt;) on modern hardware, so assuming its presence is no good.

== The Oscillator ==
The oscillator used by the PIT chip runs at (roughly) 1.193182 MHz. The reason for this requires a trip back into history (to the later half of the 1970's)...

The original PC used a single "base oscillator" to generate a frequency of 14.31818 MHz because this frequency was commonly used in television circuitry at the time. This base frequency was divided by 3 to give a frequency of 4.77272666 MHz that was used by the CPU, and divided by 4 to give a frequency of 3.579545 MHz that was used by the CGA video controller. By logically ANDing these signals together a frequency equivalent to the base frequency divided by 12 was created. This frequency is 1.1931816666 MHz (where the 6666 part is recurring). At the time it was a brilliant method of reducing costs, as the 14.31818 MHz oscillator was cheap due to mass production and it was cheaper to derive the other frequencies from this than to have several oscillators. In modern computers, where the cost of electronics is much less, and the CPU and video run at much higher frequencies the PIT lives on as a reminder of "the good ole' days".

== Frequency Dividers ==
The basic principle of a frequency divider is to divide one frequency to obtain a slower frequency. This is typically done by using a counter. Each "pulse" from the input frequency causes the counter to be decreased, and when that counter has reached zero a pulse is generated on the output and the counter is reset. For example, if the input signal is 200 Hz and the counter is reset to a value of ten each time, then the output frequency would be 200/10, or 20 Hz.

The PIT has only 16 bits that are used as frequency divider, which can represent the values from 0 to 65535. Since the frequency can't be divided by 0 in a sane way, many implementations use 0 to represent the value 65536 (or 10000 when programmed in BCD mode).

The PIT chip has three separate frequency dividers (or 3 separate channels) that are programmable, in that the value of the "reset counter" is set by software (the OS). Software also specifies an action to be taken when the counter reaches zero on each individual channel. In this way, each channel can be used in one of several "modes" – for example, as a frequency divider (where the count is automatically reset) or as a "one shot" timer (where the count isn't automatically reset).

Each PIT channel also has a "gate input" pin which can be used to control whether the input signal (the 1.19MHz one) gets to the channel or not. For PIT channels 0 and 1, the associated gate input pin is not connected to anything. The PIT channel 2 gate is controlled by IO port 0x61, bit 0.

== PIT Timer Accuracy ==
The accuracy of the PIT timer depends on the quality of the oscillator used, and is typically accurate to within +/- 1.73 seconds per day. There are many causes for this inaccuracy, however because of this there isn't much point in specifying times or frequencies to more than five or six digits.

== Outputs ==
Channel 0 is connected directly to IRQ0, so it is best to use it only for purposes that should generate interrupts. Channel 1 is unusable, and may not even exist. Channel 2 is connected to the PC speaker, but can be used for other purposes without producing audible speaker tones.

=== Channel 0 ===
The output from PIT channel 0 is connected to the PIC chip, so that it generates an "IRQ 0". Typically during boot the BIOS sets channel 0 with a count of 65535 or 0 (which translates to 65536), which gives an output frequency of 18.2065 Hz (or an IRQ every 54.9254 ms). Channel 0 is probably the most useful PIT channel, as it is the only channel that is connected to an IRQ. It can be used to generate an infinte series of "timer ticks" at a frequency of your choice (as long as it is higher than 18 Hz), or to generate single CPU interrupts (in "one shot" mode) after programmable short delays (less than an 18th of a second).

When choosing [[#Operating Modes|an operating mode]], below, it is useful to remember that the IRQ0 is generated by the ''rising edge'' of the Channel 0 output voltage (ie. the transition from "low" to "high", only).

=== Channel 1 ===
The output for PIT channel 1 was once used (in conjunction with the DMA controller's channel 0) for refreshing the DRAM (Dynamic Random Access Memory) or RAM. Typically, each bit in RAM consists of a capacitor which holds a tiny charge representing the state of that bit, however (due to leakage) these capacitors need to be "refreshed" periodically so that they don't forget their state.

On later machines, the DRAM refresh is done with dedicated hardware and the PIT (and DMA controller) is no longer used. On modern computers where the functionality of the PIT is implemented in a large scale integrated circuit, PIT channel 1 is no longer usable and may not be implemented at all.

=== Channel 2 ===
The output of PIT channel 2 is connected to the PC speaker, so the frequency of the output determines the frequency of the sound produced by the speaker. This is the only channel where the gate input can be controlled by software (via bit 0 of I/O port 0x61), and the only channel where its output (a high or low voltage) can be read by software (via bit 5 of I/O port 0x61). Details of how to program the PC speaker can be found [[PC_Speaker|here]].

== I/O Ports ==
The PIT chip uses the following I/O ports:

 I/O port     Usage
 0x40         Channel 0 data port (read/write)
 0x41         Channel 1 data port (read/write)
 0x42         Channel 2 data port (read/write)
 0x43         Mode/Command register (write only, a read is ignored)

Each 8 bit data port is the same, and is used to set the counter's 16 bit reload value or read the channel's 16 bit current count (more on this later). The PIT channel's current count and reload value should not be confused. In general, when the current count reaches zero the PIT channel's output is changed and the current count is reloaded with the reload value, however this isn't always the case. How the current count and reload value are used and what they contain depends on which mode the PIT channel is configured to use.

The Mode/Command register at I/O address 0x43 contains the following:

 Bits         Usage
 7 and 6      Select channel :
                 0 0 = Channel 0
                 0 1 = Channel 1
                 1 0 = Channel 2
                 1 1 = Read-back command (8254 only)
 5 and 4      Access mode :
                 0 0 = Latch count value command
                 0 1 = Access mode: lobyte only
                 1 0 = Access mode: hibyte only
                 1 1 = Access mode: lobyte/hibyte
 3 to 1       Operating mode :
                 0 0 0 = Mode 0 (interrupt on terminal count)
                 0 0 1 = Mode 1 (hardware re-triggerable one-shot)
                 0 1 0 = Mode 2 (rate generator)
                 0 1 1 = Mode 3 (square wave generator)
                 1 0 0 = Mode 4 (software triggered strobe)
                 1 0 1 = Mode 5 (hardware triggered strobe)
                 1 1 0 = Mode 2 (rate generator, same as 010b)
                 1 1 1 = Mode 3 (square wave generator, same as 011b)
 0            BCD/Binary mode: 0 = 16-bit binary, 1 = four-digit BCD

The "Select Channel" bits select which channel is being configured, and must always be valid on every write of the mode/command register, regardless of the other bits or the type of operation being performed. The "read back" (both bits set) is not supported on the old 8253 chips but should be supported on all AT and later computers except for PS/2 (i.e. anything that isn't obsolete will support it). The "read back" command is discussed later.

The "Access Mode" bits tell the PIT what access mode you wish to use for the selected channel, and also specify [[#Counter Latch Command|the "counter latch" command]] to the CTC. These bits must be valid on every write to the mode/command register. For [[#Read Back Command|the "read back" command]], these bits have a different meaning. For the remaining combinations, these bits specify what order data will be read and written to the data port for the associated PIT channel. Because the data port is an 8 bit I/O port and the values involved are all 16 bit, the PIT chip needs to know what byte each read or write to the data port wants. For "lobyte only" and "hibyte only", only the lowest/highest 8 bits of the counter value is read or written to/from the data port – the respective other 8 bits are zeroed (e.g. with "lobyte only", the highest 8 bits will be zeroed). For the "lobyte/hibyte" mode, 16 bits are always transferred as a pair, with the lowest 8 bits followed by the highest 8 bits (both 8 bit transfers are to the '''same''' IO port, sequentially – a word transfer will not work).

The "Operating Mode" bits specify which mode the selected PIT channel should operate in. For the "read back" command and the "counter latch" command, these bits have different meanings (see the information corresponding to these commands below). There are 6 different [[#Operating Modes|operating modes]]. Each operating mode will be discussed separately later.

The "BCD/Binary" bit determines if the PIT channel will operate in binary mode or BCD mode (where each 4 bits of the counter represent a decimal digit, and the counter holds values from 0000 to 9999). 80x86 PCs only use binary mode (BCD mode is ugly and limits the range of counts/frequencies possible). Although it should still be possible to use BCD mode, it may not work properly on some "compatible" chips. For the "read back" command and the "counter latch" command, this bit has different meanings (see the information corresponding to these commands below).

== Operating Modes ==
While each operating mode behaves differently, some things are common to all operating modes. This includes:

; '''Initial Output State'''
: Every time the mode/command register is written to, all internal logic in the selected PIT channel is reset, and the output immediately goes to its initial state (which depends on the mode).
; '''Changing Reload Value'''
: A new reload value can be written to a PIT channel's data port at any time. The operating mode determines the exact effect that this will have.
; '''Current Counter'''
: The current counter value is always either decremented or reset to the reload value on the ''falling'' edge of the (1.193182 MHz) input signal.
; '''Current Counter Reload'''
: In modes where the current count is decremented when it is reloaded, the current count is not decremented on the same input clock pulse as the reload – it starts decrementing on the ''next'' input clock pulse.

=== Mode 0 – Interrupt On Terminal Count ===
For this mode, when the mode/command register is written the output signal goes low and the PIT waits for the reload register to be set by software, to begin the countdown. After the reload register has been set, the current count will be set to the reload value on the next falling edge of the (1.193182 MHz) input signal. Subsequent falling edges of the input signal will decrement the current count (if the gate input is high on the preceding rising edge of the input signal).

When the current count decrements from one to zero, the output goes high and remains high until another mode/command register is written or the reload register is set again. The current count will wrap around to 0xFFFF (or 0x9999 in BCD mode) and continue to decrement until the mode/command register or the reload register are set, however this will not affect the output pin state.

The reload value can be changed at any time. In "lobyte/hibyte" access mode counting will stop when the first byte of the reload value is set. Once the full reload value is set (in any access mode), the next falling edge of the (1.193182 MHz) input signal will cause the new reload value to be copied into the current count, and the countdown will continue from the new value.

Note: despite the misleading name of this mode, it only generates interrupts on channel 0.

=== Mode 1 – Hardware Re-triggerable One-shot ===
This mode is similar to mode 0 above, however counting doesn't start until a rising edge of the gate input is detected. For this reason it is not usable for PIT channels 0 or 1 (where the gate input can't be changed).

When the mode/command register is written the output signal goes high and the PIT waits for the reload register to be set by software. After the reload register has been set the PIT will wait for the next rising edge of the gate input. Once this occurs, the output signal will go low and the current count will be set to the reload value on the next falling edge of the (1.193182 MHz) input signal. Subsequent falling edges of the input signal will decrement the current count.

When the current count decrements from one to zero, the output goes high and remains high until another mode/command register is written or the reload register is set again. The current count will wrap around to 0xFFFF (or 0x9999 in BCD mode) and continue to decrement until the mode/command register or the reload register are set, however this will not affect the output pin state.

If the gate input signal goes low during this process it will have no effect. However, if the gate input goes high again it will cause the current count to be reloaded from the reload register on the next falling edge of the input signal, and restart the count again (the same as when counting first started).

The reload value can be changed at any time, however the new value will not affect the current count until the current count is reloaded (on the next rising edge of the gate input). So if you want to do this, clear and then reset bit 0 of IO port 0x61, after modifying the reload value.

=== Mode 2 – Rate Generator ===
This mode operates as a frequency divider.

When the mode/command register is written the output signal goes high and the PIT waits for the reload register to be set by software. After the reload register has been set, the current count will be set to the reload value on the next falling edge of the (1.193182 MHz) input signal. Subsequent falling edges of the input signal will decrement the current count (if the gate input is high on the preceding rising edge of the input signal).

When the current count decrements from two to one, the output goes low, and on the next falling edge of the (1.193182 MHz) input signal it will go high again and the current count will be set to the reload value and counting will continue.

If the gate input goes low, counting stops and the output goes high immediately. Once the gate input has returned high, the next falling edge on input signal will cause the current count to be set to the reload value and operation will continue.

The reload value can be changed at any time, however the new value will not affect the current count until the current count is reloaded (when it is decreased from two to one, or the gate input going low then high). When this occurs counting will continue using the new reload value.

A reload value (or divisor) of one must ''not'' be used with this mode.

This mode creates a high output signal that drops low for one input signal cycle (0.8381 uS), which is too fast to make a difference to the PC speaker (see mode 3). For this reason mode 2 is useless for producing sounds with PIT channel 2.

Typically, OSes and BIOSes use mode 3 (see below) for PIT channel 0 to generate IRQ 0 timer ticks, but some use mode 2 instead, to gain frequency accuracy (frequency = 1193182 / reload_value Hz).

=== Mode 3 – Square Wave Generator ===
For mode 3, the PIT channel operates as a frequency divider like mode 2, however the output signal is fed into an internal "flip flop" to produce a square wave (rather than a short pulse). The flip flop changes its output state each time its input state (or the output of the PIT channel's frequency divider) changes. This causes the actual output to change state half as often, so to compensate for this the current count is decremented twice on each falling edge of the input signal (instead of once), and the current count is set to the reload value twice as often.

When the mode/command register is written the output signal goes high and the PIT waits for the reload register to be set by software. After the reload register has been set, the current count will be set to the reload value on the next falling edge of the (1.193182 MHz) input signal. Subsequent falling edges of the input signal will decrement the current count twice (if the gate input is high on the preceding rising edge of the input signal).

Note: under normal circumstances the output state will be low 50% of the time when the mode/command register is written. The output will then go high, which will generate an immediate (perhaps spurious) IRQ0. The other 50% of the time the output will already be high, and there will be no IRQ0 generated.

For even reload values, when the current count decrements from two to zero the output of the flip-flop changes state; the current count will be reset to the reload value and counting will continue.

For odd reload values, the current count is always set to one less than the reload value.
If the output of the flip flop is low when the current count decrements from two to zero it will behave the same as the equivalent even reload value. However, if the output of the flip flop is high the reload will be delayed for one input signal cycle (0.8381 uS), which causes the "high" pulse to be slightly longer and the duty cycle will not be exactly 50%. Because the reload value is rounded down to the nearest even number anyway, it is recommended that only even reload values be used (which means you should mask the value before sending it to the port).

Note: This even value limitation on the reload value in mode 3 reduces the number of possible output frequencies in half. If you want to be able to control the frequency of IRQ0 to a somewhat higher degree, then think about using mode 2 instead for channel 0.

On channel 2, if the gate input goes low, counting stops and the output goes high immediately. Once the gate input has returned high, the next falling edge on input signal will cause the current count to be set to the reload value and operation will continue (with the output left high).

The reload value can be changed at any time, however the new value will not affect the current count until the current count is reloaded (when it is decreased from two to zero, or the gate input going low then high). When this occurs counting will continue using the new reload value.

A reload value (or divisor) of one must ''not'' be used with this mode.

=== Mode 4 – Software Triggered Strobe ===
Mode four operates as a retriggerable delay, and generates a pulse when the current count reaches zero.

When the mode/command register is written the output signal goes high and the PIT waits for the reload register to be set by software. After the reload register has been set, the current count will be set to the reload value on the next falling edge of the (1.193182 MHz) input signal. Subsequent falling edges of the input signal will decrement the current count (if the gate input is high on the preceding rising edge of the input signal).

When the current count decrements from one to zero, the output goes low for one cycle of the input signal (0.8381 uS). The current count will wrap around to 0xFFFF (or 0x9999 in BCD mode) and continue to decrement until the mode/command register or the reload register are set, however this will not affect the output state.

If the gate input goes low, counting stops but the output will not be affected and the current count will not be reset to the reload value.

The reload value can be changed at any time. When the new value has been set (both bytes for "lobyte/hibyte" access mode) it will be loaded into the current count on the next falling edge of the (1.193182 MHz) input signal, and counting will continue using the new reload value.

=== Mode 5 – Hardware Triggered Strobe ===
Mode 5 is similar to mode 4, except that it waits for the rising edge of the gate input to trigger (or re-trigger) the delay period (like mode 1). For this reason it is not usable for PIT channels 0 or 1 (where the gate input can't be changed).

When the mode/command register is written the output signal goes high and the PIT waits for the reload register to be set by software. After the reload register has been set the PIT will wait for the next rising edge of the gate input. Once this occurs, the current count will be set to the reload value on the next falling edge of the (1.193182 MHz) input signal. Subsequent falling edges of the input signal will decrement the current count.

When the current count decrements from one to zero, the output goes low for one cycle of the input signal (0.8381 uS). The current count will wrap around to 0xFFFF (or 0x9999 in BCD mode) and continue to decrement until the mode/command register or the reload register are set, however this will not affect the output state.

If the gate input signal goes low during this process it will have no effect. However, if the gate input goes high again it will cause the current count to be reloaded from the reload register on the next falling edge of the input signal, and restart the count again (the same as when counting first started).

The reload value can be changed at any time, however the new value will not affect the current count until the current count is reloaded (on the next rising edge of the gate input). When this occurs counting will continue using the new reload value.

== Counter Latch Command ==
To prevent the current count from being updated, it is possible to "latch" a PIT channel using the latch command. To do this, send the value CC000000 (in binary) to the mode/command register (I/O port 0x43), where 'CC' corresponds to the channel number. When the latch command has been sent, the current count is copied into an internal "latch register" which can then be read via the data port corresponding to the selected channel (I/O ports 0x40 to 0x42). The value kept in the latch register remains the same until it has been fully read, or until a new mode/command register is written.

The main benefit of the latch command is that it allows both bytes of the current count to be read without inconsistencies. For example, if you didn't use the latch command, then the current count may decrease from 0x0200 to 0x01FF after you've read the low byte but before you've read the high byte, so that your software thinks the counter was 0x0100 instead of 0x0200 (or 0x01FF).

While the latch command should not affect the current count, on some (old/dodgy) motherboards sending the latch command can cause a cycle of the input signal to be occasionally missed, which would cause the current count to be decremented 0.8381ms later than it should be. If you're sending the latch command often this could cause accuracy problems (but if you need to send the latch command often you may wish to consider redesigning your code anyway).

== Read Back Command ==
The read back command is a special command sent to the mode/command register (I/O port 0x43). The "read back" is not supported on the old 8253 chips but should be supported on all AT and later computers except for PS/2 (i.e. anything that isn't obsolete will support it).

For the read back command, the mode/command register uses the following format:

 Bits         Usage
 7 and 6      Must be set for the read back command
 5            Latch count flag (0 = latch count, 1 = don't latch count)
 4            Latch status flag (0 = latch status, 1 = don't latch status)
 3            Read back timer channel 2 (1 = yes, 0 = no)
 2            Read back timer channel 1 (1 = yes, 0 = no)
 1            Read back timer channel 0 (1 = yes, 0 = no)
 0            Reserved (should be clear)

Note: Be careful with bits 4 and 5 – they are inverted.

Bits 1 to 3 of the read back command select which PIT channels are affected, and allow multiple channels to be selected at the same time.

If bit 5 is clear, then any/all PIT channels selected with bits 1 to 3 will have their current count copied into their latch register (similar to sending the latch command, except it works for multiple channels with one command).

If bit 4 is clear, then for any/all PIT channels selected with bits 1 to 3, the next read of the corresponding data port will return a status byte (discussed below).

=== Read Back Status Byte ===

After sending a read back command with bit 4 clear, reading the data port for each selected channel will return a status value with the following format:

 Bit/s        Usage
 7            Output pin state
 6            Null count flags
 5 and 4      Access mode :
                 0 0 = Latch count value command
                 0 1 = Access mode: lobyte only
                 1 0 = Access mode: hibyte only
                 1 1 = Access mode: lobyte/hibyte
 3 to 1       Operating mode :
                 0 0 0 = Mode 0 (interrupt on terminal count)
                 0 0 1 = Mode 1 (hardware re-triggerable one-shot)
                 0 1 0 = Mode 2 (rate generator)
                 0 1 1 = Mode 3 (square wave generator)
                 1 0 0 = Mode 4 (software triggered strobe)
                 1 0 1 = Mode 5 (hardware triggered strobe)
                 1 1 0 = Mode 2 (rate generator, same as 010b)
                 1 1 1 = Mode 3 (square wave generator, same as 011b)
 0            BCD/Binary mode: 0 = 16-bit binary, 1 = four-digit BCD

The bottom six bits return the values that where programmed into the mode/command register when the channel was last initialized.

Bit 7 indicates the state of the PIT channel's output pin at the moment that the read-back command was issued.

Bit 6 indicates whether a newly-programmed divisor value has been loaded into the current count yet (if clear) or the channel is still waiting for a trigger signal or for the current count to count down to zero before a newly programmed reload value is loaded into the current count (if set). This bit is set when the mode/command register is initialized or when a new reload value is written, and cleared when the reload value is copied into the current count.

== Reading The Current Count ==
To read the current count using the "lobyte only" or "hibyte only" access modes, you can just do an "in al,0x40" (for PIT channel 0) without problems. For frequencies higher than 4.7 KHz it can be easiest to set the high byte of the reload value to zero, and then use the "lobyte only" access mode to minimize hassles.

For the "lobyte/hibyte" access mode you need to send the latch command (described above) to avoid getting wrong results. If any other code could try set the PIT channel's reload value or read its current count after you've sent the latch command but before you've read the highest 8 bits, then you have to prevent it. Disabling interrupts works for single CPU computers. For example, to read the count of PIT channel 0 you could use something like:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
unsigned read_pit_count(void) {
	unsigned count = 0;
	
	// Disable interrupts
	cli();
	
	// al = channel in bits 6 and 7, remaining bits clear
	outb(0x43,0b0000000);
	
	count = inb(0x40);		// Low byte
	count |= inb(0x40)&lt;&lt;8;		// High byte
	
	return count;
}
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

== Setting The Reload Value ==
To set the reload value, just send the value/s to the corresponding data port. For the "lobyte only" or "hibyte only" access modes this only takes a single "out 0x40,al" (for PIT channel 0).

For the "lobyte/hibyte" access mode you need to send the low 8 bits followed by the high 8 bits. You must prevent other code from setting the PIT channel's reload value or reading its current count once you've sent the lowest 8 bits. Disabling interrupts works for single CPU computers. For example:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
void set_pit_count(unsigned count) {
	// Disable interrupts
	cli();
	
	// Set low byte
	outb(0x40,count&amp;0xFF);		// Low byte
	outb(0x40,(count&amp;0xFF00)&gt;&gt;8);	// High byte
	return;
}
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

It should be noted that a reload value of zero can be used to specify a divisor of 65536. This is how the BIOS gets an IRQ 0 frequency as low as 18.2065 Hz. It should also be noted that setting the divisor to an exceptionally low value (resulting in an exceptionally high frequency) can freeze any and all programs, including the kernel. It is advised to keep the frequency between a reasonable range. For reference, newer versions of the Linux kernel defaulted to 1000hz (a divisor ≈1193.182).

== PIT Channel 0 Example Code ==
The following example code was written for NASM, but hasn't been tested.

The idea is to provide a single routine to initialize PIT channel 0 for any (possible) frequency and use IRQ 0 to accurately keep track of real time in milliseconds since the PIT was configured.

For the sake of accuracy, the initialization code will calculate the number of whole milliseconds to add to the "system timer tick" each IRQ, and the number of "fractions of a millisecond" to avoid drift. This may be important, for example if the PIT is set for 700 Hz it'd work out to (roughly) 1.42857 ms between IRQs, so keeping track of whole milliseconds only would lead to huge inaccuracies.

Hopefully, everyone is familiar with fixed point mathematics. For example, with the "32.32" notation I'll be using, if the high 32-bit value is equal to 0x00000001 and the low 32-bit value is equal to 0x80000000 then the combined value would be 1.5. In a similar way, the fraction 0.75 is represented with 0xC000000, 0.125 is represented with 0x20000000 and 0.12345 would be represented with 0x1F9A6B50.

To begin with, this following code contains all of the data used by this example. It is assumed that the ".bss" section is filled with zeros.

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="nasm"&gt;
section .bss
system_timer_fractions:  resd 1          ; Fractions of 1 ms since timer initialized
system_timer_ms:         resd 1          ; Number of whole ms since timer initialized
IRQ0_fractions:          resd 1          ; Fractions of 1 ms between IRQs
IRQ0_ms:                 resd 1          ; Number of whole ms between IRQs
IRQ0_frequency:          resd 1          ; Actual frequency of PIT
PIT_reload_value:        resw 1          ; Current PIT reload value
section .text
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Next is the handler for IRQ 0. It's fairly simple (all it does it add 2 64 bit fixed point values and send an EOI to the PIC chip).

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="nasm"&gt;
IRQ0_handler:
	push eax
	push ebx
 
	mov eax, [IRQ0_fractions]
	mov ebx, [IRQ0_ms]                    ; eax.ebx = amount of time between IRQs
	add [system_timer_fractions], eax     ; Update system timer tick fractions
	adc [system_timer_ms], ebx            ; Update system timer tick milli-seconds
 
	mov al, 0x20
	out 0x20, al                          ; Send the EOI to the PIC

	pop ebx
	pop eax
	iretd
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Now for the tricky bit – the initialization routine. The PIT can't generate some frequencies. For example if you want 8000 Hz then you've got a choice of 8007.93 Hz or 7954.544 Hz. In this case the following code will find the nearest possible frequency. Once it has calculated the nearest possible frequency it will reverse the calculation to find the actual frequency selected (rounded to the nearest integer, intended for display purposes only).

For some extra accuracy, I also use "3579545 / 3" instead of 1193182 Hz. This is mostly pointless due to inaccurate hardware (I just like being correct).

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="nasm"&gt;
 ;Input
 ; ebx   Desired PIT frequency in Hz
 
 init_PIT:
    pushad
 
    ; Do some checking
 
    mov eax,0x10000                   ;eax = reload value for slowest possible frequency (65536)
    cmp ebx,18                        ;Is the requested frequency too low?
    jbe .gotReloadValue               ; yes, use slowest possible frequency
 
    mov eax,1                         ;ax = reload value for fastest possible frequency (1)
    cmp ebx,1193181                   ;Is the requested frequency too high?
    jae .gotReloadValue               ; yes, use fastest possible frequency
 
    ; Calculate the reload value
 
    mov eax,3579545
    mov edx,0                         ;edx:eax = 3579545
    div ebx                           ;eax = 3579545 / frequency, edx = remainder
    cmp edx,3579545 / 2               ;Is the remainder more than half?
    jb .l1                            ; no, round down
    inc eax                           ; yes, round up
 .l1:
    mov ebx,3
    mov edx,0                         ;edx:eax = 3579545 * 256 / frequency
    div ebx                           ;eax = (3579545 * 256 / 3 * 256) / frequency
    cmp edx,3 / 2                     ;Is the remainder more than half?
    jb .l2                            ; no, round down
    inc eax                           ; yes, round up
 .l2:
 
 
 ; Store the reload value and calculate the actual frequency
 
 .gotReloadValue:
    push eax                          ;Store reload_value for later
    mov [PIT_reload_value],ax         ;Store the reload value for later
    mov ebx,eax                       ;ebx = reload value
 
    mov eax,3579545
    mov edx,0                         ;edx:eax = 3579545
    div ebx                           ;eax = 3579545 / reload_value, edx = remainder
    cmp edx,3579545 / 2               ;Is the remainder more than half?
    jb .l3                            ; no, round down
    inc eax                           ; yes, round up
 .l3:
    mov ebx,3
    mov edx,0                         ;edx:eax = 3579545 / reload_value
    div ebx                           ;eax = (3579545 / 3) / frequency
    cmp edx,3 / 2                     ;Is the remainder more than half?
    jb .l4                            ; no, round down
    inc eax                           ; yes, round up
 .l4:
    mov [IRQ0_frequency],eax          ;Store the actual frequency for displaying later
 
 
 ; Calculate the amount of time between IRQs in 32.32 fixed point
 ;
 ; Note: The basic formula is:
 ;           time in ms = reload_value / (3579545 / 3) * 1000
 ;       This can be rearranged in the following way:
 ;           time in ms = reload_value * 3000 / 3579545
 ;           time in ms = reload_value * 3000 / 3579545 * (2^42)/(2^42)
 ;           time in ms = reload_value * 3000 * (2^42) / 3579545 / (2^42)
 ;           time in ms * 2^32 = reload_value * 3000 * (2^42) / 3579545 / (2^42) * (2^32)
 ;           time in ms * 2^32 = reload_value * 3000 * (2^42) / 3579545 / (2^10)
 
    pop ebx                           ;ebx = reload_value
    mov eax,0xDBB3A062                ;eax = 3000 * (2^42) / 3579545
    mul ebx                           ;edx:eax = reload_value * 3000 * (2^42) / 3579545
    shrd eax,edx,10
    shr edx,10                        ;edx:eax = reload_value * 3000 * (2^42) / 3579545 / (2^10)
 
    mov [IRQ0_ms],edx                 ;Set whole ms between IRQs
    mov [IRQ0_fractions],eax          ;Set fractions of 1 ms between IRQs
 
 
 ; Program the PIT channel
 
    pushfd
    cli                               ;Disabled interrupts (just in case)
 
    mov al,00110100b                  ;channel 0, lobyte/hibyte, rate generator
    out 0x43, al
 
    mov ax,[PIT_reload_value]         ;ax = 16 bit reload value
    out 0x40,al                       ;Set low byte of PIT reload value
    mov al,ah                         ;ax = high 8 bits of reload value
    out 0x40,al                       ;Set high byte of PIT reload value
 
    popfd
 
    popad
    ret
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Note: you also need to install an IDT entry for IRQ 0, and unmask it in the PIC chip (or I/O APIC).

Of course it's easier to configure the PIT to a fixed value, but where's the fun in that? :-)

==Uses for the Timer IRQ==
===Using the IRQ to Implement &lt;tt&gt;sleep&lt;/tt&gt;===
The PIT's generating a hardware interrupt every ''n'' milliseconds allows you to create a simple timer. Start with a global variable that contains the delay:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="C"&gt;
volatile uint32_t CountDown;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Next, every time the timer interrupt is called, decrement this variable until 0 is stored.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="nasm"&gt;
 section .text
 global TimerIRQ
 TimerIRQ:
     push eax
     mov eax, [CountDown]
     test eax, eax
     jz TimerDone
     dec eax
     mov [CountDown], eax
 TimerDone:
     pop eax
     iretd
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Finally, create a function &lt;tt&gt;sleep&lt;/tt&gt; that waits the interval, in milliseconds.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
void sleep(uint32_t millis) {
    CountDown = millis;
    while (CountDown &gt; 0) {
        halt();
    }
}
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

In a multitasking system, consider using a linked list or array of these CountDown variables. If your multitasking system supports interprocess communication, you can also store the semaphore/exchange where two processes can talk to, have the interrupt send a message to the waiting process when the timer is done, and have the waiting process block all execution until that message comes:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
#define COUNTDOWN_DONE_MSG 1
struct TimerBlock {
    EXCHANGE e;
    uint32_t CountDown;
} timerblocks[20];

void TimerIRQ(void) /* called from Assembly */
{
    uint8_t i;
    
    for (i = 0; i &lt; 20; i++)
        if (timerblocks[i].CountDown &gt; 0) {
            timerblocks[i].CountDown--;
            if (timerblocks[i].CountDown == 0)
                SendMessage(timerblocks[i].e, COUNTDOWN_DONE_MESSAGE);
        }
}

void Sleep(uint32_t delay)
{
    struct TimerBlock *t;

    if ((t = findTimerBlock()) == nil)
        return;
    t-&gt;CountDown = delay;
    WaitForMessageFrom(t-&gt;e = getCrntExch());
}
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

In your documentation, note the interval of the timer. For example, if the timer interval is 10 milliseconds per tick, tell the programmer to issue

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
Sleep(100);
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

to sleep for a single second.

===Using the IRQ for Preemptive Multitasking===
The timer IRQ can also be used to perform preemptive multitasking. To give the currently running task some time to run, set a threshold, for example of 3 ticks. Use a global variable like the one before but go up from 0, and when that variable hits 3, switch tasks. How you do so is up to you.

== See Also ==
=== Articles ===
* [[Time And Date]]
* [[RTC]]
* [[HPET]]
* [[APIC Timer]]

=== Threads ===
=== External Links ===
* [[wikipedia:Programmable Interval Timer | Programmable Interval Timer]] on Wikipedia
* [http://www.osdever.net/bkerndev/Docs/pit.htm The PIT: A System Clock] on osdever

[[Category:Common Devices]]
[[Category:Timers]]
[[Category:X86]]
[[de:Programmable_Interval_Timer]]</text>
      <sha1>in1g7hi054dm4c9lwm7wa4pkz0auwaz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Detecting CPU Speed</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1446</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30288</id>
      <parentid>29641</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-16T18:58:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Makaroneder</username>
        <id>1943</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Replace source tag with syntaxhighlight tag</comment>
      <origin>30288</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="13139" sha1="lm6p7d9dknea9630bileh70daar02ju" xml:space="preserve">==What is CPU Speed==

"CPU speed" has several different definitions:
# How quickly the processor can execute code (e.g. instructions per second)
# How fast the processor's clock is running (e.g. cycles per second)

How quickly a CPU can execute code is important for determining the CPU's performance. How fast a CPU's clock is running is only useful for specific cases (e.g. calibrating the CPU's TSC to use for measuring time).

There are also several different measurements for these different "CPU speeds":
# Best case
# Nominal case
# Average case
# Current case
# Worst case

For example, look at a modern Intel Core i7 CPU (with turbo-boost, power management and hyper-threading). The best case instructions per second would occur when:
# There is no throttling/power saving at all.
# Only one logical CPU is running (turbo-boost activated and hyper-threading not being used)
# Simple instructions with no dependencies in a loop that fits in the CPU's "loop buffer" are being executed
# There are no branch mispredictions
# There are no accesses to memory (no data being transferred to/from caches or RAM)

The worst case instructions per second would be the exact opposite and may be several orders of magnitude worse (e.g. a best case of 4 billion instructions per second and a worst case of 100 million instructions per second). The nominal instructions per second (commonly referred to as "nominal cycles per second") is an estimation of the normal average instructions per second a developer would expect. All of these things are fixed values - a specific CPU always has the same best case, worst case and nominal case, and these values don't change depending on CPU load, which instructions are/were executed, etc.

The current instructions per second is the instructions per second at a specific instant in time and must be somewhere between the best and worst cases. It can't be measured exactly, but can be estimated by finding the average instructions per second for a very short period of time. The average case is something that has to be measured. Both the current instructions per second and the average instructions per second depend heavily on the code that was running. For example, the average instructions per second for a series of NOP instructions may be much higher that the average instructions per second for a series of DIV instructions.


==General Method==

In order to tell what the CPU speed is, we need two things:
# Being able to tell that a given (precise) amount of time has elapsed.
# Being able to know how many 'clock cycles' a portion of code took.

Once these two sub-problems are solved, one can easily tell the CPU speed
using the following :

&lt;pre&gt;
prepare_a_timer(X milliseconds ahead);
while (timer has not fired) {
   inc iterations_counter;
}
cpuspeed_mhz = (iteration_counter * clock_cycles_per_iteration)/1000;
&lt;/pre&gt;

Note that except for very special cases, using a busy-loop (even calibrated) to introduce delays is a bad idea and that it should be kept for very small delays
(nano or micro seconds) that must be complied with when programming hardware only.

Also note that PC emulators (like BOCHS, for instance) are rarely realtime, resulting in the clock appearing to run faster
than expected.

=== Waiting for a given amount of time ===

There are two circuits in a PC to deal with time: the [[PIT]] (Programmable Interval Timer - Intel 8253 and 8254 are common PITs) and the RTC (Real Time Clock). The PIT is probably the better of the two for this task.

The PIT has two operating modes that can be useful for telling the CPU speed:
# the ''periodic interrupt'' mode (0x36), in which a signal is emitted to the interrupt controller at a fixed frequency. This is especially interesting on PIT channel 0 which is bound to IRQ0 on a PC.
# the ''one shot'' mode (0x34), in which the PIT will decrease a counter at its top speed (1.19318 MHz) until the counter reaches zero.

Whether or not an IRQ is fired by channel0 in 0x34 mode should be checked.

Note that theoretically, ''one shot'' mode could be used with a ''polling'' approach, reading the current count on the channel's data port, but I/O bus cycles have unpredictable latency and it is up to the programmer to make sure the timestamp counter is not affected by this approach.

=== Knowing how many cycles your loop takes ===

This step depends on the CPU. On 286, 386 and 486, each instruction takes
a well-known and deterministic amount of clock cycles to execute. This allows
the programmer to tell exactly how many cycles a loop iteration took by looking
up the timing of each instruction and then summing them up.

Since the multi-pipelined architecture of the Pentium; however, such numbers are
no longer communicated (for a major part because the same instruction could have
variable timings depending on its surrounding, which makes the timing almost useless).

It is possible to create code which is exceptionally pipeline hostile such as:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="asm"&gt;
xor eax,edx
xor edx,eax
xor eax,edx
xor edx,eax
...
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

A simple xor instruction takes one cycle, which guarantees that the processor cannot pipeline this code as the current instructions operands depend on the results from the last calculation. One can check that, for a small count (tested from 16 to 64), RDTSC will show the instruction count is almost exactly (sometimes off by one) the cycles count. Unfortunately, when making the chain longer, code cache misses will occur, ruining the whole process.

E.g. [http://www.sylvain-ulg.be.tf/resources/speed.c looping on a chain of 1550 XORs] may require a hundred of iterations before it stabilizes around 1575 clock cycles on a AMDx86-64 and will take an exceedingly long time to stabilize on a Pentium3.

Despite this inaccuracy, it gives relatively good results across the whole processor generation given a reasonably accurate timer. If very accurate measurements are needed the next method should prove more useful.

A Pentium developer has a much better tool to tell timings: the ''Time Stamp Counter'': an internal counter that can be read using RDTSC special instruction

[https://www.ccsl.carleton.ca/~jamuir/rdtscpm1.pdf rdtscpm1.pdf] explains how that feature can be used for performance monitoring and should provide the necessary information on how to access the TSC on a Pentium.

===RDTSC Instruction Access===

The presence of the Time Stamp Counter (and thus the availability of RDTSC instruction) can be detected through the [CPUID] instruction. Calling CPUID with eax=1, will put feature flags in edx. TSC is bit four of that field.

Note that prior to using the CPUID instruction, make sure the processor supports it by testing the 'ID' bit in eflags. (This is 0x200000 and is modifiable only when CPUID instruction is supported. For systems that doesn't support CPUID, writing a '1' at that place will have no effect.)

In the case of a processor that does not support CPUID, you'll have to use more eflags-based tests to tell if a 486, 386, etc. is running and then pick up one of the 'calibrated loops' for that architecture (8086 through 80486 may have variable instruction timings).


=== Working Example Code===

A Real Mode Intel-copyrighted example is present in the above-mentioned application note.
Another code snippet submitted by user DennisCGC that will give the total measured frequency of a Pentium processor follows.

Some notes:
*  ''irq0_count'' is a variable, which increases each time when the timer interrupt is called.
*  In this code it's assumed that the [PIT] is programmed to 100 Hz (The formula to calculate a desired Hz is provided in the snippet.)
*  The code assumes that the command CPUID is supported.

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang = "asm"&gt;
;__get_speed__:
   ;first do a cpuid command, with eax=1
   mov  eax,1
   cpuid
   test edx,byte 0x10      ; test bit #4. Do we have TSC ?
   jz   detect_end         ; no ?, go to detect_end
   ;wait until the timer interrupt has been called.
   mov  ebx, ~[irq0_count]

;__wait_irq0__:

   cmp  ebx, ~[irq0_count]
   jz   wait_irq0
   rdtsc                   ; read time stamp counter
   mov  ~[tscLoDword], eax
   mov  ~[tscHiDword], edx
   add  ebx, 2             ; Set time delay value ticks.
   ; remember: so far ebx = ~[irq0]-1, so the next tick is
   ; two steps ahead of the current ebx ;)

;__wait_for_elapsed_ticks__:

   cmp  ebx, ~[irq0_count] ; Have we hit the delay?
   jnz  wait_for_elapsed_ticks
   rdtsc
   sub eax, ~[tscLoDword]  ; Calculate TSC
   sbb edx, ~[tscHiDword]
   ; f(total_ticks_per_Second) =  (1 / total_ticks_per_Second) * 1,000,000
   ; This adjusts for MHz.
   ; so for this: f(100) = (1/100) * 1,000,000 = 10000
   mov ebx, 10000
   div ebx
   ; ax contains measured speed in MHz
   mov ~[mhz], ax
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

See the Intel manual (see links) for more information.
:- bugs report are welcome. IM to [http://www.mega-tokyo.com/forum/index.php?action=viewprofile;user=DennisCGc DennisCGC]

=== Without Interrupts ===

{{Tone}}

I'd be tempted to say 'yes', though I haven't gave it a test nor heard of it elsewhere so far. Here is the trick:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="C"&gt;
disable()     // disable interrupts (if still not done)
outb(0x43,0x34);   // set PIT channel 0 to single-shot mode
outb(0x40,0);
outb(0x40,0);      // program the counter will be 0x10000 - n after n ticks
long stsc=CPU::readTimeStamp();
for (int i=0x1000;i&gt;0;i--);
long etsc=CPU::readTimeStamp();
outb(0x43,0x04);   // read PIT counter command ??
byte lo=inb(0x40);
byte hi=inb(0x40);
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Now, we know that
* ticks=(0x10000 - (hi*256+lo)) periods of 1/1193180 seconds have elapsed at least and no more than ticks+1.
* etsc-stsc clock cycles have elapsed during the same time.

Thus (etsc-stsc)*1193180 / ticks should be your CPU speed in Hz ...

As far as i can say, 0x1000 iterations lead to 10 PIT ticks on a 1GHz CPU and a bit less than 0x8000 ticks on the same CPU running BOCHS. This certainly means that on very high speed systems, the discovered speed may not be accurate at all, or worse, less than 1 tick could occur ...

This technique is currently under evaluation in [the forum|Forum:5849]

:- hope you like my technique /PypeClicker

== Asking the SMBios for CPU speed ==
{{Main|SMBIOS}}

The [[SMBIOS]] (System Management BIOS) Specification addresses how motherboard and system vendors present management information about their products in a standard format by extending the BIOS interface on Intel architecture systems. The information is intended to allow generic instrumentation to deliver this information to management applications that use DMI, CIM or direct access, eliminating the need for error prone operations like probing system hardware for presence detection.

Do note that SMBIOS was never intended for initialization purposes. It was intended to provide information for asset management systems to quickly determine what computers contained what hardware. Unfortunately this means that it might be quite unreliable, especially on cheap/home systems. So ultimately it may not be the best way to determine CPU speed.

===SMBios Processor Information===

A Processor information (type 4) structure describes features of the CPU as detected by the SMBios. The exact structure is depicted in section 3.3.5 (p 39) of the [http://www.dmtf.org/standards/documents/SMBIOS/DSP0134.pdf standard]. Within that information you will find the processor type, family, manufacturer etc. and also:
* the External Clock (bus) frequency, which is a word at offset 0x12,
* the Maximum CPU speed in MHz, which is a word at offset 0x14 (e.g. 0xe9 is a 233MHz processor),
* the Current CPU speed in MHz, (word at offset 0x16).

===Getting the SMBIOS Structure===

SMBios provide a _Get SMBIOS Information_ function that tells you how many structures exists. You can then use _Get SMBIOS Structure_ function to read processor information.

As an alternative, you can locate the _SMBIOS Entry Point_ and then traverse manually the SMBIOS structure table, looking for type 4.

All this is depicted in 'Accessing SMBIOS Information' structure of the standard (p 11).

==Links==

===Related threads in the forum===
*Forum:5849
*Forum:767
*Forum:922
*Forum:8949 featuring info on bogomips, how linux does it and durand's code.
* https://forum.osdev.org/viewtopic.php?f=1&amp;t=32808


===Other resources===
* http://cs.usfca.edu/~cruse/cs630s04/lesson23.ppt‎, a crash course on PIT, and how to use it to compute CPU speed.
* http://www.sandpile.org/post/msgs/20004561.htm
* http://www.midnightbeach.com/jon/pubs/rdtsc.htm

*ftp://download.intel.com/support/processors/procid/
:especially section 12: "Operating Frequency" on page 29 of [ftp://download.intel.com/support/processors/procid/24161815.pdf 24161815.pdf]

&lt;!--Searching for SMBIOS should give you info on that too, it contains entries about the CPU, including current speed.--&gt;
====Regarding SMBIOS====
*http://www.dmtf.org/standards/smbios
*http://www.dmtf.org/standards/documents/SMBIOS/DSP0134.pdf
*http://www.pcpitstop.com/faq/smbios.asp

[[Category:X86 CPU]]
[[Category:Hardware Detection]]</text>
      <sha1>lm6p7d9dknea9630bileh70daar02ju</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Intel VT-d</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5063</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30803</id>
      <parentid>30802</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-06-20T21:39:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Demindiro</username>
        <id>1745</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Emulation */ info mtree should be under QEMU section</comment>
      <origin>30803</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3963" sha1="717deorvjgsrtbi6o0cwy7p7yrhvldo" xml:space="preserve">{{stub}}

Intel VT-d provides an [[IOMMU]] to translate device addresses to host addresses, similar to the MMU on the CPU. It is also able to remap interrupt lines.

The location of the configuration registers can be found in the DMAR [[ACPI]] table. Note, DMAR is specific to VT-d.

== DMAR ==
VT-d is found by locating the DMAR ACPI table, much like the [[MADT]].
{| class="wikitable"
|+
!Offset
!0
!1
!2  
!3  
!4
!5
!6
!7
|-
|0x0
| colspan="4" |Signature
| colspan="4" |Length
|-
|0x8
|REV
|CHK
| colspan="6" |OEMID
|-
|0x10
| colspan="8" |OEM Table ID
|-
|0x18
| colspan="4" |OEM Revision
| colspan="4" |Creator ID
|-
|0x20
| colspan="4" |Creator Revision
|HAW
|FLG
| colspan="2" |Resevred
|-
|0x28
| colspan="8" |Reserved
|-
|0x30
| colspan="8" rowspan="4" |DRHD #1
|-
|0x38
|-
|0x40
|-
|0x48
|-
|0x50
| colspan="8" rowspan="3" |DRHD #2
|-
|0x58
|-
|0x60
|-
|0x68
| colspan="8" rowspan="2" |DRHD...
|-
|0x70...
|}
Signature: "DMAR".

== Translation structures ==

There are two translation formats: ''legacy'' and ''scalable''. The legacy format is simpler but lacks useful features. Importantly, it only supports second-stage page tables '''which are not compatible with [[X86 Paging]] tables'''.

This section will only discuss the scalable format, which supports first-stage translation and is directly compatible with 64-bit x86 page tables&lt;ref&gt;Section 3.6: "First-stage translation supports the same paging structures as Intel® 64 processors when operating in
64-bit mode"&lt;/ref&gt;.

Note that the tables are all 4KiB in size and alignment. This can be used as a sanity check when defining structures.

{{AdmonitionNote|text=Requests to the &lt;code&gt;0xFEEx_xxxx&lt;/code&gt; region do not go through DMA translation tables. See the Interrupt Remapping section.}}

=== Scalable Mode Root Table ===

The root table consists of 256 '''Root Entries''', with each entry corresponding to a single bus. Each entry points to a single ''Context Table''.

==== (Lower/Upper) Context Table ====

The context table is split in two equally sized halves, each half containing 128 entries for a total of 256 entries.

Each entry corresponds to a single device function.

=== Scalable Mode PASID structures ===

The PASID tree consists of a directory and tables, similar to page tables. Each directory entry points to a table.

The [[Process Address Space ID (PCIe)|PASID]] is either a default value ("request-without-PASID") or included in the [[Transaction Layer Packet (PCIe)|TLP]] ("request-with-PASID").

=== First-Stage Page Table Structures ===

These page tables are fully compatible with the CPU page tables. However, some of the otherwise ignored bits may be accessed and interpreted specially by the IOMMU.

==== Extended Access bit ====

== Interrupt Remapping ==

=== MSI / MSI-X ===

Any write requests to the &lt;code&gt;0xFEEx_xxxx&lt;/code&gt; region '''do not go through DMA translation tables'''.

== Emulation ==

=== QEMU ===

To use an emulated VT-d IOMMU with support for scalable mode and first-stage translation structures, add the following argument:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="sh"&gt;
-device intel-iommu,x-scalable-mode=on,x-flts=on
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
(&lt;code&gt;flts&lt;/code&gt; is a historical acronym meaning "First-Layer Translation Structures")

==== &lt;code&gt;info mtree&lt;/code&gt; ====

The memory regions used by the emulated devices will look like this:

&lt;pre&gt;
memory-region: vtd-1f.2
  0000000000000000-ffffffffffffffff (prio 0, container): vtd-1f.2
    0000000000000000-ffffffffffffffff (prio 0, i/o): vtd-1f.2-dmar
      00000000fee00000-00000000feefffff (prio 1, i/o): alias vtd-ir @vtd-ir 0000000000000000-00000000000fffff
&lt;/pre&gt;

Note the &lt;code&gt;vtd-ir&lt;/code&gt; range with higher priority than the &lt;code&gt;dmar&lt;/code&gt; range.

== See also ==

&lt;references /&gt;

=== External Links ===

* [https://cdrdv2-public.intel.com/671081/vt-directed-io-spec.pdf Intel® Virtualization Technology for Directed I/O (June 2022 Revision 4.0)]

[[Category:X86 Virtualization]]
[[Category:X86-64]]</text>
      <sha1>717deorvjgsrtbi6o0cwy7p7yrhvldo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>IOMMU</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5001</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30116</id>
      <parentid>30112</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-03T15:35:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bellezzasolo</username>
        <id>714</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Add some more</comment>
      <origin>30116</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1265" sha1="ogqzt5cbo652yd3ccqprkpxl9uavwqp" xml:space="preserve">{{Stub}}

An '''IOMMU''' (Input Output Memory Management Unit) implements a form of Virtual Memory through [[Paging]], for I/O devices. This means that their [[DMA]] transactions can be access-controlled, and remapped, instead of directly accessing physical memory.

== Uses ==
IOMMUs have more than one use. The most obvious deployment is using a [[Hypervisor]]. Guest OSes in virtual machines can then access virtualized hardware that is passed-through to the guest VM, but the IOMMU will remap Guest Physical Addresses to the real memory backing it, and prevent DMA accesses beyond the bounds of the VM.

However, the same principles may also be applied to application software running in an unprivileged context, too. Some IOMMUs use the same paging format at the CPU, and nested translation too. This means they can translate Virtual Addresses, to Guest Physical Address, to Physical Addresses. Using this, it is possible to allow Ring 3 software to communicate directly with the hardware, and program DMA, without breaking security. Some modern graphics cards support this for performance reasons, for instance.

== Implementations ==

=== X86 ===

* [[AMD-Vi IOMMU]]
* [[Intel VT-d]]

=== ARM ===

* [[ARM SMMU versions 1 and 2]]

[[Category:Virtualization]]</text>
      <sha1>ogqzt5cbo652yd3ccqprkpxl9uavwqp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>SVM</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5006</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30150</id>
      <timestamp>2026-03-06T10:57:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bellezzasolo</username>
        <id>714</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>AMD SVM</comment>
      <origin>30150</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="553" sha1="1vkgz7t1ip8nr9g3f4i7gs9rl77uy5i" xml:space="preserve">{{Stub}}

'''AMD's Secure Virtual Machine''' is AMD's counterpart to Intel's [[VMX]] instructions.

== Programming == 

=== Discovering support ===
After enumerating the features from [[CPUID]], page 0x80000001, bit 2 in ECX indicates support for SVM.

Next, the VM_CR MSR (0xC00010114) needs to be consulted. Bit 4, SVMDIS, must be zero. If set, the CPU supports SVM, but it has been disabled by the platform firmware.


=== Basic environment ===
Software should enable bit 12 of EFER (EFER.SVME) first.

==References==

[[Category:X86 Virtualization]]</text>
      <sha1>1vkgz7t1ip8nr9g3f4i7gs9rl77uy5i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>VMX</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2598</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30309</id>
      <parentid>30113</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-17T18:52:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Makaroneder</username>
        <id>1943</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Replace source tag with syntaxhighlight tag and pre tag</comment>
      <origin>30309</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8650" sha1="02te35eqrgcq7axh42adk3e0luh7jre" xml:space="preserve">{{Stub}}

'''Intel's Virtual-Machine Extensions''' 

== Programming == 

=== Discovering support ===
After enumerating the features from [[CPUID]], bit 5 in ECX will tell you if VMX is supported or not.  This is the first thing that should be checked!

=== Basic environment ===
Software should enable bit 13 of CR4 (CR4.VMXE) first.  Here are a few definitions of some used MSR's that we'll be dealing with: 
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
 #define IA32_VMX_BASIC          0x480
 #define IA32_VMX_CR0_FIXED0     0x486
 #define IA32_VMX_CR0_FIXED1     0x487
 #define IA32_VMX_CR4_FIXED0     0x488
 #define IA32_VMX_CR4_FIXED1     0x489
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

In order to see what your OS needs to support, you need to read the lower 32-bits of IA32_VMX_CR0_FIXED0 and IA32_VMX_CR4_FIXED0.  The bits in those MSR's are what need to be set (and supported) in their corresponding control registers (CR0/CR4).  If any of those bits are not enabled, a GPF will occur.  Also, to see what extra bits can be set, check the IA32_VMX_CR0_FIXED1 and IA32_VMX_CR4_FIXED1.  It's basically a mask of bits, if a bit is set to 1, then it "can" be enabled, but if it's a 0, you may generate an exception if you enable the corresponding bit in the control registers. 

From my own hardware and emulator (bochs), I've found that you will most likely need to enable these bits: CR0.NE, CR4.VMXE, CR0.PG and CR0.PE. For 64-bit kernels, you need to have IA32_EFER.LMA set.

=== Executing VMXON ===
The main entry point for using VMX is through the VMXON instruction.  The instruction requires a single operand of a m64 region called the VMXON region.  The memory region needs to be 4096-byte aligned (bits 0-11 must be 0) and the only VMCS field that should be modified is the VMCS revision identification field.  This ID field should contain the value in bits 0-31 of MSR IA32_VMX_BASIC.  In order to prepare a memory address in 32-bit PMode for use as an m64, some modifications need to be made.  The upper 32-bits of the m64 on non long mode capable processors have to be 0 or an "invalid memory address" error will occur and a VMEXIT will be called.  
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
 uint32_t * region = (uint32_t *)allocate_4k_aligned(4096);
 uint64_t region64 = (uint64_t)((size_t)(region) &amp; 0xFFFFFFFF);
 asm volatile("  vmxon %0; "::"m" (region64));
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

This general process of taking a 32-bit memory address and turning it into a psuedo-64bit int (unsigned long long) will be used for all m64 operands later.  VMCLEAR is another example instruction that requires the upper 32-bits of a memory address to be 0.  

Long mode capable processors simply requires a 64-bit pointer to the region.  

Note: '''The VMXON, VMCLEAR and VMPTRLD instruction must point to the physical address of their respective regions.'''

== VMX instruction error checking ==

VMX instructions have their own error reporting mechanism to indicate the success or failure of a given operation.

There are two flags used to signify the success or failure of a VM instruction.  The carry flag(CF) and the zero flag(ZF).

If both of these flags are clear after a VM instruction was executed then it succeeded.

If the carry flag is set then current VMCS pointer is invalid.

If the zero flag is set, it indicates that the VMCS pointer is valid but there is some other error specified in the VM-instruction error field (encoding 4400h).  Error numbers are listed in section 5.4 of the Intel SDM Volume 2B.

The following table represents the error numbers in the VM-instruction error field:

{| {{wikitable}}
|-
! Error Number !! Description
|-
| 0x01 || VMCALL executed in VMX root operation
|-
| 0x02 || VMCLEAR with invalid physical address.
|-
| 0x03 || VMCLEAR with VMXON pointer.
|-
| 0x04 || VMLAUNCH with non-clear VMCS.
|-
| 0x05 || VMRESUME with non-launched VMCS.
|-
| 0x06 || VMRESUME with a corrupted VMCS. Indicates corruption of the current VMCS
|-
| 0x07 || VM entry with invalid VMX-control field(s).
|-
| 0x08 || VM entry with invalid host-state field(s).
|-
| 0x09 || VMPTRLD with invalid physical address.
|-
| 0x0A || VMPTRLD with VMXON pointer.
|-
| 0x0B || VMPTRLD with incorrect VMCS revision identifier.
|-
| 0x0C || VMREAD/VMWRITE from/to unsupported VMCS component.
|-
| 0x0D || VMWRITE to read-only VMCS component.
|-
| 0x0F || VMXON executed in VMX root operation.
|-
| 0x1A || VM entry with events blocked by MOV SS.
|}

== VMCS ==
The VMCS only has two relevant fields that can be accessed at this time, a 4-byte VMCS revision ID located at byte offset 0 and a 4-byte abort indicator field located at byte offset 4.  The rest of the VMCS is reserved for field data.

The revision field must be filled with the 32-bit revision Id stored in bits 0-31 of the IA32_VMX_BASIC MSR similar to the VMX region.

The abort field will simply contain a non-zero value if the VM abort occurs during a VMX exit, see section 23.7 in Intel's SDM 3B for error values.

A VMCS is loaded with the VMPTRLD instruction, which loads and activates a VMCS, and requires a 64-bit memory address as it's operand in the same format as VMXON/VMCLEAR.

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="c"&gt;
 asm volatile ("vmptrld %0; ":: "m" (vmcsRegion64));
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

The structure of the VMCS is covered in detail in Chapter 20 of the Intel SDM volume 3B (see link below).  Field encodings for VMWRITE and VMREAD are covered in Appendix H of the same manual.
== Peripheral Emulation ==
=== IO framework emulation ===
In x86, there are two kinds of IO channels: Port-Based IO(aka '''PIO''' ) and Memory-Mapped IO(aka '''MMIO'''). PIO has separate address space and special instructions to do IO jobs. while with MMIO, the device IO space is backed with the memory address space, you can use memory data move instructions to do IO jobs.
==== PIO emulation ====
with Intel VT-x, the hypervisor is able to determine whether the guest's IO instructions trap into vmx root mode by setting the primary processor based control bit 24. if this bit is set, all the guest's IO instructions will causes vm exits. otherwise, you have to setup the two IO bitmap regions to capture the vm exits you are interested in.

the IO causes vm exit with basic reason number as 30, you can retrieve the IO operation size, direction, port id and etc. for more please refer to the vmx_pio.c in reference pages.
==== MMIO emulation ====
MMIO emulation in x86 is a bit different: we are going to exploit EPT in order to capture MMIO events.
VMX provides two kinds of EPT involved vm exits: EPT violation and EPT misconfiguration.  In general, when guest is accessing memory which is not backed correctly(e.g. the memory is '''writable''' but '''not readable'''!), VMX results in vm exits with EPT misconfiguration. 
the hypervisor must do the following steps to do MMIO operation:
&lt;pre&gt;
 1). decode the memory move instruction to determine the memory involved instruction length, access size, direction, operations, registers index/immediates  and memory address,
 2). search the MMIO devices regions to see whether the address is backed with a DEVICE.
 3). store the result in destination  register if necessary.
 4). advance to next instruction by adding guest RIP with instruction length resolved in step 1.
&lt;/pre&gt;

=== Devices emulation examples===
{| {{wikitable}}
|-
! Device !! IO type !! Refference
|-
| Intel 8259 PIC || PIO ||https://github.com/chillancezen/ZeldaOS.x86_64/blob/master/vm_monitor/device_8259pic.c
|-
| Intel 8253 PIT || PIO ||https://github.com/chillancezen/ZeldaOS.x86_64/blob/master/vm_monitor/device_8253pit.c
|-
| Intel 8042 keyboard || PIO ||https://github.com/chillancezen/ZeldaOS.x86_64/blob/master/vm_monitor/device_keyboard.c
|-
| serial port controller || PIO ||https://github.com/chillancezen/ZeldaOS.x86_64/blob/master/vm_monitor/device_serial.c
|-
| 16-colors video controller || MMIO ||https://github.com/chillancezen/ZeldaOS.x86_64/blob/master/vm_monitor/device_video.c
|-
|}

== References ==
Intel's SDM 3B: http://www.intel.com/Assets/PDF/manual/253669.pdf 

Intel's SDM 2B: http://www.intel.com/Assets/PDF/manual/253667.pdf 

KVM's VMX.c (GPLv2): http://lxr.free-electrons.com/source/arch/x86/kvm/vmx.c 

BOCHS's VMX.c (LGPLv2): http://bochs.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/bochs/bochs/cpu/vmx.cc 

PIO sub handler: https://github.com/chillancezen/ZeldaOS.x86_64/blob/master/vm_monitor/vmx_pio.c

Memory move instruction decode: https://github.com/chillancezen/ZeldaOS.x86_64/blob/master/vm_monitor/vmx_instruction_decoding.c



== Other examples ==
Vmx implementation in home made OS:
http://www.dumais.io/index.php?article=ac3267239dd3e34c061de6413203fb98

[[Category:X86 Virtualization]]</text>
      <sha1>02te35eqrgcq7axh42adk3e0luh7jre</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>EM64T</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1895</id>
    <revision>
      <id>28117</id>
      <parentid>26403</parentid>
      <timestamp>2023-07-09T23:15:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Khaledhammouda</username>
        <id>1596</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>28117</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1250" sha1="fubplbmt1e0yn34tbngfcflkp6a8sru" xml:space="preserve">Intel Extended Memory 64 Technology ([http://www.intel.com/technology/64bitextensions/ Intel EM64T]) enables 64-bit computing on the server/workstation and desktop platforms when combined with supporting software. Intel EM64T improves performance by allowing the system to address more than 4 GB of both virtual and physical memory.

Technically speaking, EM64T offers to Intel processors what [[x86-64]] offers to AMD processors. Ancient disagreements such as 3Dnow-vs-MMX still holds, but the rest should be exactly the same. It is supported by latest XEON processors.

Intel EM64T provides support for:

* 64-bit flat virtual address space
* 64-bit pointers
* 64-bit wide general purpose registers (16 - added R8-R15)
* 64-bit integer support
* Up to 1 tebibyte (TiB)  of platform address space

Currently physical addresses are restricted to 40 bits, and linear addresses are restricted to 48 bits, sign-extended.

== See Also ==
=== Articles ===
* [[X86-64]]
* [[Creating a 64-bit kernel]]
* [[User:Stephanvanschaik/Setting_Up_Long_Mode|Setting up long mode]]

=== External Links ===
* [[Wikipedia:EM64T|EM64T]] on Wikipedia.
* [ftp://download.intel.com/design/Pentium4/manuals/25366816.pdf XEON manual]

[[Category:X86 CPU]]
[[Category:X86-64]]</text>
      <sha1>fubplbmt1e0yn34tbngfcflkp6a8sru</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Main</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>1400</id>
    <revision>
      <id>28974</id>
      <parentid>28971</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-06-06T17:21:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lukflug</username>
        <id>1762</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Kukuva|Kukuva]] ([[User talk:Kukuva|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Jhawthorn|Jhawthorn]]</comment>
      <origin>28974</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="30" sha1="4htdjonyh1mnibq1hoy668c2b6aenbn" xml:space="preserve">:''Main article:'' [[{{{1}}}]]</text>
      <sha1>4htdjonyh1mnibq1hoy668c2b6aenbn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:In Progress</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>1408</id>
    <revision>
      <id>22717</id>
      <parentid>10203</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-10T02:23:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Carver</username>
        <id>1397</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <origin>22717</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="385" sha1="ftpr7r4h0tkq0nkkfelfncbe3rebmps" xml:space="preserve">&lt;center&gt;
{|style="border: 1px solid #cfcfbf; margin-top: 25px; margin-bottom: 25px; background-color: #f0f0ff; text-align: center;"
|
[[image:Under_Construction.png|This page is under construction!]]
This page or section is a work in progress and may thus be incomplete. Its content may be changed in the near future.
|
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;includeonly&gt;[[Category:In Progress]]&lt;/includeonly&gt;</text>
      <sha1>ftpr7r4h0tkq0nkkfelfncbe3rebmps</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Stub</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>1513</id>
    <revision>
      <id>29006</id>
      <parentid>28998</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-06-06T17:30:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lukflug</username>
        <id>1762</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Kukuva|Kukuva]] ([[User talk:Kukuva|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Bellezzasolo|Bellezzasolo]]</comment>
      <origin>29006</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="393" sha1="mdiuzhhmobgskoueq6qyk7fzx70ykd2" xml:space="preserve">&lt;center&gt;
{|style="border: 1px solid #cfcfbf; margin-top: 25px; margin-bottom: 25px; background-color: #f0f0ff; text-align: center;"
|
[[image:Stub.png|This article is a stub!]]
This page or section is a [[:Category:Stubs|stub]]. You can help the wiki by ''accurately'' [{{fullurl:{{FULLPAGENAME}}|action=edit}} contributing] to it.
|
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;includeonly&gt;[[Category:Stubs]]&lt;/includeonly&gt;</text>
      <sha1>mdiuzhhmobgskoueq6qyk7fzx70ykd2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Eq</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>2085</id>
    <revision>
      <id>28982</id>
      <parentid>28977</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-06-06T17:23:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lukflug</username>
        <id>1762</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Kukuva|Kukuva]] ([[User talk:Kukuva|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Bellezzasolo|Bellezzasolo]]</comment>
      <origin>28982</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="35" sha1="1k5xsqdt4buw1jcs2d1xkmv4f2x02k0" xml:space="preserve">{{Eq1|_reserved={{{1}}}|{{{2}}}=1}}</text>
      <sha1>1k5xsqdt4buw1jcs2d1xkmv4f2x02k0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Eq1</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>2086</id>
    <revision>
      <id>12737</id>
      <parentid>12723</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-19T20:33:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bellezzasolo</username>
        <id>714</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>12737</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="22" sha1="eg0hatmudxlixoi3gelt09k4rtzd9wz" xml:space="preserve">{{{{{{_reserved}}}|}}}</text>
      <sha1>eg0hatmudxlixoi3gelt09k4rtzd9wz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:If</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>1558</id>
    <revision>
      <id>29029</id>
      <parentid>29016</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-06-06T20:16:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Klange</username>
        <id>720</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Protected "[[Template:If]]" ([edit=sysop] (indefinite) [move=sysop] (indefinite))</comment>
      <origin>29029</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="75" sha1="aohsf5znfbf9d03xxlbtfbziny1r07h" xml:space="preserve">{{show1
|1={{{2|{{{then|}}}}}}
|1{{{1|{{{test|}}}}}}={{{3|{{{else|}}}}}}
}}</text>
      <sha1>aohsf5znfbf9d03xxlbtfbziny1r07h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Show1</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>1557</id>
    <revision>
      <id>28994</id>
      <parentid>28989</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-06-06T17:27:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lukflug</username>
        <id>1762</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Kukuva|Kukuva]] ([[User talk:Kukuva|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Jhawthorn|Jhawthorn]]</comment>
      <origin>28994</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="7" sha1="cmn9dlq4osu63jqm4mfq9mfvdt3q6zw" xml:space="preserve">{{{1}}}</text>
      <sha1>cmn9dlq4osu63jqm4mfq9mfvdt3q6zw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Kernel designs</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>2388</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30814</id>
      <parentid>30634</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-06-23T19:26:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Demindiro</username>
        <id>1745</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Add rump kernel</comment>
      <origin>30814</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="575" sha1="2hgnc3090feu4gzrisj0sobxadbu39m" xml:space="preserve">{{SmallNavBox
| width:200px;
|Name=[[Kernels|Kernel Designs]]
|Group0=Models
|List0=&lt;div&gt;
[[Monolithic Kernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Microkernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Hybrid Kernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Exokernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Nanokernel|Nano/Picokernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Exokernel#Cache Kernel|Cache Kernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Exokernel#Virtualizing Kernel|Virtualizing Kernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Megalithic Kernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Multikernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
|Group1=Other Concepts
|List1=&lt;div&gt;
[[Modular Kernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Higher Half Kernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Creating a 64-bit kernel|64-bit Kernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Pre-kernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Rump kernel]]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
}}</text>
      <sha1>2hgnc3090feu4gzrisj0sobxadbu39m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:SmallNavBox</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>2325</id>
    <revision>
      <id>29007</id>
      <parentid>29004</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-06-06T17:30:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lukflug</username>
        <id>1762</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Kukuva|Kukuva]] ([[User talk:Kukuva|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Virtlink|Virtlink]]</comment>
      <origin>29007</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1558" sha1="rtpigzoqbue6156la3sodkfz9kw4psk" xml:space="preserve">&lt;table style="font-size:95%; line-height:1.5em; padding:0.25em; float:right; margin: 0 0 8px 15px; clear: right; border:1px solid #aaaaaa; background:#eee; text-align:center;{{{1|}}};"&gt;&lt;!--

--&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th style="background:#ffce7b; padding:0.3em; font-size:1.1em;"&gt;{{{Name}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;!--

--&gt;{{If|{{{List0|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group0}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{If|{{{List0|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List0}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--

--&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group1}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;!--
--&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List1}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;!--

--&gt;{{If|{{{List2|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group2}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{If|{{{List2|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List2}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--

--&gt;{{If|{{{List3|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group3}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{If|{{{List3|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List3}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--

--&gt;{{If|{{{List4|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group4}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{If|{{{List4|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List4}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--

--&gt;{{If|{{{List5|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group5}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{If|{{{List5|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List5}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--

--&gt;{{If|{{{List6|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group6}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{If|{{{List6|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List6}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--

--&gt;{{If|{{{List7|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group7}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{If|{{{List7|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List7}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--

--&gt;{{If|{{{List8|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group8}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{If|{{{List8|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List8}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--

--&gt;{{If|{{{List9|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group9}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{If|{{{List9|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List9}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--

--&gt;{{If|{{{List10|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;{{{Group10}}}&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{If|{{{List10|}}}|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{{{List10}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;|}}&lt;!--
--&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</text>
      <sha1>rtpigzoqbue6156la3sodkfz9kw4psk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Rating</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>2411</id>
    <revision>
      <id>28968</id>
      <parentid>28952</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-06-06T17:18:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lukflug</username>
        <id>1762</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Strokegmd|Strokegmd]] ([[User talk:Strokegmd|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Sortie|Sortie]]</comment>
      <origin>28968</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="833" sha1="flfcce2y6jpg2iglr4i1vcso2p8r7m1" xml:space="preserve">{{{2|[[Category:Level {{{1|{{{level|0}}}}}} Tutorials]]}}}&lt;table style="font-size:95%; line-height:1.5em; padding:0.25em; float:right; margin: 0 0 8px 15px; clear:right; border:1px solid #aaaaaa; background:#eee; text-align:center;{{{2|}}};"&gt;&lt;!--

--&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Difficulty level&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[Image:Difficulty {{{1|{{{level|0}}}}}}.png]]&lt;br /&gt;{{If|{{Eq|{{{1|{{{level|0}}}}}}|0}}|Not rated|{{If|{{Eq|{{{1|{{{level|0}}}}}}|1}}|Beginner|{{If|{{Eq|{{{1|{{{level|0}}}}}}|2}}|Medium|{{If|{{Eq|{{{1|{{{level|0}}}}}}|3}}|Advanced|Master}}}}}}}}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;!--

--&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;noinclude&gt;
Usage:
&lt;pre&gt;
{{Rating|3}}
{{Rating|3|}}
&lt;/pre&gt;
Use the following levels:
* 0 or not specified: Not rated
* 1: Beginner
* 2: Medium
* 3: Advanced
* 4: Master
Add an empty second parameter to prevent the article from being added to the category.
&lt;/noinclude&gt;</text>
      <sha1>flfcce2y6jpg2iglr4i1vcso2p8r7m1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:DiscussThis</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>4318</id>
    <revision>
      <id>22868</id>
      <parentid>22867</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-14T23:24:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Carver</username>
        <id>1397</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>22868</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="33" sha1="9zmxmow08u64io4l1mya1rj98d56j3d" xml:space="preserve">[[Talk:{{FULLPAGENAME}}|{{{1}}}]]</text>
      <sha1>9zmxmow08u64io4l1mya1rj98d56j3d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Disputed</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>1794</id>
    <revision>
      <id>22865</id>
      <parentid>12743</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-14T23:21:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Carver</username>
        <id>1397</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>22865</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="421" sha1="f3986rckgmjs171hy1tuf2zmatxb2tc" xml:space="preserve">&lt;center&gt;
{|style="border: 1px solid #cfcfbf; padding: .0em .25em .0em; background-color: #f0f0ff; text-align: center;"
|
&lt;font color="black"&gt;The factual accuracy of this article or section is [[:Category:Disputed Pages|disputed]].&lt;/font&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color="red"&gt;Please see the relevant discussion on the {{DiscussThis|talk page}}.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
|
|}
&lt;includeonly&gt;[[Category:Disputed Pages]]&lt;/includeonly&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;</text>
      <sha1>f3986rckgmjs171hy1tuf2zmatxb2tc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:No</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>1404</id>
    <revision>
      <id>16083</id>
      <parentid>1566</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-04-12T01:44:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Virtlink</username>
        <id>205</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>16083</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="40" sha1="a7vcpiwqzhkohdy01l8esqhrdme60gr" xml:space="preserve">style="background: #ffdddd" | {{{1|No}}}</text>
      <sha1>a7vcpiwqzhkohdy01l8esqhrdme60gr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Wikitable</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>1402</id>
    <revision>
      <id>28972</id>
      <parentid>28966</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-06-06T17:21:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lukflug</username>
        <id>1762</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Kukuva|Kukuva]] ([[User talk:Kukuva|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Lukflug|Lukflug]]</comment>
      <origin>28972</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="162" sha1="b22loeeedg5kcnq8li4x36nep1n17js" xml:space="preserve">border="2" cellpadding="4" cellspacing="0" style="margin-top:1em; margin-bottom:1em; background:#f9f9f9; border:1px #aaa solid; border-collapse:collapse; {{{1}}}"</text>
      <sha1>b22loeeedg5kcnq8li4x36nep1n17js</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Yes</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>1403</id>
    <revision>
      <id>28957</id>
      <parentid>28954</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-06-06T17:17:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lukflug</username>
        <id>1762</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Kukuva|Kukuva]] ([[User talk:Kukuva|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Jhawthorn|Jhawthorn]]</comment>
      <origin>28957</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="41" sha1="d1nn6dhmf47nengqckn7m58m24cjb70" xml:space="preserve">style="background: #ddffdd" | {{{1|Yes}}}</text>
      <sha1>d1nn6dhmf47nengqckn7m58m24cjb70</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:ACPI</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>4800</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30725</id>
      <parentid>29670</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-06-11T07:47:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sircmpwn</username>
        <id>917</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>30725</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="429" sha1="4apx0mmhwkj8ijlydgpq5sji6ejrnbr" xml:space="preserve">{{SmallNavBox
| width:200px;
|Name=[[ACPI]]

|Group0=
|List0=&lt;div&gt;
[[RSDP]]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

|Group1=Fixed Tables
|List1=&lt;div&gt;
[[BGRT]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[FADT]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[MADT]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[MCFG]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[RSDT]]/[[XSDT]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[SRAT]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[WAET]]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

|Group2=Differentiated Tables
|List2=&lt;div&gt;
[[DSDT]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[SSDT]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[AML]]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

|Group3=Tools/Libs
|List3=&lt;div&gt;
[[ACPICA]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[uACPI]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[LAI]]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
}}</text>
      <sha1>4apx0mmhwkj8ijlydgpq5sji6ejrnbr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Historical</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>4680</id>
    <revision>
      <id>26762</id>
      <timestamp>2021-12-19T06:45:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kazinsal</username>
        <id>994</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Created page with "&lt;center&gt; {|style="border: 1px solid #8f9f8f; padding: .0em .25em .0em; background-color: #d3cdbb; text-align: center;" | [[Image:HistoricalCuriosity.png]] | &lt;font color="black..."</comment>
      <origin>26762</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="396" sha1="dyc2noin0tp90vj9bmqohq2sklcqrxu" xml:space="preserve">&lt;center&gt;
{|style="border: 1px solid #8f9f8f; padding: .0em .25em .0em; background-color: #d3cdbb; text-align: center;"
|
[[Image:HistoricalCuriosity.png]]
|
&lt;font color="black"&gt;The content of this article or section is considered a historical curiosity and should not be considered for new designs.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
|
|}
&lt;includeonly&gt;[[Category:Historical Curiosities]]&lt;/includeonly&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <sha1>dyc2noin0tp90vj9bmqohq2sklcqrxu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:NoteBox</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>4305</id>
    <revision>
      <id>22788</id>
      <parentid>22742</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-10T04:40:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Carver</username>
        <id>1397</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>22788</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="154" sha1="0myhusmy8xxz7pbkgklp48dl1bquc97" xml:space="preserve">&lt;center&gt;
{|style="border: 1px solid #cfcfbf; margin-top: 25px; margin-bottom: 25px; background-color: #f0f0ff; text-align: center;"
|
{{{1}}}
|}
&lt;/center&gt;</text>
      <sha1>0myhusmy8xxz7pbkgklp48dl1bquc97</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Tone</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>4021</id>
    <revision>
      <id>22744</id>
      <parentid>20292</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-10T03:18:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Carver</username>
        <id>1397</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>22744</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="276" sha1="8uk26fcvc97frc989g6xd4k03nx2avg" xml:space="preserve">{{NoteBox|This article's '''tone or style''' may not reflect the encyclopedic tone used throughout the wiki. See [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Writing_better_articles#Tone Wikipedia's article on tone] for suggestions.}}

&lt;includeonly&gt;[[Category:Tone]]&lt;/includeonly&gt;</text>
      <sha1>8uk26fcvc97frc989g6xd4k03nx2avg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:AdmonitionNote</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>5036</id>
    <revision>
      <id>30617</id>
      <parentid>30614</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-05-24T14:48:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tocariimaa</username>
        <id>2217</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>add "note" text</comment>
      <origin>30617</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="129" sha1="faletokqzq82wcmhnpiqhpbgzdmx2lg" xml:space="preserve">&lt;div style="border-left: 4px solid #f0a500; background:#fff8e6; padding: 8px 12px; margin: 8px 0;"&gt;
'''Note:''' {{{text}}}
&lt;/div&gt;</text>
      <sha1>faletokqzq82wcmhnpiqhpbgzdmx2lg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
